hey folks
mike and nicole here with the pragmatic studio
you could do a bunch of cool things
with the elixir programming language
from building web apps using the Phoenix framework
to embedding code on network devices
and is tempting just to jump right
into these and hope for the best
but elixir is a functional concurrent language
and it requires a
different way of thinking to enter these new worlds
in this course
you'll learn how to develop with elixir confidently
for smooth settling
now if you're coming from an oo programming background
making the transition to functional programming can
be a bumpy ride
but the good thing is
it isn't the syntax that's going to throw you
in fact if you're a ruby programmer
a lot of elixir syntax is going to feel familiar
what's different is how you think
about programming in o
programs you're thinking revolves around objects
whose state you can modify by calling methods
but in elixir all data is immutable
so you think more in terms of transforming data
with functions
an http web server is a great
example of the elixir way of doing things
at a high level
a web server just takes a request and
through some series of transformations
produces a response
and it turns out
that building a simple web server is a great
way to learn elixir
as it requires us
to use a whole
bunch of elixir features and functional design concepts
and by incrementally building
this app throughout the course
you'll gain practical experience with elixir
and learn how all the pieces fit together
to develop a complete elixir app
as an added bonus
if you're planning to use the Phoenix web framework
you'll have a better
understanding of how it's designed
so without further delay let's get started