in the last module we handled an about page
and I can imagine having routes for other static pages
maybe a contact page or an f page
yeah and to serve each of those pages
we'd first
need to get the absolute path to the pages directory
as we did with the about page
so to share this bit of code
we could extract it into a function
but the path to the pages directory is a constant
which gives us an opportunity to learn something
new about modules
modules can have attributes
module attributes are defined at the
top level of a module
and in general
you can use module attributes to associate metadata
with the module
for example elixir has
two reserved module attributes
for documenting modules and functions
the documentation for a module goes at the
top of the module
and the name of the module attribute is module dock
and you notice it starts with an at sign
that indicates that it's a module attribute
and then because it's documentation
we can give it a string
so say handles http requests
now you can use it here
doc
and add a bunch more documentation here in the string
but I'm going to just keep it really
simple for this screencast
because you really don't want to watch me
typing in documentation
so that documents the module
there's also a module attribute called at doc
that document the function underneath it
so this one might be transforms
the request
into a response
and the same attribute can be set
multiple times in a module
so to document this function
we would also use the
dock module attribute and then the string might be
logs four or four requests
and then using these well defined attributes
elixir can access the values to generate documentation
so elixir has
reserved attributes for documentation purposes
and we can add
arbitrary or custom module attributes as well
yeah another common use of module attributes is as
constants and that's exactly what we have
down here
we can take this and make it a consonant
so I'm just going to copy it and the module attribute
it just has to be defined at the top level of module
but you can put it anywhere
and so we can call this one pages path
and then the value will be
the result of that expression
then down in our pipeline
instead of doing this
we can just read that value at pages path
and if we had
other route functions that needed to read page files
while they could use the pages path attribute
what's also nice
is that using a constant lets us easily change
the location of the page
directory in one place
so if we run it now we see that it works
now I said that you can add module attributes
anywhere in the top level of module
but I generally put constants at the top of a module
because their value is set at compile time
so I'm going to take this out of here
and we'll just put it right up here
under the module dock
just like that
so now any function defined below this point
can read the value