we currently have all of our functions to find
in a single module
and
we've been fairly disciplined about grouping together
functions that have similar concerns
but we know from experience
that having them all
in one module is going to become a bit unruly
yeah it's getting a bit wild already in this one module
but we generally start with everything in one module
and then once we see clusters of similar functions
well
then we'll organize those in a properly named module
so let's do some function wrangling
in our pipeline
we have some functions that we plug in
to map certain requests and responses and then
modify the conversation in various ways
so for example we have rewrite path log and then track
we want to put those in a new module
so I'm just going to cut out the definitions of those
functions right here
and then at the top I'm going to define a new module
naming is
always the hardest part of creating a new module
let's just call this plugins
it's going to be service plugins
and a single elixir file can define multiple module
so we're just going to put these modules in the same
file now don't let this dot character throw you here
when I first saw this module naming scheme like this
I assumed it implied some hierarchical relationship
between the survey module and the plugins module
but in fact there is no implied relationship
all modules are defined
at the top level
using dots just gives us a simple convenient way
to express a name space
now I've got those functions in my copy paste buffer
so I'm just going to
paste those inside of the module like that
and then we can close
this up in sublime
just to give us a little bit more room
I said that the module acts as a name
space so to call the functions
we need to use the module name
so when we call rewrite path we have to say survey
plugins rewrite path
the same way before calling log
we have to prefix it with the module name
and the same thing for track
if we save this away
and it looks like we haven't broken anything
prefixing the function names with the module names is
explicit however
module names can get fairly long
and it's tedious to type the name of the module before
every function name
thankfully there's a couple options to deal with this
one approach is to import the module
to do that we just go up above the function
at the top level of the module and we say import
survey plugins
and that's going to import those functions
into the current name space
the survey handler name space
so now we can get rid of
this prefix on all these functions here
if we save that away well that should work too
however importing functions this way is a bit cavalier
because it imports all the functions
which can lead to ambiguity
now it's not a big deal in this case
because we're only dealing with a handful of functions
but instead of importing the entire module
we could be more selective and
only import the functions we need
and we do that by using the option only
and then we give it a list and we can say
okay we want the rewrite
path function that takes one argument
we also want the log function that takes one argument
and the track function that takes one argument
and doing it this way just makes it more explicit
where those functions are defined
note here that the number
is the functions airily
or the number of arguments it takes
it's not the number of functions with that name
so this imports all five of our functions
we save that away
well it works just as well
now we started by saying we didn't want all of our
functions in one module
and in the same way
we don't want all of our modules in one file
and it turns out it's super easy to do
so let's cut the plugins module
and we'll put it in a separate file
I'm going to open up the sidebar here
and in our lib survey directory
we'll just create a new file and we'll call it plugins
ex
and then I'll just paste in that module
now if we save that away and I also
save handler ex
and I try to run this in sublime
where we get this air module
service plugins is not loaded and
could not be found
in the same way
if we're over on a command line in our top level
survey directory
and we try to run the elixir command on our handler
ex file well we get this same error it can't find
survey plugins
and that's because in either case it doesn't have
the code path setup
for a mixed project
so at this point we need to run it as a mix application
and to do that we're going to fire up fix
but we're going to do it
in the context of our application
by using sex dash capital s and mix
and then it went ahead
and compiled and loaded all the modules in our project
and then it interpreted any code outside of a module
so we see the same output we used to see
in the sublime build window
it's just printing out the results of
running our request through our handler
and if we want to recompile and
reload the survey module
well we can always use the r helper functions
we just say r
servi handler
so it recompiled the module and reloaded it
and
also interpreted the code that's outside of the module
so this is a way for us to run our handler module
while we're at it
the parse function does a necessarily feel at home
living in the handler module
so let's take the parse function
and we'll create a new parser ex file
and then we'll define a module survey parser
and we'll paste our parse function into it
then back in our handler we need to import that
so up here we need to import it
just like we did with plugins
I'm going to say import
see parser
and it only has one function
it's called parse with an ability of one
now back over nine
ex if we try to recompile our handler module as we did
before while we get this familiar error module
service parser is not loaded and could not be found
because it doesn't know about the parser module
so at this point we can either restart the sex session
or we can recompile the entire application
using recompile
that's a helper function
it doesn't take any arguments but
you need to use parentheses
otherwise you'll get a warning there
and it recompile the application and we get the
familiar output from our handler
coming up we'll define
another module that happens to be an elixir structure
and use another technique to reference modules
the alias