we're currently using a map
to represent our conversation
and maps are a generic data structure
we can add arbitrary keys and values to maps
but our conversation has some implied constraints
it has a fixed set of fields with default values
and since it's the central data structure of our app
it flows through the entire pipeline
we'd like to give it a bit more structure
and that's exactly what a structure gives us
now a structure needs to live in its own
module and we'll put it in its own file too
under lib survey will create a new file
and we'll call it con
ex
and then inside of that we'll define our co n module
service nv
then to define a structure within that module we use
def structure
and we pass it a keyword list it looks like this
square brackets
and then inside of there
we list the fields of this structure
so one of them is method
that's the name of the field
and then we can give it default values
this one's just going to be an empty string
same way with path
response body is also empty
and then we have a status field
and we'll default that to nil
keyword lister
commonly used to pass options to a function
or in this case an elixir macro
since the keyword list is the last
and only argument
we can actually remove the square brackets
so what's the name of this structure
well it's the same as the name of the module servey
co and v that's why a structure must live in a module
and you can't define
more than one struck
per module so let's save that
away and we'll fire up an ix session
just to get a feel
for how the s works
I'm inside of the top level survey directory
and I'm going to use fix
s mix so that we're running this as a mix application
and you notice it interpreted that
code that was outside of the module
so
I'm just going to clean this up and go back to the top
so you probably remember how we create a map
we just use per cent and then curly braces like that
well similarly we can create a structure
by using % curly braces
but
between the two of them we put the name of the struck
so it's servey co n
and we notice the result is a strict
it's got these
fixed fields inside of it with their default values
now we can also create the structure and supply
values to override those defaults
so if we wanted to override method
we would just say method
would be get
and maybe the path would be slash bears for example
and you notice the method is now get
and the path is bears
and then we have the default values
for the remaining fields
now unlike a map we can't create a structure with
a field that's not in the keyword list like
name is mike
now you'd probably
never just add a spurious field like this
but if you're like me
then you're likely to miss type of field
like maybe you forget the o and method
yeah what's nice here is
the constraint is checked at compile time
so misspelled field names won't slip through
for example now let's get rid of all this red
and we'll just go back to the version
that had this spelled right
and we can access fields of the structure
just like accessing a map
using dot notation
so if we want to look at the method
or we want to look at the path
well it's the familiar dot notation
we're used to with a map
but unlike maps the square bracket syntax won't work
so we try to do this
well we get an error message
so you can say that structures have stricter access
since they don't allow dynamic access
using square brackets like maps do
for example we still have our map loaded up in ix here
and if I would try to access
the age key of that map
well it just returns nil
but if we try to do the same
thing with our co and v struck
well we get an actual error rather than returning nil
so again with a struck we get compile time checking
which often saves your bacon
now updating a structure is similar to updating a map
for example
let's say we wanted to update the status code to 200
we'll use this familiar syntax we say co and v
a vertical bar and then status of 200
then we see the status has been updated
it follows then that we can also pattern match struts
so I have my co and v struck on the
right hand side
and I want to write a pattern on the left hand
side that matches it
well it would be servey
co and v and if I just use method as get
looks like that
well that'll match because this is a co n struck
and it certainly has a
field method with a value of get
and we don't care what else is in there
because remember on the left hand side
we don't have to give all the fields to get a match
in the same way we could match it against a status
of 200 for example
and no surprise
we can also extract values in the pattern match
as we've already learned
yeah I'll just use the variable method right there
and that's a match
and if we look at method well it's bound to the string
get so using a structure feels a lot like using a map
and in fact a strict instance
is just a special kind of map
with a thick set of keys and default values
and we can kind of test that there's a function in
elixir called is map
if we pass at co and v it returns sure enough
so it follows
then if we were to go back to this form here
where we've got a struck on the right
but then we remove this on the left
so that this is just a plain old map
well that'll match because we know that a structure
is a map and this is a map on the left hand side
it has a key of method and a value of get
which this structure certainly has
and so that's a match
so what about the converse
if we have this strict pattern on the left hand side
and then over here on the right hand side
if we just give it a plain old map
that has the key method
and the value get
well that doesn't match because a map
isn't a structure
so what's the big deal here
maps are structures do we really care
indeed we do because by pattern matching on a structure
we can be sure
we're always working with the expected type of map
not just any old map
which makes our application code more robust
so back in our app
let's first change
how the map is initialized in our parser
yeah right now
we're just initializing it as a plain old elixir map
but we want it to be a seal and v s
we're just going to move that down
and then because we provided
default values for these
two fields when we define the structure
well we don't need to do this here
so basically what we're going to do is just
override the method path
with whatever's in the method path variables
so you might think of this as like a typed map
if we save that away
then back over an ix if we say recompile
well
you might be surprised to see that that still works
and that's because if we look at handler
and all these functions in our pipeline
that take this plain old map
while we know
that if this is a structure on the right hand side
it will match a map on the left hand side
back over and parser
we'll need to refer to this structure in other places
and it's tedious
to type survey
con every time
so instead we can set up an alias for the name
to do that at the top of the module we just use alias
we want to alias the serve
v module and then we can give it a name
we say as colon that's an option
and we want to refer to it as just
co and v and then down here we can remove this prefix
defining aliases
this way is so common that there's a shortcut
if we drop the as coal and option
then we get an alias that's the last part of the name
and that should work
and it does
one of the benefits of modeling
our conversation is a struck as compared to a map is
we can ensure that all the functions in our pipeline
always get the expected type
in other words we get type safety
let's start on our plugins module
in first we're going to alias service co and v
so we don't have to use the full prefix
and then down here instead of a plain old map
we want it to be a co and v struck
and we want to do the same thing here
notice we don't really care what's in this structure
so a way to do that is just to say c
and then just open close curly braces equals
and that guarantees that this is a cnv struck
we don't care what's inside of it
but we do care that it's that typed map
we'll go ahead and change this one
and we'll do the same thing down here
and I'll just take that
and we want to do this exact same thing
for log so now these functions will
only match if this argument is rco and b struck
they won't match if it's a plain old map
and putting this here also makes it clear
just when you look at the function head
that these functions only accept co and v instances
so in a way it's sort of a form of documentation
we need to make similar changes in the handler module
again we'll start by aliasing it
and then we'll need to update the route patterns here
so this is going to be co and v
and I'm just going to copy this
because we have a few of these
we've got to paste this into
and then down below
we also have this format response
and we want that to be
just any co and v struck
if we save that away should still work
now it's common for a structure to be the
only thing defined within a module
and that's what we have right now
however when you start modeling entities
of your domain as structures
as we did with the conversation
you often end up defining functions that go hand
in hand with the struck
and it makes sense to define those
functions in the same
module as the struck
as a simple example
if we look at this format response function
we have this string right here being interpreted
and there's two parts to it
well
we can tidy that up by defining a function in the co
and v module that returns the full status string
so I'm just going to cut this out of here
and we want it to look like this
on the co and v module
we want to be able to call a function
full status and then we'll just pass in co and v
then if we go over to that
module that has our structure defined
well we can add functions down
here so we can define our full status function here
and this is just going to return a
concatenated string and I'm just going to paste in
what I cut from over there
so it just interpolates
those two things the status and the reason
and returns a full status string
now for this to work
it needs to call this status reason function
so we need to move it over from handler as well
we'll just grab it from over here
and then just paste it down here
and we'll keep it as a private function
since it's only called by this function
and we don't really need to expose this
as a public function
so now we have a module that defines one struck
and two functions
and thankfully it still works
we'll see another
example of a structure in an upcoming video