let's look at a different kind of request
a post request for creating new things
maybe new bears or any other new resource
now to handle a post request
we have to take into account the request headers
as well as the posted parameters
and this turns out to be a neat example of traversing
and processing lists
we'll see a new type of pattern match and
even a bit of recursion
and in the end
you'll be able to make heads and tails of it
we already have the post request heat up down
here in handler
so the method is post
and then we're just posting the slash bears
and when the form is posted
the form content is encoded in the post request body
which is this last
line right here
and you see that it's just a set of name value pairs
separated by an ampersand
and then the names are separated from the values by
an equal sign
and we have a starting point for the route function
already defined
since there's nothing new to learn here
and I've pasted the last
line of the request up here as a comment
just so we remember what it looks like
our goal here is to parse the last line of the request
into a param's map that looks like this
yeah we'll just have
the keys match up with the keys here
and the values match up with the values
so this is just a map
that represents this post prim string
we can then access the values in the map
and use them in the response body
to pronounce something like
created a whatever the bear type is
named the bear's name
obviously this
works because the para are hard coated for now
so we're going to need to make it dynamic
now we know this doesn't actually create
a bear in the database
we get it you could
actually do whatever you want
with a bear at this point
but that's sort of outside of our scope right now
we're going to stay focused instead
on how our web server handles post request in general
so let's look back
over at how we're parsing the request
over in parser
we have the parse function here
and we're taking the request
and we're splitting the request lines
and then we're just parsing the first
line which is the request line
well let's look at our post request again
over in handler
well here's the request line right here
which we're parsing at our parts function
but we also need to parse the last line of the request
this is the request body
so that we can create that param's map
so one way to do this would be to
split the request in the lines
and then use list at last
to get that last line the body
but thinking ahead
we ultimately want to restructure the request
into three parts that we can work
with the request line which is a string
the body which is a string of para
and then the header lines
because this content type here
will impact
how we ultimately parts the para in the next module
so we'll start by splitting the top two
parts from the param string
and that's easy to do because there's two consecutive
end characters right here and here
so back over and parer let's go ahead and do that
we'll use string split
we're going to take the whole request
and we're going to split it
on a double new line
and that's going to return a
list with two elements so we can pattern match on it
the first element is the request line in the headers
which I'm just going to put in a variable called top
and then the
second element is going to be our prem string
that's the last line of the request
so now we have the prom string
which is what we were aiming for
but we lost our request line while we can get it back
by splitting top rather than request
yeah right here we'll just use top
and then we're going to split it into its lines
that's going to be the request
lines and the header lines
but we only care about the first one
and we split it to get the individual parts
the method the path and
the protocol which we don't care about
if we save that away
and we run it
and it still works so we haven't broken anything
but here's the problem
looking back at the post request
we know we're parsing this line
but we need these remaining lines
the header lines to be in a list of their own
so that we have three distinct parts to work with
and it turns out
we can write a pattern to match a request line
followed by any number of header lines
to demonstrate how we're going to do that
let's play around with a simple list of numbers in six
now we know that we can match and destruct the list
by putting a pattern on the left hand side
so if numbs is on the right hand side
our pattern is going to look like this
let's say we want to capture these in variables ABCD
and e
well the value of a is one value b is going to be two
all the way through to e which has a value of five
but suppose we want the first
element of the list to be a value
and then the remaining elements to be a list
well a list has a head and a tail
which we can extract through pattern matching
using something called the cons operator
it looks like this here's the pattern head vertical bar
tail
and then the right hand side we have our numbers list
now if we look at the value of head it's one the
value of tail is a list
with the values two through five
so what follows then that if the tail is a list itself
then it has a head and a tail as well
which means we can use the same pattern match
so if I just go back up here
and put tail on the right hand side
well now the value of head is two
the value of tail is a list three four and five
there's no magic to the naming hair
in fact head and tail are often abbreviated as h and t
respectively the cons operator the vertical bar
here it's the special sauce
so let's go ahead and continue traversing the list this
way
now the value of head is three
tail is four and five
now heads four
and tail is a single element list five
now here's where things get interesting
now the head is the value five
and the tail is an empty list
so the tail of the final element of any list is
always an empty list
so now what happens if we do this
well that's not going to match because tail
is an empty list
and that doesn't match a head and a tail
so a list is either empty
or it consists of a head and a tail
and the tail is itself a list which could be empty
and we've seen how we can traverse a list recursively
now we'll come back to this recursive
part a little bit later
coming back to our post request
for now
we want to write a pattern that gives us this request
line and then gives us these header lines as a list
so this is going to be the head
and this is going to be the tail
so let's go back over to our parser
so remember that the request line in the headers are in
top
so once we have the top
we're going to split it
just on new lines
now that's going to return a list
so we want a pattern match over here
that gives us the head and the tail
well the head is the request line
so we'll put in a variable request line
use our vertical bar
and then the tail we want header lines
then we can change how we parse the request line
into its three parts
instead of doing it this way
we can simplify this quite a bit
we just say string split on the request line
and we split that by a space
to get the three parts of that request line
save that away
now back over an ix if we recompile that
well it looks like we haven't broken anything
but we have the bonus of having the request destruct
into three parts
so now we need to parse the param string
so we get the name and the type of the bear dynamically
well there's no need to reinvent the wheel
here
elixir has a function for decoding this query string
in the uri module
there's a function called decode query
and then I've got the query string right here
that's the last line of our request
and what's great about this function is
it returns a map
where the keys and the values
are the same thing that are in the query string
now you might be tempted to convert the
keys from strings
to atoms and
using atoms as keys is generally a pretty good idea
however in this case it's dangerous
because these
strings are coming from outside of our application
and since atoms aren't garbage collected in elixir
if we convert them to atoms
well we can run out of memory
now back over in our parser
we can define a function
that will decode this param string
just going to put it right down here
and I'll call it parse para
that's going to take in our param string
and I'm just going to use a pipeline here
there's a new line at the end of that param string
so I want to trim that off
I'll use string trim to do that
and then we can use that function we used in ix uri
decode query
and remember this is going to return a map of the para
and then up here in pars
we'll call that function
and we're going to assign the result to
a variable called paras
just going to be parsed para
and passing in that pram string
then once we have the prams we want the prams map
to be part of the conversation
so we'll just add a feel down here prams
and set it to that variable
so let's save that away and give it a try
we'll recompile our application
ooh and we get an air message
it's saying the key paras was not found in survey
com which remembers a s
don't you just love it when a plan comes together
yeah we set up this structure to get
type safety and that's exactly what it gave us
we need to add a field to the struck
so I'm going to put these on separate lines
and then we'll add the field paras
and we're going to default it just to an empty map
now let's see what happens if we save that
away in recompile
so it turns out we get another error
but it doesn't have to do with our code
it looks like recompile just didn't pick up the change
so I restarted ix and everything's now running
and we see that we have the prams in our logger output
so now we just need to use these
prams in our route function
that's back over in our handler module
and we have this hard coated prams right here
well we don't need that anymore
instead we can just use
come
dot params because that's the new field that we added
and the same thing right here
save that away
and now if we recompile this
well sure enough we get created a brown bear named ball
so our para are no longer hard coated
but the way we did this it's a bit presumptuous
and we'll see why in the next section