in the last section we assume that we
always get post parameters in the same format
but that's not always the case
let's have a look at this post request
again
in the last section we hinted that this content type
was kind of important
when the content type is set to this value
it means that the body is a query string
encoded in this name
value pair format that we see down here
so the content type effectively tells us how to parse
the request body
now you can also post data encoded differently
so it's important to check the content type
to determine how to parse the body
to do that we need to parse all of these headers
and we
already have them right now as a list of strings
so we've added a bit of logging so that we can see that
so here is our headers as a list of strings
but transforming this into a map with key value pairs
well that would be so much more useful
so to set this up over in our co and v struck
similar to how we have para as a field
and it has a default value of empty map
what we want to do the same thing with headers
so we'll have a headers field
and it'll also default to an empty map
and then over in the parse function similar to prams
we need to parse our headers
so we'll have headers equals
and we're going to write a function called
parse headers
and it's going to pass in
header lines which remember is a list of strings
then once we have those
parsed down when we initialize our co and v struck
while we want to set that field headers
to be the value of that header's variable
so of course we need to define this function
and I'll just do this
right down here
takes in the headers lines
and ultimately this is going to need to return a
map of the headers
so how are we going to do that
well let's look at that request again
so the conventional way to do this would be to
loop through these header lines
which is a list
pars each line into a key value pair
so for example
this line the key would be host and the value would be
example com
and then accumulate those key value pairs
in the headers map
but here's the thing though
there are no conventional looping constructs in elixir
but remember in the last section when we saw that
list our recursive data structures
I've recreated our sex session from the prior video
and we started with a list of numbs
and remember that we used the head and tail
pattern match with that cons operator
to traverse through this list
so the first time the head had a value of one
and then tail was a list itself
and then we use tail on the right hand side
and then the value of head was two
and tail was three four and five
and so on all the way down to the point where tail
was a one element list
we then matched it against that pattern
and head was the element five
but tail was an empty list
so by pattern matching tail each time
we recursively walked through each element of the list
here's a simple program that does the same thing
it's in a standalone file called recurred
ex it's not in a mixed project
and you can find
it in the code bundle if you want to follow along
so it just defines a module called recurse
it has a function called loopy
and then we call loopy down here and we pass it a
list of numbers one through five
that matches the pattern
that's the argument in this loopy function
which gives us the head and the tail
we print out the head print out the tail
and then here's the key part
we call loopy on itself here
passing in the tail which is that remaining list
in other words it's recursive and if we run it
well we get the same output
we got in ix just in a little bit
different format
so you see that it's just
walking through the list recursively
pulling off the head and the tail
until finally we get
to the point where the tail is an empty list
but what about this function clause air
well remember
the tail of the final element of any list is
always an empty list
so when it loops with tail being an empty list
the pattern doesn't match
yeah
so we need a function clause that matches that pattern
which will effectively terminate the recursion
I'm just going to paste one in
so it's loopy
with an empty list
and when this function is called
because that pattern matches while we know the worth
the end so we just print out done
say that away
run it again well sure enough it prints out done
when we've walked through the entire list
so there are three ingredients that make this work
the first one is these multi claws functions
this is called the terminating claws here
the second is we do pattern matching on
the head and the tail
this is the pattern up until the list is empty
and then we match on the empty list
to know that we're done
and the final ingredient of course is recursion
we're looping back on ourself
so to loop through the header lines we can recurs
the same way with two function clauses
that's going to happen over in our parser
and right now our parsed headers function
takes one argument these header lines
but we're going to change this
around to match a pattern
it's going to be
head and tail
and then just like with the recursive numbers we need
to call the parse headers function as the last
line of this function here
and we're going to pass in the tail
remember just like we did an ix and that program
we keep
matching on the tail until we get to the end of it
and then above this line
I'm just going to add a little bit of debug
just so we can see what's going on
and I'm using the inspect function on these lists
just
because it'll print out the raw form of these lists
and then we also have these labels head and tail
around it
we also need a second function clause when our
list returns empty
yeah it's just parse headers
it's going to be the empty list
and in this case we'll print out
done just like we did before
so now if we save that away
and we recompile
we scroll back up just to see what that debug gave us
well the first time through the head is
this host line and the tail is all the remaining lines
then the second time through
it's the second thing in the list
and the tail is everything else
and it just walks through until finally
the head is the last line content length
and the tail is an empty list
and it matches the empty list and we get back done
so the next question is
what do we want to do for each head and tail
well we really don't
care about the tail
but for each head
we want to parse it into a key value pair
and we know how to parse a string
and match the returned list
yeah I'll just do it down below this debugging
just give it a little bit of space here
our pattern is going to be a key in a value
and we'll take string split
split the head
and the dilemma here is a colon and a space
and then I want to add a little bit more logging
so I'm just going to copy this
and we'll do it
after we have the key in the value
I'm just going to change these around
this will be our key
and this will be our value
now if we save that away
come back over here and recon pilot again
and scroll up here
all right head host example
com and notice we have key
well the key is host and the value is example
com similarly when we have the head being this
user agent line
while the key is user agent
and the value is
whatever the value of that in the header is
so we're successfully parsing this string the head
into key value pairs
so the next thing we want to do is put
the key value pairs in the header's map
so I'll do that right below this line
we'll have variable headers like I did before
I took it out a little bit earlier
but we'll put it back in here
and then we want to make a map
so we're going to use the map modules put function
we're going to start off with an empty map
and then we'll add the key and the value to that map
and just to give a little bit more debug
we'll do io inspect
on those headers
so let's run it again
so here's the head and tail output
here are our key value pairs and then we have a map
host is the key example
com as the value
if we look down at this one here's our head and tail
here's the key value
and then we have a map with user agent as the key
but it's a new map
every time yeah this one has one key value
this one has one key value
if we keep looking through here
it's always one key in value
we need a way to remember the header's map and add
to it each time through the loop
because we want all the header information
to end up in a single map
in other words we need a way to maintain state
and there's only one way to do that
and that's to take the state
a map in our case
and pass it as an argument to the recursive function
before we do that
let's get rid of this debugging just to clean this up
so we can see what's going on
then we're going to change
the function claws to take a second argument
and we're going to call it headers
and then instead of calling map
put passing in an empty map as the first argument here
we want to pass in headers
because we want to add the key and the value
to this header's map
then here's the key part
when we recursively call parse headers
we need to pass in headers as that 2nd argument
likewise we need to change our termination claws to
also take headers
now when this termination claws runs
it means worth the end of the list
so instead of printing out done
we just want to return that headers map
and it should have all the key value pairs in it
now don't forget
we need to update the function call
to pass in an empty map
as the second argument
so we start out with an empty map
yeah it's this call right here
it's just passing in header lines
but we know we have to take two arguments
so we're just going to start this off with
an empty map
so just to walk through this we call parts headers
passing in an empty map that comes down here
matches head and tail
and then
we go through there accumulating
all the keys and values into this header's map
passing it back to itself
until finally Bing
we get the final header map returned from parse headers
so now if we save this away
come back over and recompile
we'll check it out
here's our co and v structure and it has a headers
field and the value of that field is a map
containing all of our headers
now
if you've done recursion like this in other languages
you might be concerned that recurring this way
with a large enough list could consume a lot of memory
and blow up the call stack
but because the last
thing the function does is call itself
elixir uses something called tail call optimization
no new frames are pushed onto the call stack
so it consumes no additional memory
in other words this is really efficient in elixir
so now that we've collected all the headers
we can return to our original problem
if the content type matches this
then we can proceed with the parsing we
already have in parse parts
but if not then we'll ignore
the request body or the param string altogether
and to do that
we're going to use
multi claws functions in pattern matching
so what we'll do is we'll change
this function to
take the content type as the first argument
and that way we can pattern match on it
and then when we call parsh para which happens up here
well we'll pass it the value that's in the headers map
associated with the key
content type
so if the content type is this application
x wow form url encoded
well we want to decode it
using that I code query function
but we also need to define a
default clause for all other content types
so it's going to be called pars para
and we don't really care what the content type is
and we don't even care about the param string
because if we fall through to this level
well we're just going to return an empty map
because we're going to match this one
and we're going to handle it the way we know how
by decoding it
but for everything else
well we don't know how to deal with that
so we're just going to return an empty map
now if we save this away it should run just as it did
before
and indeed it does
but let's change the content type of our post request
let's make it a multi part slash form data
if we run it now
we see that the para is empty just as expected
yeah
this is another content type that web servers handle
but it's a lot more complicated and
there's really nothing new to teach about
elixir by implementing that
plus it probably takes a long time to do
so I'm just going to set it back
and say that we just handle this content type
recursion is a basic building block of elixir
and you'll see it used extensively
but you won't often use it to
traverse and process the list as we did
yeah this kind of code is so common
that the e new module provides convenience functions
for manipulating lists
providing a really nice abstraction from the details
but under the hood the e new functions are implemented
using recursion
we'll have a look at the e new module coming up next