as our app stands now
when we get a request for slash bears
we respond with this simple string
but this being a web server in all
we really should respond with some html
yeah and we'll do that
by using
some of the transformation functions that are in the e
new module
but let's start off by organizing our code to look
more like a web framework that follows the nvc pattern
such as Phoenix or rails
typically in a web framework
the routes would simply dispatch or
delegate to a controller
yeah we can do that
we'll define a new controller over here
new file and we're going to call it bare controller
we'll set up the module
it's going to be survey bare controller
save that away
and then we're going to use that back
over in our handler module
so at the top of a handler I'm going to alias that in
and then we want to use that in the
bears route right here
so I'm just going to cut this line out
and instead we'll call bear controller
and we'll assume we're going to have a
function called index
and then we're going to pass in that co and v map
that way
the function can update it and return a new copy
so then back
over in our bare controller we just need to find index
it takes co and v
and I'm going to paste in what I cut out from the
other file we want to do a similar thing
for the bare slash one route
we want to delegate it to a show function
yeah so I'll cut this out of here
this is going to be bare controller
dot show
we'll pass it cunt
and it's also going to need that id
so we'll pass it as the second parameter
then over in the controller
we'll set up show
see one v in the id and I'll paste that in
so this will work
but there's another way to do it
as opposed to passing in an id like this
what if we wanted to package up that id
with the other parameters because id's really just a
request parameter
so what we want to do is merge it
into the existing parameters
and you'll remember that those are in co and v paras
so let's do it this way
param's equals map put
we'll take co and v paras and we'll add to it
a key called id
and the id value
and then we'll turn around and pass that as the second
parameter to our show function
and if we do that back over here in show
then instead of taking id this is going to be a map
and we can just pattern match on it
so we want to extract the value of the id like that
and then we reference id right here
so this will work just as well
just gives us a little bit more flexibility
we can take the entire prams map
and then do some pattern matching
figure out what's inside of there
you can imagine that there might be
other parameters being set further up the pipeline
so this just gives the action all the parameters
and it can figure out what to do with those
so we have one more to go
for the post route we want to delegate to a create
function
this would be bare controller
create
pass it co and v
and it's going to need the posted parameters
so we're going to pass
co and v paras
remember those posted parameters
get parsed out and we put them in co and v params
which we did a bit earlier in the course
then over in the controller
we'll define create
take ceo and v and also takes paras
and I'll just paste that in
now because the name of the argument here is para
we don't have to reference cover paras
it's just going to be param's type
and then over here
we've got the name of the bear
it's just going to be params
now to take this one step further
we know that we can pattern match on this
so we could do it this way
extract the name
extract the type
and if we wanted to
we could set this equal to
para if we wanted access to that
but now down here we have type that's bound to the
type that was in parts and
we have the name
we save that away
and back over an ix if we recompile everything
well it looks like everything still worked
we just moved some code from the route functions
into our controller functions
right now our resources or our bears are just names
but resources typically have
other attributes
and we know
how to model entities that have multiple attributes
we define a structure with specific fields
so let's define a bear structure
we'll put it in a file called bear
ex to find the module
survey bear
then inside of there we'll define our structure
and our bears will have an id initial value will be nil
they'll have a name
which will default to an empty string
they'll also have a type which will be an empty string
and then we'll put a hibernating flag on there
to indicate whether the bear is hibernating or not
and we'll default that to false
then we just need to create some instances of
this bare structure
so where should we do that
well we could do that in the index function
but here's another idea
let's create a new module
that provides some abstraction for fetching
any of our wild resources
let's call the new module wild things
sure I'll put it in the file wild things dot
it's very wild things
and then we're going to be using our bear
struck inside of here
so I'm going to alias
survey bear
and then we want to function
that returns a
list of example bears
and I have one of those queued up
I'll just paste it in right here
so it's just a list that contains bear strict instances
notice we've got one through
tin here with different names
different types and
some of them are hibernating
and you can pick up these examples in the note
so you don't have to type all this in
so we'll save that away
we want to use that over in our bear controller
so I'm going to start by just aliasing that in
alias survey wild things
and then we want to get our list of bears down
on the index function
so we're going to say bears
wild things list bears
and then the next thing we want to do
is transform the list of bears
there are bear structures right now
we want to transform them into an html list
so what we're going to return
in the response body isn't going to be a comma
separated string of bear names
instead it's going to be an html ul
and inside of that we'll have an li
for each of the bears so we'll have
a bear name here and it's type
and we'll have
however many of those we have bears
so how are we going to transform this list of struts
into this html
well the e new
module includes a bunch of
functions that you've likely
used in other programming languages
for working with lists
so over an I ex let's see what e n has for us
I'll use h e new dot I'm just going to hit tab
well it has a bunch of familiar functions
so if I just scroll up here
you'll notice it has each
it has filter it has map
we've got reduce
and reject
it has all sorts of functions
but what we want to do is
transform a list of strings to a list of html items
and that's a job for the map function
yeah let's look at the documentation for that
it's map with an ability too
so what it does is that transforms this given list
into a new list
by applying this
function which is the second
parameter to the map function
and this 2nd parameter is an anonymous function
anonymous functions are delimited with this fn
and then a
list of parameters in this case just one called x
then it has this arrow
and then this is the body of the function
it just takes x and multiplies it by two
and then there's an end
so it applies this function
to each element in the given list
giving us back the double numbers
so let's just copy this out of here
and we'll paste it in
I'm going to change the function body to
actually triple the numbers
and we get back a list of the triple numbers
now anonymous functions
are first class values in elixir
so we can bind them to variables
let's say we wanted to bind it to variable triple
I can just take this here
and paste it like that
and now we have a function called triple
and to call the function
we say triple
and then give a dot
and parentheses and then pass in the argument
in this case 10
and we get back to triple value 30
now it's important to note that this dot
between the variable triple and the prostheses
is required to invoke an anonymous function
it differentiates it from calling a name function
which could be somewhere else inside of a module
since anonymous functions are first class values we can
also pass them as arguments
to other functions such as map
so if we take map
give it a list of 1 2 3
then instead of inclining the anonymous function
we could just give it triple
and we get the same thing
so we can either inline the function like we did
the first time
or we can assign it to a variable
and then pass that function as an argument
so let's peek at a few more
en functions that take a function as an argument
sure one of the familiar wants to be em each
it takes a list and a function
and then it calls that function
for each of the elements in the list
there's also emu find
it takes a list in a function
that returns a truth value
or you might consider this a predicate function
and the first item in the list for which
that function returns a truth value
well it's returned
there's also enzyme filter
in this case it runs the function
on each of the elements to figure out which
ones to keep so it filtered 1 2 3
it was looking for all the evens and it returned two
and then finally there's emu reduce
and this one's kind of interesting
because it takes a list
and then it takes an initial value
and then the third argument here
is an anonymous function
but notice this anonymous function takes two arguments
x and an accumulator
and you've probably used reduced in other languages
what it does is reduces this list down to a value
in this case it's six and it's doing that by
adding each element
to this accumulator each time through this loop
so this example just sums the list of numbers