so coming back to our app
we want to respond with each
bare name and type in an html list item
yeah and to do that we'll need to map these bare struck
into these list items
so we know what we need to do
so we can get rid of our to do there
and I'm going to set up a pipeline here
we'll take our list of bears
and then we're going to pipe it into em
map remember
the first argument to map is that list
so that's going to be piped in
from the left
then the second argument is a functions
we're going to use an anonymous function here
it's going to have an argument which we'll call b
that represents the bear
and then the body of the function
we're just going to concatenate some strings
we're going to have an li
and then interpolate into that
the bear's name
put a dash and then we'll interpolate the bears type
and then we'll just close off the li
and then I often forget this but you need to end
that anonymous function
so that's going to give us a list of strings
these allies
but we want them in one big string at the end
so I'm going to use
em
join and that's going to join the list of items
these things here which are strings
into a string itself
it's just going to be one long string
with all the allies inside
of it so given that this returns a string of items
I'm going to change this from
bears because these aren't bear struck anymore
to just items
and then down here instead of having these hard coated
we'll interpolate the items in there
so I have an idea
let's just show all the grizzly bears
and we know how to do that
we can use the filter function
yeah we'll just add a step to the pipeline right here
after we get the list of bears
we'll call enzyme filter
the function is going to take
an argument which is going to be a bear again
and then the body of the function
we say b type equals grizzly
that will return true or false
depending on if the type is grizzly or not
which is exactly what filter wants
and if it returns true
then that bear is going to be in the list
and then for the final touch let's use
sort to put the names in alphabetical order
well we'll do that right after filter
so just add another step to our pipeline
now the function we give sort takes two arguments
I'm going to call in b one and b two
and then the body we can just say b one name
less center equal to b two name
and this will return a list with the bears
sorted by their name
in ascending alphabetical order
save that away
give it a recompile
now need to reload survey handler
and here's the generated ul right here
we notice we have brutus first
keen 2nd and scarface is last
so we've got those in the right order
and we're generating the ul with
the allies we expected
so we have our index action responding with html
while we're at it
let's go ahead and change this show
to respond here with an h one with the bear's name
so what we'll do is we'll delegate over to wild things
that's our module
and let's assume we have a function called get bear
and we can pass in an id
and it'll return the bear with that id
then in the response body
change this around this will be an h one
and we'll say bear and we'll interpolate
bear id put a colon
bear dot name
then we just need to define this function over
and while things
I'll just put it down below list bears here
give myself a little bit of space
it's going to be called get there
and it takes an id
and inside of there we can use e noun find
we saw that in six a little while ago
and we'll just
pass it the list of bears that are returned by
the list bears function
and then we'll give it a function
that selects the bear from that list with the given id
so it'll be function
taking a bear
if the bear's id
equals the pasta id then we want
to select that
so this is going to return
the bear that has the matching id
but the double equal sign
assumes that the id argument is an integer
this means that any value other than an integer
won't match that's a great point
if we pass in the id is a string for example
then this comparison isn't going to work
and there's a new way to fix this
we can use something called a guard claws
to enforce this functions expectation
that the id parameter is an integer
we do that up here on the function head we say when
and then there's a function in the elixir called is
integer and we pass in that id just like that
so now this function clause will only match
if that id is an integer
so if we save this away
then we recompile
reload our handler
we see we get this no function claws matching
get bare one
but notice we're calling get bare with a string
notice the double quotes there of one
and there's no function claws that matches that
so our guard is working
so why is dewberry getting called with a string
well back over in our controller
if we look here
we're just pattern matching an id
and then passing that in
and if we look back over and handler
where we're picking up that id
right here
well we're just
pattern matching using that concatenation operator
and getting id which will be
a string that gets put in the map
and that makes sense because the url is just a string
and we're just pulling the id off of it
so we could
convert the id to an integer right here in the show
action
but then we'd have to do that everywhere we have an id
so instead let's arrange things
so that the get bare function
can handle ids that are either integers or strings
and to do that we'll come back over here
we'll scroll down a little bit
and we'll define
another function clause called get bear
it'll take an id
and then we want this
function clause to match when id is a string
so we say when
is binary remember strings or binaries in elixir
so when the id is binary
what we want to do is take that id
we'll convert it to an integer using string to integer
and then we'll pipe that integer
into
this get bare function right here
now if we save this way it should work
recon reload and sure enough now it works
so this clause is called when id is an integer
and this clause is called when id is a string
now we have something working
but I want to clean up some code back
over in the controller
right in this pipeline here are filter sort and map
then we have these anonymous functions
it's just really difficult to read and
understand what's going on as
you just kind of scan that code
so let's do a quick bit of refactoring
to make it more descriptive
make it more readable
well here's a place to start
this code right here is simply creating a bare
line item so let's make a function that does that
and name the function
bare item that's a good idea
now you could put that function in a new module
that just has view helper functions for example
but we're just going to put it in bare controller
so I'll copy it out here
I'm going to put it right up here
it's going to be a private function
called bear item
it's going to take in a bear
and then I'm just going to paste in
that concatenated string that generates our list item
so now back down in map
instead of doing this right here
we'll just take this out
and we can call bear item passing in b that's the bear
oh and I got to remember up here
because we called the argument bear
that's going to be bear as well
next let's put this code in a function named is grizzly
yeah and since this doesn't have
anything to do with generating html and
really nothing to do with the web at all
I'm going to put this inside of our bare module
so I'll just cut this one out this time
over and there
we know that we can add functions into a module that
has a structure
so this one's going to be called is grizzly
give it a bear
I gotta change that over
so it's just a small
predicate function that returns truer false
then back over in our controller we can call bear
is grizzly
passing in b and since
this function lives outside of the module
we need to prefix it with the module name
and I'm also going to alias it
so I can refer to it just as bare
and since we're on a roll
let's put this ordering code into a function as well
okay I'll take that out of there
and that feels like it should be in the bare module
as well
we'll call that function order ascending by name
takes two bears you want to be two
and then it just does the comparison
then here we can call bear
order sending by name
passing in b one and b two
yeah that certainly is more readable does it work
indeed it does
it's really
common to have anonymous functions like this that take
one or two arguments and then pass them through
to named functions
yeah you notice those anonymous functions
just turn around and call
the named functions with
whatever argument was given them
so this takes a bee
just turns around and calls its grizzly with a bee
and you end up doing this all the time
so no surprise elixir provides a shortcut
over an ex let's say I have
this list of phrases lions tigers bears ult
and what we want to do is
map them to their shortage version
so we can use emu map
give it the phrases
and we'll have a function that takes each phrase
then calls the string module's upraise function
passing that string
and we get all the phrases shouted out in uppercase
so this is the same situation right
we have a function
that takes
x and it just turns around and calls a name function
passing it x now for the shortcut
we can use the capture operator
it looks like this it's an ampersand
and then we can drop the end here
and instead of
x because there's
no x because there's no anonymous function anymore
we can use ampersand one
which will be a placeholder for the first argument
and if we had two arguments
then you would use ampersand two
and so on so if we do this
what we get back to the same result
so this
is exactly the same as doing this it's just a shortcut
you can think of the ampersand
as wrapping the named function
in an anonymous function
this same as we had on this previous line
arguments passed to the anonymous function
are passed on to the named function
so now we know how to make our code a bit more succinct
yeah starting with filter here we'll just drop this out
use the capture operator the ampersand
there's one argument
so we use ampersand one
and then drop the end
we'll skip down here
drop this we can capture that function
ampersand one
all right and then this one's a little interesting
because it takes b one and b 2 2 arguments
but no problem
this just turns into imp one
and this is imp two
so this is pretty cool
and better yet it still works
but wait as they say
there's more yeah
there's one more tiny shortcut here
instead of passing in ampersand one like that
we can use the name of the function is grizzly
and the arty that function which is one
this has an er two
so there will be slash two and this has an er one
and that'll work just the same
now this shorthand syntax is tasty and succinct but it
also becomes cryptic
if it's overused
I didn't only use it in cases where you have
one or two arguments
and it doesn't obscure the intent of the code
so I'd use the shorthand syntax here as we did
because I still think it's quite readable
and remember
clear code is always better than clever code