next up we want to dynamically generate content
by rendering some template files
our templates will be a mix of html and electric code
similar to templates you may have used with
other web frameworks
and we'll use a comprehension
to keep the template code nice and succinct
right now we're generating html inside the controller
but let's change it up
to make a template that does this for us
yeah we'll make a new directory for templates
we've got this pages directory
but that's for our static file
so let's create a new directory under survey
and we'll call it templates
and then we'll start
with the template for our index action
so I'm going to call that index
and by convention that's going to have the extension
ex which stands for embedded elixir
and I already have an outline for our template teat up
so we want a ul with allies
and we want the name to get interpolated right here
and then we'll also interpolate the type of bear
in the same way let's have a show template
show ex and I've got an outline of it as well
we're just going to use an h one saying show bear
is the bear whatever their name is
hibernating and we're going to display true or false
so we need to read these template files
and then dynamically fill in the values
and it turns out elixir has a module
that makes quick work of this
no surprises the ex module
now we're interested in the evil file function
the first argument is the name of the template file
in this case they have sample
sex and the second argument is a keyword list of
bindings names and values
that can be referenced inside of the template
so if we have sample ex
then food is just some static text in there
and then we use less than % equals
in bar and % greater than like that
well this whole thing is going to get replaced
by the value of bar
which is bass
so the output of this is food bass
now if you're a rails programmer
this syntax will actually look quite familiar
yeah it's similar to ruby's erb
so to start things off
in the bare controller
we need to get the absolute path to the template file
and we actually
already know how to do that
we did it over and handler
yeah it's up here at the top
we have our pages path so I'm just going to copy it
go over to bare controller up here
paste it in and change this to templates path
and templates
now we need to change this pipeline down here a little
bit we want to see all the bears
so I'm going to remove the filter for is grizzly
we also don't need to transform these struck
into bear items anymore
because
the ul and the alli is going to get generated in the
template so I can remove that
and while I'm at it I'll remove this
function because we're not going to need it
anymore either
and then we can also remove this join
because we don't need to join the list
into a string anymore
this is going to return a list of bears
we're just going to sort those
so now we're back to having a list of bear struck
and then for the response body what we want
is the content of that evaluated template
so this is just going to be content
we're going to create that content right here
content equal
we're going to take our templates path
we're going to pipe it into path join
index ex
that's going to give us an absolute path to that
template file
then we're going to pipe that into
ex evil file that's the function we just looked at
it takes a file name as the first argument
which is going to be piped in from the left
and then we can give it our bindings
so we want the name
bears in our template to refer
to the value that's in our bears list
this thing set right up here
now because this keyword list is the
last argument to the function
we can actually drop the square brackets
so in the index template
let's start by inspecting the list of bears
yeah I'll just put it below our static text right here
we use less than %
equals
that's how we interpolate values into a template
and then % greater than like that
I'm going to use the inspect function
just so we see the raw
form of bears
save that away
if we look at the response
what we see we have a list of bear struck
so all we need to do is just loop
over this list of bears
and generate an html line item or an ally
for each element in the list
so let's go ahead and fill out this template
inside of the ul we want to generate allies
so I'm going to start just here
we'll use less than % equal
let's say we have a bear variable and its name
we'll interpolate that right there
in the same way we'll have
bear type like that
okay but we need to generate one of these
for every element that's in the bears list
and one way to do that would be to use em map
now
don't follow along because this isn't going to survive
for very long
but we could do this
me dot map
bears for every one of those
we generate a list item
and then we need to make sure to close this off
down here less than % and
god remember to do that parentheses right there
like that save that away
reload
and it looks like it worked
we have all of our bears in a ul
and they're neatly tucked away inside of a list item
okay so using emu map certainly works
but the syntax is an ideal
especially with this anonymous function
it was actually really difficult to type in
yeah simple looping construct here sure would be nice
and hey this gives us a chance to use a comprehension
you may not have seen a comprehension before
so let's start with this simple example
remember when we used map on a list 1 2 3
and gave it an anonymous function
and that tripled all the numbers
well here's the way to do the same
thing with a comprehension
we use four
x a left pointing arrow
then we give it a list 1 2 3 in this case
a comma and then do and we can give it a block
this is a single line comprehension so I'll use
comma do colon
and then we triple the numbers x times three
just like that
so that's pretty cool this
x left arrow and then this 1 2 3 right here
this whole thing is called the generator
it generates the numbers one through three
so what happens is
it iterates through the list
and then it runs this do expression for each element
so the first time
x is going to get set to a value of one
and do is going to return three
and then 2nd time x is going to be set to two
and this is going to return six and so on
and you notice that it returns a list
containing the results of that due expression
so we gave it a list here
and even though this says x times three
it puts the result of that
inside of a list
so just comparing these two right here
using a comprehension is just a more succinct way
to map one list of values into another list
we'll use a simple comprehension like this
for our template
but it's worth noting before we move on
that you can do all
sorts of cool stuff with comprehensions
for example suppose we have t
shirt sizes and colors
and we want to generate the combination
we want small for red and blue
medium for red and blue and whatnot
to do that we can give the comprehension two generators
so here's a generator for the size
then there's a comma
and here's the generator for the color
and then the due expression just puts size and color
inside of a tuple
so if we run that as nicole said we get small red
small blue medium red medium blue large red large blue
and you get the point
using multiple generators like this
is like having a nested loop
so back in our template instead of using map
we can use our comprehension
we'll say four bear
and then the list is
actually the list of bears that were set in our
controller action
then just remember to put a do right there
and we can drop this prints right down here
save that away
oh there's nothing to recompile
because I just changed the template
and you see we've got our bears in our list
same as before
this just feels a lot
nicer than the version we had that used map
now
it's worth noting that you can use comprehensions in
any electric code
not just templates
in some cases in in particular templates
I think they're easier to read
than using e new functions
we still have the show template we haven't used
so we need to dynamically generate content for it
yeah
so what we need to do is evaluate the show template
inside of the show action
so to get started I'm going to copy this
we're going to end up with a little bit of duplication
but that's okay
the name of the template is going to be show ex
and then in terms of our bindings
we're just going to bind
the name bear to the value bear
that's the thing we have set right here
then for our response body
we can get rid of this string
because this is just going to be the template content
then say that away we'll go to this show template
and instead of a hard coded name
here we'll use less than % equal
bear that's the name of the binding we have
and then for truan falls
we're going to have
their dot hibernating
save that away
I change the controller so I need to recompile
and if I reload the handler
check it out shell bears in an age one
is teddy hibernating yes he is
now
we've obviously introduced a bit of duplication here
which we can clean up
how about we make a new function named render that
we can then reuse in both index and show
yeah and to get that started
I'm just going to copy an instance of one of these
and we'll define render up at the top here
just so it's handy
we'll make it a private function
because it's not going to get called
outside of this module
and I'll paste in what I copied below
all right and now
let's figure out what arguments it's going to need
to take well
it needs co and v
because we update that as the last line
it also needs the template
we don't want this hard coated right here
so I'll just call this the template
we'll make that the second argument
and also needs the bindings
because those
are going to vary depending on the action
so let's take this out and we'll just call it bindings
that will be the third argument
and we can default that to an empty list
this is how you set a default parameter an elixir
so if we don't supply the bindings
it's just going to be an empty list
then down in index
we can go ahead and call that render function
pass co and v it's going to
be index ex and our bindings are bears will be bears
the same way I'll just copy that
and we can paste it down here for show
the only difference here
is the template is called show
and it's just a single bear
save that away
recompile
and it looks like everything's still hunky dory now
besides wanting an excuse to look at comprehensions
you might be wondering why
we went through all the trouble to create a controller
the wild things module and these template files
we'll stick around because all will be revealed next