now this module is completely optional
but in case you're learning elixir
because you're on your way to Phoenix next
well we have good news for you
it's gonna look pretty familiar
yeah it's a bit like learning a new language
before an international trip
you pick up a language course
you learn some common words and phrases
and then you practice them around the office k
then when you turn up at your destination
some of the sights and sounds feel familiar
so let's start by looking at a Phoenix app
just so you don't think we have
any tricks up our sleeve
we'll generate a Phoenix app
from scratch and see what we get
for free
now I already have Phoenix installed on this computer
check the notes
if you need installation instructions
to get it set up on your computer
and to generate the app
we say mix p new in the name of the app
in this case we're going to call it refuge
now just make sure
that you're not in the survey directory
when you run this you can be anywhere else
I'm in an empty apps directory right now
and that went ahead and generated a bunch of code
and then asked us
if we want to install the dependencies
sure go ahead and do that
then it's going to download the dependencies
and compile them and get
everything set up
and through the magic of video
we'll speed this up a bit
then we'll change
into that refuge directory that it created
and we'll want to generate some scaffold code
for creating
reading updating and deleting our bear resources
yeah Phoenix has a number of generators
we're going to generate an html app so let's say mix p
dot gm html then once the name of a context
I'll explain that a bit later we're going to call our
wild things
the name of the resource is going to be bear
then it wants the plural name it'll be bears
and then we give it attributes for the resource
so we're going to have a name
that's going to be a string
a type will be a string
and we'll have hibernating
which will be a boolean
and it went ahead and generated all the files
for managing that resource
so now we'll go ahead and open it in our editor
and I'm using sublime
and I have our survey app on the left
and the Phoenix app on the right
let's dive right into the controller of the Phoenix app
yeah it's done in the live directory
there's a directory called refuge
and then if we go inside of web
well there's a sub directory called controllers
I'll open that up just a little bit more
so we can see it
and there's the bare controller
and didn't just save space
I'm going to close that sidebar
and just like our bare controller on the left
it's a module that defines
functions called actions
to handle different requests
so starting from the top here the first line is this
use line and it's a meta programming incantation
which requires this web module
which in turn injects some code
into our controller
now this is a Phoenix specific thing
don't worry about it
and then it aliases this wild things
module which we'll look at in a minute
then we have the index action
now in Phoenix
each action takes two
parameters which the Phoenix framework provides
when the action is run
the first parameter is always co n n
it's an abbreviation for connection
it's similar to our con
it's a structure
that holds information about the request
the second parameter is
para which is a map that holds any request parameters
similar to our param's map
now the index action in this case doesn't use
the parameters
so it uses underscore
parameters so that we don't get a compiler warning
about it not being used
now our index action just takes conv
as the first parameter doesn't have a second parameter
because we don't use the para in our index action
but you know how to pass those through
if you wanted to do that
just like our app calls wild things
list bears to get all the bears
if we look in the Phoenix app
the first line in index action does the same thing
we've got a module wild things
and calls a function to list bears and
both return a list of bear struck
then it calls render passing conn
and it also passes the template name index html
now Phoenix uses a slightly
different naming convention than ours
but both templates render html
and then the third parameter is the bindings
so they're going to bind bears to bears
just like we did over here when we called our render
now let's dig one level deeper
into this wild things module
open up the sidebar again
it's down here in a directory called wild things
and there's a wild things ex
and we'll do the same over here in our survey app
we just have everything under survey
and there's our wild things module
so if we look at the wild things
module generated by Phoenix
it's a simple abstraction for creating reading
updating and deleting a resource bears in our case
now if you look to the Phoenix documentation
they're going to refer to this thing as a context
and the comment says that it's a boundary for the wild
things system
so basically this is a data access layer
it encapsulates
everything related to
getting bears creating bears
updating bears and deleting bears
so if we look at this list bears function right here
it calls below passing bear
well the re module is part of the
ecto library and this is the database rapper library
used by Phoenix
and repo represents a connection to a database which
by default is going to be
a post risk database
so calling rep
queries the database to fetch all the bears in our app
we just have an in memory database
so our list bears just returns a list of bears
then back over here
if we scroll down a little bit further
they have a get bear function that calls repo dot get
passing the bear in the id
which will issue a database query to find
the bear with the given id
it's pretty similar to our get bear
except we're using email
find to find
the bear within the list of bears
that has that matching id
now you notice if we scroll down over and wild things
they have a function for creating a bear
there's a function for updating a bear
and also for deleting a bear from the database
now let's go
have a look at that index template to see what's going
on in there so in the Phoenix app
under the web directory you'll find a template
sub directory
and then it has these organized by the controller
so all the templates for the bare controller are
under the bare sub directory
and there's the index for that
and you notice they use the naming convention index
that html ex
it's just a different naming convention than we used
the intent here is
you know by looking at the name
that this generates html
thus open up our index template over here
down in templates
there it is
hey check this out in the same way
we use a comprehension to
loop through all the bears
and then we're using less than % equals
well they're doing the same thing here
there's a comprehension for bear
notice the bears has an at sign before it
this is just the way Phoenix sets up data
in the actions
so to get access to the value bound to the bears name
you have to use at bears in Phoenix
and then inside of that loop
they use the same
syntax to get all the attributes of the bear
so far this is all pretty familiar
now let's go back to the controller
bear controller here
and the bare controller here
let's have a look at this
show action in the Phoenix generated app
here is put them side by side
and you notice just like our show action
the second parameters
these para and they're using pattern matching
to extract this id
then they turn around and call
get bear with that id to get the bear struck
then they call render with the template show html
and pass the bear as a bound value
the same way we extract the id
get the bear from our wild things module
and render the show template
now what about this crate action over here
well in our app
we didn't actually create a bear in the database
that's sort of outside the scope of this course
but if we look at
how the generated crate action does it
it's familiar code
we notice its pattern matching
on the para
to extract the bear para into this variable
and the way these para come in is they're nested
under a key called bear
so it's a map inside of another map
then they call the create
bear function with those bear prams
and that can succeed or fail
so they're using a case expression
and then they can pattern match
on the success or failure
so if it succeeds we're going to get an ok atom
and then we're going to have a bear
in that case they take the connection
and they call
put flash on it to put a flash message
inside of that connection
this just adds extra information of the connection
in the same way that we plugged in functions
using things like log and track
and then it redirects to the show action
to show the new bear
otherwise if creating the bear fails
then we get this tuple and pattern match on it
we get an error
and then we have this thing called a change
set that they pattern match on
and that change
set will include any validation errors to be displayed
so they extract the change set
and then they render the new template
giving it the change
set so it can pull out the validation errors
and if you scroll through this file
you'll see that the generator implemented
other restful actions
like edit there's update down here
there's a delete action
but there's really no new syntax or concepts here
the router is more interesting so let's hop over there
the router is over in the directory web
if you scroll down here there's a file router ex
and just for comparison
over here
I'm going to open up our handler because that has our
route function inside of it
now this router module looks pretty
different than other modules that we've seen
rather than defining functions
it uses macros
so it feels more like a domain specific language
and the macros get expanded
into functions at compile time
now there's a lot going on in here
so let's break it down
forget about these pipelines for just a minute
we'll come back to those
let's focus on this route right here
so it matches a git request for the path slash
and then it's going to call the page controllers
index action to handle that request
now Phoenix generated the page
controller in the index action by default
because it just wants to display a welcome page and
have something
there for people to look at
but we want a route for listing bearers
so I'm just going to copy this
put it below this route
and when we go to slash bears
we want to run our bear controller
index action now
I mentioned that this module makes heavy use
of macros and
get is a macro
and it's going to get expanded at compile time
into a function called match
it looks something like this
I'm just going to paste it outside of here
so the function is called match
it
takes a conn that's their connection or conversation
did it pattern matches on the hdp verb
in this case it's going to be a get
because we used get there
and then the third parameter is
a list that they pattern match on
and this is the path slash bears
so the match function takes three arguments
if we look over at our route function for slash bears
we're just taking one argument
it's the co and v our connection
and then we pattern match on
what's inside of that connection
so we're pattern matching
whatever's inside of the conversation map
as one argument
and their pattern matching on the
verb and the path separately is two separate arguments
but that's no big deal
now that you know how to pattern match
you could pattern match on one argument that has
everything inside of a map
or you could pattern match on separate arguments
it's six and one half a dozen of the other
so I'm going to get rid of this
because again that's generated at compile time
by the macro but let's say we wanted the full
complementary route to manage a bear resource
well we could do this
by putting a bunch of routes in here
and I'm just going to paste in a
list I already have
and each of these is a macro
that's going to get expanded
into a match function
so we're going to end up with eight
multi clause match functions
and we know how multi clause functions behave
elixir tries to match them from top to bottom
and the first
clause that matches the verb and the path will be run
now as you might expect
there's a shortcut to adding all these restful routes
so if we comment this out
shorthand way of doing this is to say resources
slash bears
and then bare controller
and that itself is a macro that's going to expand
to give us all
eight clauses of the match function
so now let's double back and look at this
pipeline stuff at the top here
and remember we have our own pipeline
over in this handle function
we're using the pipe operator to do that
it pipes the request
through various functions we've written
while Phoenix has two separate pipelines
one of them's called browser
and one of them's called api
and they perform different transformations inside
this one for the browsers
a little bit more involved than the one for the api
because they have different needs
instead of using the pipe operator
they use this plug function
right here
and then they give it the name of a function
so this plugs the accepts function
the fetch session function and so on
but it's basically the same thing it's a
pipeline of transformation functions
they get applied to the request
then because these pipelines have names
if we look down here under scope slash
it says pipe through browser
so browser based requests get piped through
this pipeline
which means
any of the requests that match these routes will have
already gone through this pipeline
likewise if you scroll down a little bit further
there is a scope for
api and it gets piped through the api pipeline
now we've barely scratched the surface of Phoenix
it's a full stack web framework
after all with lots of bells and whistles
but hopefully this quick walkthrough has given you more
confidence before setting sail
for the fiery land of Phoenix