in this module
we're going to look at how to write automated
tests in elixir
but here's some things
we're not going to do in this module
we're not going to try to convince you that testing is
important we assume you already know that
we're also not going
to shame you if you're not
doing restroom and development
or don't have 100% test coverage
in fact we're not going to preach testing dogma at all
we're going to assume
you've used a unit testing framework in
another language
and you want to know how to test in elixir
right now we have this code at the bottom of handler
that sends request to the handle function
and prints out the responses
so when we recompile survey handler in an ix session
that code is run and we see the requests and responses
so in essence we're just visually
testing and I'm using air quotes here
that each request works
and as you might guess
there's a better way to do testing
when we created a new elixir project using mix
new service mix was presumptuous enough to
also generate a test directory
and it has two files in it
test helper exs and service test exs
the test files are elixir scripts
that's the sex extension
which means they don't have to be compiled
before their run
and if we look in test helper
well we see that it starts
ex unit and ex unit is elixir's built in
test framework
then if we have a look in survey test
well there's a module called survey test
and this first line says use ex unit case
use adds the testing functionality or behavior
that's defined in this ex unit case module
and it adds that behavior to the current module
which is our survey test
the 2nd line is this
dock test and we'll come back to that in just a minute
then we have the testing macro which defines a test
and then there's a description as a string
and a block of code
and then inside of the block of code
we state our expectations
using this assert macro
was just test that this expression is truth
so we're asserting that 1+1 equals two
the opposite of assert is something called refute
so we could refute that 2+1 equals two
because that's not true
and generally these
two macros are all
you need to do testing
because you're either going to assert that
something's true
or you're going to refute something
all right I'm going to get rid of this for now
so let's go ahead and run this test
I'm in the survey directory
and we run the test by using
mix test and then we give it the name of the test file
so it's going to be
test survey test ex
and no surprise it succeeds
now
let's make it fail just to see how the output changes
so we'll assert that 1+1 equals
three
run the test again
you scroll up a little bit here
well what's nice about the assert macro is
it introspects the code
to give us some helpful feedback
it shows us the assertion that failed right here
this is the expected value two
and then this is the actual value three
cool so let's go ahead and change it back to a
passing state
there we go
so let's not write our own unit test
to help us get started
let's copy this code
and then we can create a test case for our parser
named parser underscore test
and I'll just paste in the code that we have
and we're going to change the module from
survey test to parser test
I'm also going to change this doc test to serve parser
and we'll come back to that in a minute
we also need to alias in the parser
since that's what we're going to test
so what should we test in the parser
well let's have a look at that in parser ex
well before we get to our end to interest
let's show them two ways to write unit tests
yeah we've got some recursion going
on here when we're parsing the headers
so let's write a unit test for these functions
you'll remember this function
it takes a
list of header lines that's the head and the tail
and then we want to parse those
into a map that contains key value pairs so
it'll be the headers
so we can write a test for that
come back over to parser test
change the description here
parses a list of header fields
into a map
get rid of this so let's set up some header lines
it's going to be a list that looks like this
the header a might have a value of one
and then the header b might have a value of two
now the actual headers have
different keys and values but a one and b two work
just fine for the test here
then we want to transform this
into a map of headers and we do that by calling parser
parse headers
we pass in the header lines
and an empty map like that
so what do we expect to return to headers to look like
well we can use the assert macro and say we assert
the headers equal a map
that has a key of a
and a value of one
and a key of b
the value of two
so we expect it to parse this list of lines
into key value pairs
if we save that away
then to run it we'll do it just like before
except we're going to give it parser test
it looks like it works
the assert macro is
actually pretty smart about helping you figure out
why an assertion is failing
so let's say
that we remove one of the key values from our expected
map and then we rerun our tests
well it fails
and it tells us why we see the map on the left
doesn't match the map on the right
because the one on the left
also has a key b and a value of two
so we're missing a key value
so I'll just change that back so we have a passing test
there we go so that's one way to write unit tests
but instead of putting them in a separate file
we can write something
called doc tests
so let's go back to our parish
we've got this tested
but what about this parsed para right here
I'm going to paste in a little bit of documentation
at the top
we already know how to use
at dock to document what a function does like this
it's also helpful to include examples of
how to use the function
and by convention
those examples are shown in an ix session like this
now
this is a bit difficult to see with this color scheme
so i'm just going to uncommon these
for a minute to get a different color
now the first thing to note is that we write
elixir documentation
using markdown
you notice this double hash here
that's going to generate an h two
and you also notice that the code that we have up here
for keys and values
goes inside of single back ticks
and then this part is called the docent
and it's basically a set of expectations
or assertions about how our code is intended to work
so if we have a param string that looks like this
and then we call serve parser pars para
this is the first parameter to it
and then the second parameter is our param string
well what do we expect
well we expect ix to return a map that looks like this
it took the name and the type from here
and put it inside of a map
and then if we call parse para with
multipart form data as the first parameter
and param string is the second parameter
well we don't handle
this format so we expect to get back in
empty map
now wouldn't it be cool if we could run
these examples and check
that the actual value returned by the function
matches the values shown in the comment
imagine that well that's exactly what this docent line
over in parser test does
it's a macro that looks for
docents in this module survey parser
and if it finds docent then it generates tests for them
so because we already have this line
and we've got this dock test over here
I just need to
comment this the way it should be
so it's an actual dock test
like that save it away
now if we come down here and run parser test again
well now we have two tests
one of the unit tests we wrote conventionally
and one of the tests got generated from
this dock test
now just to show that this is an actual test
let's make it fail
I'll change this type to a color
and sure enough it fails
just like any other unit test would
so let's go ahead and change that back
what's really cool about this is we
always know that the examples in the dock test are
up to date and they never lie which is something you
always hope for in documentation
but don't always get
so now we have two test files
and we can run those tests in one swoop
we just do that by using
mix test and not giving it a file name
we see that we have three tests
we've got our parser tests and then survey tests
and what mix test did is it just looked in the
test directory here
and it found all the files ending in underscore tests
ex and it went ahead and ran those
now that we know how to write tests
let's return to our original goal
which was to convert
this code at the bottom of the handle module
into automated tests
let's start by deleting these
because we don't want this
code executing when we run our app
so we're just going to go down to the very bottom
grab all this stuff here
to there and zap it out
I'm going to create a new test file
under the test directory
it's going to be called handler test exs
and I'm going to paste in our first end end test now
don't worry about typing in this test
you'll actually find it
as well as all the other tests in the code bundle
it's called handler test
there's this use line again
and then we have this import line
what we're going to do here is import this
handle function
just so it's easy to use inside of this module
then we use our test macro here
and our description is
this is for a get of wild things
we've got our code block
so what we do inside the code block is
we set up a request
using a hear dock
we pass the request
into our handle function this is serve handler handle
we get back a response
and then we're going to use the assert macro
to assert that that response equals
another hear dock which is our response
now you might be wondering
what's with these characters at the end of the lines
well the http spec
actually requires these lines to end
in a carriage return line feed which is backslash r
backslash n
now the hair dock implicitly gives us the backslash n
at the end of each line
but we have to explicitly add the backslash r
so you see that at the end of these lines
in the same way
the spec also requires
backslash r backslash n on the response lines
so we've added those here
now this is a bit
pedantic but the message body this last line here
doesn't have to have a backslash r
so you don't see one there
we didn't want these to get in the way earlier
they do kind of look obnoxious
but a bit later will send requests from a browser
and they'll be in this format
so we might as well account for these characters now
so let's see if this test works
mix test
handler test ex
and it looks like we have a problem
if we scroll up here
while we see no match the right side value
get wild things
and notice we see these
backslash r backslash ends throughout here
because that's what our request has
but that's not what our parser's expecting
so we go back over to the parser
the very top here
we split on
slash n well this is actually going to be
backslash r backslash n
that separates the top from the pram strings
in the same way
all the top lines will have a backslash r backslash n
so that fixes the parser but over in the handler
we also need to change this format response function
to include backslash r
at the end of these lines
and now our test should pass
come down here
run it again sure enough they pass
already so only seven more tests to write
get your fingers ready
just kidding
we're not going to make you suffer through that
we're just going to paste them in and again
you can find all the tests in the code bundle
so here's the test that we just wrote
and then we pasted some tests beneath it
so here's one for get slash bears
we set up the request
we call handle get a response to that
and I did this one a little bit differently
notice I say expected response equals
and then we have a hear dock
and then we have the headers we would expect
and then the content
remembers generated from a template
so this is all that template generated content
and because that template can have different
white space in it
and sometimes it's difficult to assert
based on white space
I wrote a little function down
below called remove right space
so we just call remove white space on the response
and that should equal
the equivalent of our expected response
and we use the assert macro
to make sure that's true
and all the other tests work in a similar way
there's really nothing new here
if it's just one line
of a response like this
that wasn't generated from a template
well then I just use assert on that response
but if it's template generated code
I use this pattern of removing white space
but you can look through here and you'll see that
all of them follow the similar style
and better yet they should all pass
and indeed they do
but if you scroll
up
you might wonder what's with all this output up here
well if you recall
our pipeline at the top of handler has plugins
to log and track requests
those functions are in the plugins module
and they use io to print out a warning message
and log information to the console
but perhaps we
only want to print this
stuff to the console when the app
is running in a specific environment
yeah mix actually supports three different environments
dev test and prod which is short for production
de is the default and it switches to test when we use
mix test
so suppose we only want to see the output of this
log function during development
while we can change this around
and change it to a multiline function here
and then we only want this line to run
during development
so we can put an if statement around here
if and you can call mix
end that will return the current mix environment
if it equals dev
we'll go ahead and print that out
otherwise it won't and remember
because this log functions in a pipeline
we always need to return co n
oh
and I always forget to add the dew at the end of an if
just old habit
so that takes care of log
what about this track function up here
well let's say we want to track four of fours
in development and in production
but not in test
so what we can do here is say
if mix end does not equal test do
put that inside of that if condition
and then make sure to always return co and v
if we save that away
and run our test we should get a lot cleaner output
there we go
and if we run all of our test well
we should have green across the board indeed we do