so our first step is to create an elixir project
and get some code running
and no surprise
elixir has conventions for organizing projects and
great tooling to automate project tasks
to create a new elixir project
we use the mix command that we say mix new
and the navar project is going to be see
and it generated a few files and directories there
we'll look at those in just a minute now
the mix tool lets us automate common project tasks
sort of like ruby's rake tool
in fact if you just want to see all the tasks you do
mix help and it lists all those out
so we did the mix new to create a new elixir project
but there's a load of tasks in here for
just common things you want to do
around your elixir project
so I'm just going to change directory
into that
survey project directory and then open it up in
my editor
let's take a quick peek at the lightweight
directory structure
that the mix new command created
we've got a con directory
which contains one file configurable
exs and this file is responsible for
configuring the application
no surprise here
most of it is comments and
it's pretty rare that you have to drop
into this and change anything
we'll return back to this
as we need it later on in the course
and we've got a live directory
this is where our application code is going to live
and generated a survey
ex file which we'll look at in just a second
we also have a test directory which no surprise
has some test inside of those some generated tests
again we'll look at those a little bit later
and then we have this mix exs
and this is where we configure our project
and its dependencies
we'll have to add
a dependency a little bit later on in the course
so we'll come back to this file as well
now don't let the two file extensions dot
ex and dot exs throw you
both types of files contain elixir code
dot ex files are meant to be compiled and then run
whereas dot sex
files are effectively interpreted like scripts
thus the trailing s
most of the time though you'll just use the
ex extension
and that's exactly the extension we have on this serbia
ex because it's application code
and all of our application code is going to have a
ex extension so I'm just going to remove these comments
so we can focus on the code
and elixir code is always organized in name module
so the file starts by defining a module here
which is just a name
space for functions it uses def module
then the name of the module is see
notice that it starts with an uppercase character
and all module names and elixir use
camel case similar to
ruby classes and modules
then inside of the module we have a
name function called hello
and
the function names are lowercase with underscores or
snake case and these are similar to ruby method names
and
all name functions must be defined inside of a module
if you're a ruby programmer
this should look fairly familiar
but one thing that might trip you up
that at least a trip to me up was trying to remember
to type the dew
yeah
I always forget these dues on the ends of these lines
so that's just something to keep in mind
and this hello function is currently returning an
atom which is like a symbol in ruby
so it's the atom world
and adam is just a
name whose value is the same as its name or
a constant
let's just have it return a proper greeting here
so we'll use an elixir string which is double quotes
no surprise and then we can use string interpolation
just like in ruby
if we wanted to say hello
some name and then we could pass that name in
as an argument to the hello function
then to call a function
we're going to come down
outside of this module and I'm going to use io
that's a module name that's built into elixir
use puts
which should be familiar if you're a ruby programmer
and then we use the module name
which is serving in this case
and the name of the function hello
and then we'll just pass it elixir
so defining modules
and functions
and then calling those
functions on the modules is pretty straightforward
obviously
the next thing we want to do is to run our code
and to do that
we're going to need to compile our elixir files
to bike code
and then run that bike code on the up virtual machine
now the early virtual machine is like 20 years old
so you can imagine what we're going to have to
go through
just to print out hello elixir to the console
make files cross compilers
the good news is once we get past this point
it's all downhill from here
just kidding
elixir makes it really easy to run our code
so the first way to run an elixir file is using the
elixir command
and our serbia
ex file is down in the lip directory
so I just give it a relative path there
and we see we get hello elixir no surprise
but this is pretty cool when you think about it
because the file got compiled in memory
into bike code and then it was run
on the early virtual machine
now our file lives in the mixed project directory under
lib but you can create a one off elixir file
anywhere you want
and run it using the electric command
it doesn't have to be in a mixed project directory
like we have it here
but unless it's a one off file
I always put my code in a mixed project directory
because I usually
end up with multiple files
and that's just the proper way to do it
I can also run this back in sublime
I've got it set up if I do apple b
I get the output there it's hello elixir
and this is just set up to
run the elixir command on the current file
and I'm going to use this approach
at least for the first
part of the course
just so you don't have to watch
me switch back and forth
between the command line and the editor
and it's just the easy way to get the results quickly
another way to run our app
is to use a luxor's interactive shell fix
yeah this is similar to ruby's irb
and we could just type in
any expression and get its result
so you type sex
just like that
and it'll evaluate any expression
no surprise you can also call
any built in modules like string
and the function reverse for example
but what happens if we try our survey module and
call our hello
passing in my name
well it says survey hello is undefined
the module survey is not available
and that's because by default index doesn't know about
this survey file
so one way to compile it and load it is using the c
function
then we just give it a string which is the relative
path to the file we want to run
and you notice we immediately got hello elixir
so this compiled
the file in memory and then loaded the survey module
into the session
and then
any code that's outside of the module is interpreted
so this code right here that prints out hello elixir
got interpreted
which is why we see the output right here
to get out of
if you can hit control c
and this is going to open up the brake menu
and then you can either type a
right here to get out of this session
or as most people do
you just hit control c again
so to get out of if it's basically two control cs
there's a shortcut to starting fix and
loading up a file
you can just use it and then give it
the name of the file relative path
again as an argument
and again the file is compiled in memory
and the series modules is loaded
into the runtime and then
any code that's outside of the module is interpreted
which is why we see this right here
so that's a shortcut to
opening six and then using the c function to compile it
and to get out of this
I'm just going to hit control c twice
one final
way to run code in six is to start the ix session with
a s option and then mix
and then it says it compiled the file
we got the output
because it interpreted this line up here again
when you start it with the dash s mix option
it knows about the project so
we're in an ix session
in the context of our application
so we can go ahead and use our module survey
hello for example
I tend to use this approach
because
it compiled and loads all the modules in the project
and we can interact with any of the application code
so you don't have to compile it or
load item with a specific file
you've got access to everything you need right here
so let's look at what happens when we need to recompile
let's say we change our code from hello to howdy
if I save that away here
in sublime I can hit appleby again
we get back howdy elixir
down here
if I'm still in an ix session I can use the r function
and then give it the name of a module
in this case our module is see
and that recompile and reloads the given module
you see we get a little bit of warning here saying
we're redefining that module
and then it recompiled reloaded it
and we see that we've got
howdy elixir because it interpreted that line again
so now if we say low mic it says howdy mic
so I'm going to go ahead and comment out this
line right here
so it doesn't get interpreted
every time we load up our project and ix going forward
so now we have a project and a jumping off point
from which to build our web
server next up we'll handle our first http request