up to this point all of our responses are returned html
but let's say we want to return json
for an api request
well to do that
we'll use an external json library that's not
built into elixir
now let's start a little differently this time
here's a test that expresses what we want to have
happen when we get a request for api bears
we want to respond with a content type of application
json and then the
body is a list of json objects representing
all the bears
again don't worry about typing this in
you'll find this test in the notes
now to make the test pass
we'll need a way to encode the list of bear struck
as json
and elixir doesn't have a module that does this
so we'll need to use an external json library
elixir's package manager is called hex and it's at hex
pm and then we'll search for encode json
and their first result
here is a library called poison
and we're going to go ahead and use that
because it's very popular
and
also Phoenix uses it by default for j sound encoding
you notice over here
it actually
gives us the code we need to put in our mix
ex file so let's go ahead and copy that
and then back over on our project
we'll open up mix ex and you'll remember
this is where we can figure our project
in any of its dependencies
so we'll add in that code down here
under depths this is where we list
the dependencies
so inside of this
list we'll just paste that code that we copied
if you have other project dependencies
you would just list them here
and you notice that each
element of the list is a tuple
where the first
value of the tuple is the name of the library
and the second value of the tuple is the version
so this indicates that we want the poison package
with a major version of three
and a minor version of one or greater
and if we save that
away and come back over to a command line
we can run mixed depths to list the dependencies
it says okay you've got a dependency on poison
but it's not yet available
run mixed depths get
so let's go ahead and do that
you notice it goes off to the hex rep and
downloads poison 3 1 0
now if we run mixed depths again
it says okay it's locked at 3 1 0
but it's outdated and you need to compile it
well it's going to get automatically compiled
when we run the application
so we've got everything we need
in fact if we look in this directory
there is a mix lock
and that's where it remembers which version
so it basically locks down those version dependencies
we also see that we have this directory called
depths and I'm going to use the tree utility here
just to see what's
inside of it and you notice inside of depths
we have a directory called poison that's the library
it has a lib directory poison
and then we've got the elixir code for that library
so this is just an elixir application
let's give the poison library a quick spin
and mix to see how it works
and you notice when I fired that up
it went ahead and compiled
the poison file
so we've got that
now let's get some bears
all right that's a list of our bears as bear struck
and then to convert those into json we use poison
that's the name of the module
there's a function called in code
and it has an exclamation market the end
which means it raises an exception if there's an error
and then we just pass it in our list of struck
what we get back is a list of
json objects just like we want
so this is perfect
now that we know how to encode the bears as json
we simply need a row and a controller for our api
and since it's common practice to have a separate
controller for api requests
we'll create a new controller in an api directory
create the directory here undeserving api
and this just demonstrates that you can
organize code in
arbitrary directories
it's just under lib survey api
and you can have other directories under here
and then inside of the api directory
we want a file called bear
controller ex
so we've got a bare controller under api
we also have a bare controller just under survey
but they're going to be different
because the module is going to be called serve
api bare controller so this reflects
the directory structure over here
and then we need to define an action in here
and we're going to use index
it's going to take co and v
just like the index in our regular bear controller
and then we want to generate some jason
we're going to say json equals
we're going to use serve wild things
list bears to get all of our bears
and then we're just going to pipe that into poison
encode
and that'll give us back json
and then we need to return an updated co and v map
with a status of 200
and then our response body
will be jason
the second thing we need is a route
so if we go to handler
we can just copy the route we have for slash bears
and then modify it
yeah we wanted to match
api slash bears
and then instead of calling the bear controller index
we're going to call
survey api bear controller index
you can save that away
so now what happens if we run our tests
what we've got one failure if we scroll up here
what we see in red that
we're returning text html
but we're expecting application
json so the content type isn't right for api
requests we should
always be setting the content type to application json
well this is easy enough to fix
we'll just set the content type
in the co and v structure
we'll add a new response content type field
and default it to text html
as an exercise
you could name this response headers
and keep arbitrary response headers in a map
but we'll just keep it simple by using
response content type and a string here
so now that we have that
we need to come back over to our handler module
and we need to change
format response instead of hard coding text html
we need to interpolate
co and v
response content type
we'll save this and cnv need to save that off too
and then we'll head over to our api bare controller
and then here we'll just override
response content type to be application json
so all the other actions will take the default of
text html but this one's going to override it because
it's returning json
and if we save that away the test should now pass
and indeed they do
and that's all there is to using an external library