so I've been thinking since we're writing a web server
after all isn't it
about time we start sending our request from a client
you know like a browser
well here's the cool thing
our handler module knows how to transform requests
into responses that the browser can display
so all we need to do
is wrap that handler in a thin socket layer
that lets any hdbb client interact with our server
and we can do that
with a fairly limited amount of code
by using an early library
here's a quick refresher on how a web server works
the server first
creates a socket
to listen for client connections on a specific port
number for example port 4000
you can think of a socket as a communication channel
between any two programs a client and a server
in our case we'll assume the client is a browser
though it could be any http client
after creating the listening socket
the server waits to accept a client connection
on that listening socket
to send an http request
the browser sends a connection request to the server
on the port number
and ip address where the server is listening
the server accepts the connection and creates a new
client socket
a new socket is
needed so that the server can continue listening for
other connection requests on the listening socket
the browser then sends the http request to the server
over the client socket
the server receives the request generates
out an appropriate http response
and sends that response back to the browser
over the same client socket
finally the server closes the client socket to
end the connection
the server is now
ready to accept the next connection request
on the listening socket
in this way
ignoring bells and whistles such as keep alive
as simple web server handles one
http request response cycle at a time
so basically a web server has
two separate layers with distinct responsibilities
there's a socket layer that's responsible for
communicating with hdp clients
and it doesn't know how to handle requests
so it delegates that responsibility to a request
handler which is the second layer
the handlers responsible for
transforming a request string
into a response string
and it doesn't care where the request came from
or where the response is going
now we already have a handler module that
parses and router requests
and returns an appropriate response
we just need to set up some sockets
so that http clients can interface with our app
over the network
to do this we'll use a socket library that takes care
of all the low level details
but it won't be an elixir library
because elixir doesn't need to reinvent that wheel
early already has an excellent proven socket library
named jen tcp
and that library is pre installed with elixir
since gen is an urban library
the documentation for it is at urban
org dock and you'll notice right away at the
top it says urban
top now top stands for open telecast platform
which is misleading
because it's not specific to telecommunications
but earling was originally
designed for building telecommunication systems
and as often happens the name stuck
so why is top still relevant today
while it turns out
today's high availability systems have similar needs
the telecast systems including concurrency
fault tolerant capability and distribution
and since top was
designed as a general purpose framework
a set of libraries and patterns
it enables us to build these kinds of systems with
greater ease
now remember this all started some 20 years ago now
and in the meantime
top has evolved into a battle proven foundation
on which to build modern applications
so to find gntc we just go over to the left hand
nav here and click on modules
and we see a bunch of ruling libraries now
these libraries are written in ruling but we can call
any ruling library from elixir
because elixir code is compiled into bite code
that runs on the urging vm
and this is
huge because it means elixir is compatible with all
existing or lang libraries
we're looking for the gentle library
so we just scroll down
there's a ton of libraries inside of here
go down to the gen section
and by the way when you see gen underscore
it just stands for generic
so we're looking for gen tcp I'll click on it
and we see in the description it says
this module provides functions for communicating with
sockets using the to protocol
which is exactly what we need
now this first example down here
shows how to write in http client
but we're going to be using a browser as the client
we need to write the server side of this equation
so I'm going to go down
a little bit further and there's a server example
and I'm just going to copy this
and we'll use it as a starting point
then back over and sublime in the lib survey directory
I'm going to create a new file called http server
ex and then just paste in that code
now at first glance this looks familiar
we see functions matching what we saw in the diagram
so there's a listen function
an except function
there's this custom do receive function
to receive the data
that's just what this example used
we're going to change that to just receive in a minute
and then we have the close function
now these are ruling functions
and we can call them from elixir
but we need to convert or transcode
this code to elixir
this turns out to be a fairly straightforward
and instructive exercise
since as an elixir developer
you'll sometimes want to use
an existing early library
instead of reinventing the wheel
so it pays to know how to call early libraries
from elixir I'll paste it
again and comment out the earland code
so we can see the differences
so this first line here server
this is an earland function
so let's just change it to an elixir function
it doesn't take any argument so it's just def server do
and end now I'm going to scorch these over
there we go so this first line here
creates a listening socket it calls listen to do that
and it's going to be on port 5 6 7 8
and then it has some options
here's a list in square brackets
now since this code comes from erling documentation
it follows earling naming conventions
which are slightly
different from elixir
so let's walk through transcoding it to elixir
1st we have this tuple on the left hand side
and we pattern match it
against what we expect to be returned
from this listen function
now we're not going to worry about any air conditions
so we expect this to be successful
so we're going to get back ok and you notice ok
here is all lowercase
well name starting with lowercase letters
in early are atoms
in elixir we need to add a colon here
this is an elixir atom
then the second element in the tuple is this l sock
and this is the variable and it's going to be bound
to the new listening socket
the thing returned by the listen function
in variables in earling start with uppercase letters
but in elixir
they're lowercase letters
so we're just going to convert this to l sock
so that's it for the
tuple and if we come over here
we've got the erling module g and then the function is
listen well to reference earlier modules from elixir
we need to use a colon at the beginning here
so it's going to be colon g
and then to call the function
we replace this colon with a dot
so just like calling any function in elixir
we use a dot and then the function name
the module comes before it
but the only difference here is
erelong modules need to start with a colon
and they're all lowercase
then the listen function takes two arguments
the port number
and then the list of options here in square brackets
well again this is a
lowercase binary and we know that's an atom
in early in elixir we have to use a colon
the same way with packet
and active here
so now what we have is a list where the first
element is an adam binary
the second element is actually a tuple
where the first element is an atom and then a value
zero and then the third element in the list is
also a tuple active
and the value false
and that will work
but there's a more automatic way to do this in elixir
because we have a list of tuples
where the first item of the tuple is an atom
we can use an elixir keyword list
the way to do that if we just drop the curly braces
here and we put the colon on the other side of this
so it's packet zero
drop that curly brace then down here
take this off
coal and false
and drop that
and that's just the more significant way to do it
but internally it's represented as the same
list of two poles we started with
and don't worry about what these options mean
right now we'll come back to that in a minute
and then finally the last thing on this line is a comma
and in earl the body of a function is
one or more early expressions separated by a comma
but we don't need the commas in elixir
the 2nd line calls accept
which suspends it's a blocking call
and it waits to accept a client connection
on the listening socket which is this loss
and when a connection is established
this sock is bound to the new client socket
so let's go ahead and convert this
this is going to be the atom okay
this is going to be a variable sock
so lowercase an elixir
colon getup
dot except and this is just
l sock and we can remove the comment at the end
now on the 3rd line we need to receive the request
from the client by reading from the client socket
which is sock in this case
and you notice
this example uses the custom do receive function
so let's go ahead and convert it
this is going to be adam
okay this bin variable is going to be bound
to the request string
it's name bin because it's a binary string
it's a variable
so we're going to change it to a lowercase bin
then instead of calling do receive
right here we're going to call go tcp
there's a function called receive r e
we pass it in that client socket
and then instead of using a list here
we're going to pass in zero
that means we want to receive
all the available bites
so all available bites will be returned
and it will be bound to the variable bin
and then we can get rid of that comment at the end
now that we have the request string
here we can go ahead and close that client socket
so this is going to be the adam okay
getup dot clothes
get rid of that comma and this is just lowercase socket
and then the final line here just returns bin
that's the request string
so we're changes to a lowercase b
and we can remove this
dot at the end
in earning the dot means we're at the end of a function
but we don't need that in elixir
finally we know that
all elixir functions need to live in a module
so let's put this in a module
we'll call it survey htp server
there's our function
and there we go
now let's take our http server for our spin in sex
so we'll start with
survey dot top server
dot server that's the name of the function
alright
index hangs because it's waiting for a connection
so let's head over to a browser
and we're going to go to local host
and it's going to be 5 6 7 8
that's the port
he notices says this page isn't working
local hosts didn't send any data
well that's
because our example doesn't actually
send a response back to the browser
but if we come back and look at six
well we see that it prints the request
that was returned by that server function
remember
the server function just returns bin at the end
and that's the request that it got from
the receive so fix is just printing out
that request which is a string
and that's what we're seeing right here
and then it's done
because the server function only handles one request
this actually gives us a great start to finish it off
we simply need to
send a valid http response back to the client
and then loop
back to the accept line
to wait for the next connection request
so let's look at what a more
fully fleshed out server would look like
I'm going to paste some prepared
code to replace what's currently in this file
and then we're going to close the sidebar
just so we have more room
don't worry you'll find this code in the code bundle
so let's walk through it
we've got the same module served at
http server and then we have this function start
we name it start
rather than server as they did in the example code
and this just starts the server on the given port
of local host
and we've used a guard clause here
to make sure the port is an integer
and
also that the port number is above ten twenty three
and that's because ports zero through ten twenty three
are reserved for the operating system
so we need a port above ten twenty three
and we've used the guard claws to enforce that
then the first thing that happens is we call listen
just like we did in the example
and it's going to create a socket to
listen for client connections
and so this listen socket variable is bound
to the listening socket
as we saw before
listen takes two arguments the port
and then a list of options
so this is similar to the options we had before
but we've changed a couple of these
so what do these options actually mean
we don't have to really worry about these details
because you'll use
different options in different scenarios
but let's walk through these
this binary option
means we want to open the socket in binary mode
and deliver data as binaries
and then the second option is this packet raw
which means we want the entire binary deliver to us
without any packet handling happening behind the scenes
then we have this active false which
means we want to receive data when we're ready
by calling g receive
which we'll look at in just a minute
and then finally we have this
reused address set to true
which means we want to allow reusing the
address if the listener crashes
and these are pretty standard options for a simple
web server then we print out that we're listening for
connections on that port
and then we drop into the except loop
so this is just a function called except loop
we pass it the listen socket
and this is going to accept client connections
on this listen socket
we print out that
we're waiting to accept a client connection
and then we call
accept just like we saw in the example code earlier
remember it suspends or
blocks and waits for a client connection
and when that connection is accepted
then this client socket is bound
to the new client socket
so then
we just pronounced that the connection was accepted
and then we call this function serve
which is going to receive the request
off that client socket and send a response back
over that client socket
and once this returns
then we're going to call accept loop again
recursively to loop back up here
and wait for the next client connection
so let's dive into this serve function
well it takes the client socket here
pipes it into reed request
that's going to return the request as a string
then we pipe it
in this function generate response so we generate a
valid http response
and then we pipe it into right response
to write it back out
over that client socket
read request is pretty simple it calls gnpc receive
on that client socket passing in zero
which means we want all the available bites
then
the request is going to get bound to this variable
request which we return from this function here
so the return of this is our request string
which we then pipe into generate response
generate response just returns this
generic http response
you notice we're actually
ignoring the request here because we don't really care
we're just generating a
hear dock to return
a valid http response that just says hello
so that returns the response
here which gets piped into right response
if we have a look at that
it takes the response in a client socket
calls gntc send
on that client socket giving it the response
and we assume that that's successful
so we pattern match it to okay
we say hey we sent the response back
and then we closed that client socket
so then back up here
this pipeline here is done that's the serve part
this returns
and then we loop back up to accept loop here
which takes us back up here
and we're waiting for the next client connection
so this is basically what we saw
in the early example we
transcended earlier
we just added a bunch
of comments and some print statements
to demonstrate what's happening
we also added the part
where it sends a valid hdp response
back out
over the client socket
the other important
change we made is that we recursively call
accept loops so the server can continue to accept
new connection requests
now let's take this version of our code for spin and I
x
it's survey hd server
we called our function start and it takes a port
I'm going to use port 4000
you can use whatever port you want above ten
twenty three
okay it starts up
and we see that it's listening for connection requests
on port 4000
and it's waiting to accept the next client connection
that's that blocking call except right there
so now if we browse over to local host
4000 that's our port
I'm going to do slash bears
look at that we get hello that's our generic response
and back over an ix if we scroll up
it was waiting right here
but then when we sent the request in
the connection was accepted
it received this request right here for slash bears
so here's the full http request
and then it sent the response back out
our generic response here
and then it loot back up
and it's waiting for the next client connection
cool so our generic http server is going
through all the correct motions
now all we need to do is plug in our request handler
into this pipeline
so instead of generating a generic response right here
we want to call survey
handle handle
so what's going to happen
is read
request
is going to get the request from the client socket
then it's going to pipe that string
into our handle function
which returns the response as the string
and that response string is then piped into
right response
which sends the response back out
over the client socket
in other words
we've wrapped our handler in a thin
socket layer that lets
any http client interface with our server
so let's run this again
now my sex session is hung
because it's waiting for a client connection
so I'm just going to
control c twice to get out of that
and start ix back up again
then we'll start our server on port 4000 again
okay it's waiting for a client connection
reload local host 4000 slash bears
and look at that we get a list of all of the bears
cool so now we know it's calling our handler
so it works on their browser but now
any http client can interface with our web server
in fact
we can use the curl command line client to send an
api request so I'm just in a new terminal session here
I'm going to use curl
and then I'm going to give it http local host 4000 api
slash bears and we get back a json list of bears
that's pretty sweet
since earling has
been around for decades
it has an extensive set of tried and true libraries
this is something worth keeping in mind
if you don't find an elixir library to suit your needs
look for an earling library
odds are if it's a general purpose need
somebody has already written a library
and now you know how to use
any ruling library in your elixir wrap