let's say I'm the web
server we wrote in the previous section
and I'm a browser
and let's say I send you a request
well I handle the request
send back a response
and that works pretty good
if we only get requests once in a while
but let's say we get five requests at the same time
well right now I can only handle one request at a time
so I take the first one
send back a response thank you
take the second one
send back its response
but by the time I get to this 5th request
well
it's potentially been waiting in line for a long time
and the more requests we get the longer the line grows
here's that bottleneck in our server
where in the except loop function of the hdp
server file and as you'll recall this
except function here is a blocking call
it suspends execution
waiting for a client connection on this listen socket
and when it accepts a new connection
then the client socket is going to get bound here
and then we hand that off to this
serve function right here
which is going to go about the process of
actually handling the request and returning a response
so we have to wait for this serve function to return
before we can recurs calling except loop again
which takes us back up to this line
waiting for the next client connection
so let's simulate this problem with a request
that takes a relatively long time to handle
yeah we'll do that over in the handler module here
I'm going to paste in a new route up here
and the route is called hibernate
because that's what bears do
so we're going to pattern match on hibernate slash
and then
we want to hibernate for a certain amount of time
so we're going to bind the variable time
to whatever number comes after hibernate in that url
now that's going to be a string
so we're going to take the time
and then we're going to pipe it
into string to integer to convert it to an integer
and then we want to sleep for that amount of time
while earling has a module called
timer which we're calling right there
it has a function called sleep
that takes the number of milliseconds to sleep
so we're just going to pipe in
that time into the sleep function
and we learned how to use an earling
library in the previous section
then we're just going to return
a response with the status code of 200
and the bodies
just going to say
hey I'm awake
now to simplify the output a bit
I'm going to comment out this
log plugin up here in our pipeline
and then let's go ahead and fire up our server
we do ix mix
we're going to say serve hdp server
start and we're going to start it on port 4000 again
okay we've got our server running
now let's try sending it a request
so back in this
terminal session right here I'm going to use curl again
I'm going to send a request to 4000 api slash bears
so you notice we get back a response almost immediately
and the server is
now waiting to accept the next client connection
so now down in this window let's send a request
to hibernate so we're going to hibernate for 10,000
that's ['ten', 'thousand']millisecond
that's going to be 10 seconds
all right and it's hibernating
now if we try to run the api bears request
well we don't get an immediate response
this one's hung up
still doing its work and this one's waiting for it
and as soon as we get back awake from that
long running request
well then we also get the response for our api bears
so it doesn't handle the api request until
after the hibernate request has finished
yeah that's right
in fact we can see that if we scroll up
in the server output up here
so is waiting to accept a client connection
we sent in a request for hibernate 10,000
it received that request
then it sent the response back
saying it was awake
then it went back to waiting
for the next client connection
that connection was accepted and that was the
api bears request
and then it went ahead
and sent the response back for that
so if we look back at the code in our
server at this except line right here
if a client tries to connect to the server
while it's busy handling a long running request
which is going to get handled in serve
then the connection request gets put
in what's called a backlog q
and tell
the server finishes handling the current request
only then can it loop back
up to accept the pending client connection
and because we can only accept one connection at a time
the api request sat in the backlog for 10 seconds
and if the backlog fills up
by default it can only hold up to five connections
then any new connections are rejected
and this isn't good
we need to modify the server to handle
multiple requests concurrently
so that requests don't get delayed
we also have another problem we need to address
let's say an exception gets raised while
handling a request
well we'll simulate that with a new route
and I'll just paste it in above our hibernate route
here in the handler
and the path to this request is just slash kaboom
and then we use the
rays function here
to raise an exception with the string cab
now you could defensively add
some exception handling that catches this exception
and returns of 500 response
but let's just go with this for now
yeah I'll save that away and then back over here
I need to restart the server
now what happens if we send that can request
so I'll come down here
while we see the runtime error up here
in the server log cab
and you notice we're back at an ix session terminal
so sending in that request
it brought down the entire web server
if we come here and we try to run a request
for api bears
well it just hangs
so clearly our server isn't very fault tolerant
an exception or any failure handling just one request
makes the entire server go poof and impacts all
other requests
so we need a way to run each request concurrently and
keep each request isolated
that sounds kind of tricky
but it's actually
fairly straightforward using elixir processes
in fact this is where elixir really shines
in the accept loop function
we have this sequential code we call accept
and then we call serve and wait for it to return
and then we call accept loop again
which recuses back up
and we just go through here
lock step running these functions
but we want to run this function
this serve function right here is a separate process
asynchronously rather than sequentially
that's right
that way we can accept any new client connections
other requests while at the same time
handling the current request
in other words we can handle requests concurrently
so how do we run code as a separate process
well we use the spawn function
and there are two ways to call the spawn function
with an anonymous function and with a named function
let's just start with an anonymous function
and we'll do that over in our sex session
so spawn is defined in the colonel module
so it's automatically imported
which means we can just call spawn like that
and then it takes an anonymous function
so we'll use fn
and then inside of that function
we're just going to print out howdy
and if I hit return
while it ran this chunk of code
io put us howdy in a separate process
and we see that it printed out
howdy back here in sex session
and we also got this thing called a pid
that was returned by the spawn function
and the pid is a unique identifier
of the process that ran
in this case it was processed one sixty six
now yours is going to be different because well
it's a different process
now let's look at a slow motion replay of this
yeah let's do it again
this time I want to make a couple changes
I want to capture the pid
so we're going to bind
the pid to the pid variable on the left hand side
and then inside
here before printing howdy
I want to sleep for 5 seconds
so I'm going to call that timer module sleep function
again
and then to put multiple expressions on the same line
I'm going to use a semicolon right there
that way I don't have to do
multiline expressions inside six
so we're going to sleep for 5 seconds
and then print out howdy
and if we hit return
while we immediately get the pid back it's pid 170
and then the process is working on
this anonymous function so it slept for 5 seconds
and then when it was done it printed howdy
and we see that right here
so let's try that again
this time I'm going to change it to 10 seconds
and then we can check that it's running
there's a process module in elixir and there's a live
question mark function
we can call and pass it the pid
it's alive still alive
still alive
oop now we get back howdy so is it alive
no now the process has died
it printed out howdy and it's no longer alive
after running the anonymous function
the spawn process exited
a bit later we'll see how to use the pid
as an address to send messages to a process
but for now let's go back to our original problem
yeah you probably see where this is heading
we said we wanted to run this serve function
in a separate process
and now we know how to do that
we're just going to spawn a process
we're going to put an anonymous function
call serve just like that
and in this case we don't need the pid
so I'm not going to bind to it on the left hand side
so now once we've accepted a client connection here
we're just going to spawn a new process to
handle the request
which means we're going to drop back
into this accept loop
pretty quickly because this is going to run
asynchronously in the background
in fact since it's running in the background
I'm going to add some output
down here and serve
because this is going to get
run in that separate process
and we just want to see what pid is
actually doing all this work
so I'm going to use it
and I want to print the pit of the process
that's running this function
and the way you can do that is call self
that returns the pit of the current process
and then I'm going to need to interpolate it
like that and the pid structure we want to display
just in some way that's easy to see
and so I'm going to use inspect
so we're going to inspect the pid
that's going to give us basically what we saw in ix
and then I'm just going to say
working on it
now once we've spawned this
process it's going to be all on its own
we can essentially forget about the spawn process
because it has access to this client socket
through which it
sends the hdp response back to the browser
and once the response has been
sent while the process is going to exit
so what happens when we spawn a process that
doesn't use a socket
which is a more common scenario
well we'll look at that in the next section
for now let's just get a clean slate
by restarting it and the server
now let's try that hibernate request again
we'll hibernate for 10 seconds
if we look up here
we see we accept a client connection
but it almost immediately comes back
and starts waiting for the next client connection
even though this hibernate request is still running
so now let's send the hibernate request again
and
in a separate window we'll send a request for our api
and you see
we get a response back immediately for our api
before our hibernate request even finishes
and that's because the api request
was handled in a separate
concurrent process
so sending our cab request now
shouldn't affect the server or any other requests
yeah up in the server window
we see that the exception got raised
here's cab right here
but you notice we don't return to an tax session prompt
because the server isn't affected
it's still running and in fact it's still responsive
we can send requests in so I'm going to send one in for
just bears
right got that request and got a response right back
or api bears
the server still responding to other requests
and if we scroll up in the server
we should see the
bids of the processes that handled those requests
so here process 170 was working on it
here process one sixty nine was working on it
and I think you get the point
each request was handled by a different process
this is pretty cool
every client connection gets its own
process isolating the failure of one request
from another yeah
simply by wrapping some existing code in a spawn
function our web servers now more fault tolerate
and can handle multiple requests concurrently