so you might think
our request
handling process that we spawned previously
is the only process running in the uranium
but it turns out that elixir apps are made up of a
lot of processes
in fact
let's see how many processes are currently running
yeah to do that I'll fire up an ix session
and as we saw in the previous video
elixir has a process module
and we can call a list function
wow that's a lot of processes
we see all those kids
and it's a list of kids and in fact there's a
dot dot meaning there's a bunch more of these
so let's take this and we'll pipe it into enzyme count
and wow there's 83 processes currently running
so what are these processes doing
well to find out we could use this tool called observer
it's an early module observer
and the name of the function is start
and this is just the
gooey that lets us see what's going
on inside of the earlyn vm
and this system
tab just gives us some high level information
we see the number of cores on my computer
it's eight cores here
see over here
we've got the memory usage which is pretty cool
we've got the up time
well this has
only been up for 1min because we just started it
and we see the number of processes here
it says 98 processes
we're over here it said 83
but that's because when we started
the observer itself
it had to fire up some new processes
to let it do its work
to actually see which processes are running
let's go over to the process tab
and we get a full breakdown of
all the processes currently running in their early vm
now
if you look at the name of these processes they're not
recognizable as
any of our application code
so let's go ahead and sort this by name
just click on name here
and we'll click it again that way it's alphabetical
and you see all this stuff starting with elixir dot
while elixir modules in early are prefixed
with the name elixir dot
and so if we start at the top here we see
there's some stuff related to the
hex module
and we know that hex's elixir's package manager
so it has three processes here
just sitting in a loop doing something
not sure exactly what it is
but they're waiting on something there
then we see some processes related to is
and this one in the middle is an evaluate
and it's sitting in a loop
and it has the pid 150
well that shouldn't match our sex session
so if I come over here and use self
to get the current process as pid
well sure enough
our in session is pied 150 so that matches up
right here
then we see some processes related to elixir's logger
there's some processes related to mix itself
and then it gets
into some erelong functions here and if we scroll down
there's a bunch of stuff going on here
here's the processes related to the observer
I said when we fired up the gooey
the observer created some processes to do its work
well here are those processes
here's the thing
all elixir code runs in a process
so to demonstrate that
let's sort by pit in descending order
and then we'll go fire up our server
now let's send in a hibernate request for 10 seconds
okay we see the pit of the process that's working on
it is two o four thirty nine so if we come over here
there it is right there two o four thirty nine oh
and then that request is done
so this process should exit
and it'll get removed from this list
what's cool about the observer is that we cannot only
see what's going on in the early vm
we can also interact with our running application
for example
let's suppose we have a process that's gone rogue like
let's hibernate for a full minute
okay that's process 2 2 5 1 3 that's working on that
there it is 2 2 5 1 3
but we don't want this process gumming up the works
so let's go ahead and kill it
I'll just right click on this
kill that process
and boom it's gone
and as we saw in the previous section
the request handling process is isolated
so killing it doesn't crash the server
so if I just come
back over here
I'm just going to control c out of that and we run
api bears well we see that our server still responding
now
when we started the server from ix the server code ran
in the sex process
yeah let's find that again
here it is right here this evaluate
and we see that it's running the except function
which is waiting for the client connection
because that's what the server over here is doing
it's inexpert
just blocking waiting for that client connection
and because we ran it this way
it ties up the sex session
I don't have a prompt right here so we can't do
anything else in sex
but we could spawn the server
so that it runs concurrently
in its own process
and we know how to do that by calling spawn
all right because my sex session is tied up
I'm going to have to quit out of there
that kills the observer
because we started observer from
if I'll start fix up again
so instead of starting our server like this
we want to start it in this bond function
so let's capture the pid
we would call spawn
and we could give it an anonymous function
that does this
and we know that'll work
we saw that in the previous section
but remember
we said that you can call spawn in two different ways
with an anonymous function or with a name function
so let's use a name function
here to do that we drop the anonymous function
the first argument to spawn
is the name of the module service
http server the name of the second argument is then
the function to run
as an atom so it's going to be start
and then the third parameter is a list of arguments
so instead of passing an anonymous function
we pass it three arguments
the name of the module the name of the function
and then any arguments in a list
okay
and it starts up and it's listening for a connection
but because we spawn that in its own process
notice we have an ix prompt
ix isn't tied up anymore
because our servers running in a process
with the pid one fifty four
so now we can start our observer
we'll go over to processes
I'm going to sort this by name
and we're looking for the sex evaluate there it is
and now we notice
that the current function is not accept anymore
it's actually loop
because it's looping waiting for us to enter something
at the six prompt
but now we have this new process elixir server
has the pid one fifty four
which matches this pid over here
and it's sitting in an accept loop as we would expect
so now let's go ahead and send that hibernate request
again
we'll hibernate for 10 seconds
come back over here
I'm going to sort by pit
it's going to be the highest pit there it
is right there it's sleeping 3 2 5 9
which is the same as this one over here
all right and then it went away
so we saw that we had two
spawn processes in the observer
both the server itself and the one to hibernate
so what happens now if we kill the server itself
just right click
we'll kill that process
well it goes away
so if we try to send a request to hibernate
well it can't connect to our server
because the server is dead
but if we come up to fix well it's still running
and it has the same pid 150 that it's always had
so killing the web server didn't kill the sex session
that's right
but what happens if we do kill the sex session
let's over here
this evaluate that's sitting in a loop pit 150
let's kill it off
well this is interesting
notice our last six prompt was 6 3
it got this exit that pid was killed pid 150
and now we're back at 6 1
so it restarted an ix session automatically
in fact if we look at self now
it's not 150 as it was before
it's now 7 6 6 2
so it's a brand new process with a different pid
now it automatically restarted
because something
called a supervisor is monitoring the sex process
and the supervisor restarts lie
if it dies we'll learn more about supervisors later on
so we've seen that an elixir application is made up of
lots of isolated processes running concurrently
some of the
processes are spawned automatically when the app starts
and continue running for the life of the application
other processes are spawned on demand
and run for a relatively short amount of time now
unlike operating system processes
elixir processes are lightweight and
also fast to spawn
small
applications might be running hundreds of processes
whereas larger applications might be running
hundreds of thousands of processes
during peak times
all these
lightweight elixir processes are running inside
of an earland vm
otherwise known as beam
the vm itself runs in a single operating system
process that started when you start an elixir app
when the vm starts
it also starts a scheduler thread
whose job it is to run
each process can currently on the cpu
but running concurrently doesn't mean
that multiple processes run
at exactly the same time
the way it works is
that the scheduler allocates a slice of cpu time
to a process it's a tiny amount of time
when the time is up
the scheduler
preps or suspends the running process and
allocates time
to another process
and then another process gets its turn and so on
in this way the scheduler
actually switches between processes so fast
that they appear to be running simultaneously
consider this diagram like a very slow motion replay
the upshot here
is that a long running process won't tie up the cpu
every process gets its fair share
here's where the story gets
even better
it's unlikely that your computer has just one cpu
in fact you saw in the observer gooey
that even our aging laptop has multiple cpu cores
to take full advantage of multicore computers
the vm actually creates one scheduler thread per
cpu core
so a four core computer will have four schedulers
in each of those schedulers
is running multiple processes concurrently
which means at any given point in time
four processes are running at exactly the same time
in other words they're running in parallel
we hope this gives you an appreciation
for what's happening
inside the early vm when you call spawn
it's pretty incredible
the way the vm
takes care of scheduling processes across multiple
cpu cores
as to achieve both concurrency and parallelism
all the while
keeping the application responsive to new demands
in the next section we'll see how processes communicate
via messages