hey folks we're out on the refuge today
playing around with some fancy new technology
trail cams we're positioning three of these at
different areas around the refuge
then to keep an eye on things
we can get a snapshot image from each
camera by sending a request
to an api
we're back in the studio
and you can see that we've added a video cam
ex file here and as usual you'll find
this and other prepared files in the code bundle
in this file just to find a module called video cam
that simulates sending a request to an external api
then we can get a snapshot image from a video camera
so the functions called gets napshot
we give it a camera name
and
here you would put the actual code to send a request
to that external api
but we're not going to worry about that
we're just going to simulate
that it can be relatively slow
by sleeping for one second
and then it's going to return some response
and so we've got an example response
that would be returned
from that api
we just take the camera name
add a hyphen dashnapshot
jpeg
now we're just returning the file name of this napshot
but you can imagine that it would return a full
url to a file living on an image server somewhere
so if we call that function
I'll just pass in cam one
well it takes a second to get a response
and it just returns that file name
same for cam two
we just get a different file name after a second
and cam three
and in handler dx we already have a
snapshot's route that gets us three snapshots
yeah it calls that function three times
so we get back three
different file names
we then put those file names into a snapshots list
and then we inspect that list
and that makes up our response body
we won't worry about how the images would get
rendered on a page
just so we can stay on topic
and you'll notice we could call that
get snapshot function
from the video cam module
and that's because we have that aliased in
up here at the top
alias survey videocam
now let's spawn the server in its own
process so we can continue to use iex
and we learned how to do this in the previous module
in this case we'll call spawn with the named function
so it's going to be our module hp server
the function is going to be start
and then we give it a list of arguments
we're going to start it on port 4000 again
then over in a different terminal session
we can send a request to get the snapshots
it's just going to be a request
to local those 4000 slash snapshots
and we have to wait for the request
and it's going to take a full
3 seconds to get back the response which
is at the list of those file names
so it shouldn't be any surprise that it takes 3 seconds
because the route calls to get snapshot function
three times and we know that each api request
takes one second
ah but we know how to do this more efficiently with
processes as we saw iex runs in its own process
and while in iex we spawn our http server
so the server is running in its own process
then when we send a request to our server
safer bears
it spawns another process to handle that request
and once it is send a response back to the client
that process exits
in the same way
our new requests for snapshot spawns yet another
process to handle that request
right now in that process we send three
api requests sequentially
and since each request takes one second
the process has to wait a full 3 seconds
before sending back a response
instead we can spawn each api request
in its own process so they run in parallel
so processes can spawn other processes
and that way the request handling process will
only take as long as the slowest api request
which in our case is just one second
in our route function
we know how to spawn an api request in its own process
so here's the function we'll just call spawn
give it anonymous function there
run that
get snapshot function inside of the anonymous function
and what's going to happen if
we do this
well let's copy it out and just try it in iux
so I'll paste it in
I need to change this to use
servy dot because we don't have the alias here
it return
and it creates a process and it's going to run
that get snapshot function in that process
but we just see the pid right here
that's what's returned by the spawn function
but we don't see the value that's returned by
the get snapshot function
that's going to be the file name
we just get the pid
because that's what's returned by the spawn function
so now back over in our handler file
this really isn't snapshot one
this is a pid so let's call it pid one
but now we've got a problem right
we've got a pid but what we really need is snapshots
we need to create a list of snapshots or file names
so we need some way to return
the file name that's returned by this
get snapshot function
to the process that spawned it
in this case
that process is the one that's running this
route function
so we have two processes and since
one process spawned the other
you can think of this process as the parent
and this process is the child
this process gets a file name from an external api
and then needs to send that file name to this process
but how can it do that
if the processes run concurrently and
don't share anything
well you can think of processes as being kind of like
people we're all doing things concurrently
and we often need to communicate asynchronously
allowing each person to carry on
uninterrupted with whatever they're doing
how do we do that
while we send each other
a synchronous messages such as emails and text
which end up in some kind of mailbox
likewise each process has a mailbox
it's created when the process is created
in our case we're
only concerned with messages sent to the
parent process
so we'll focus on its mailbox
each mailbox has an address
it's the pid of the process
to send an asynchronous message
to the process's mailbox
we call send with two arguments
the pit of the process to send the message to
the parent pid in this case and the message to send
messages can be any elixir term
for example we could just send the file name
but it's common to use a tuple
to tag the message with some identifier
an atom we've arbitrarily chosen to tag it as result
but it could be anything
sending a message puts that
message in the process's mailbox
not unlike how you decide when to check your mailbox
a process gets decide
when it wants to read its messages
when it's ready it calls receive with a block
inside the block we use patterns to match messages
when a message matches this pattern
the process acts upon it in this case
we simply want to extract the file name and return it
and because the receive
function returns the value of the last
expression in the matching claws
we can bind it to a variable
having matched this message
it's removed from the mailbox
now what we really want to do is spawn three
processes all at once so they run in parallel
each process will send the final
name it got from the external api
back to the same parent process
when the parent is ready
it reads the messages one by one
by calling receive three times
once for each message
in this way the parent process can collect
all the file names in a list
you'll often hear this
referred to as the actor model of concurrency
each process is an actor living in its own independent
isolated little world
it doesn't share anything with other processes
the only way processes can communicate
is by sending and receiving messages
let's give this a whirl in iex
we want to spawn a process and have it send a result
back to the parent process
so who's the parent process
well
we're going to do the spawning from this iex session
so it's the parent process you remember
you can get the pit of the current process by calling
self so the iex session process is pied to 48
and I'm going to sign that
pid to a variable call to parent
and I'll explain why in a minute now
we can spawn a process and use that pid
to send a message back to the iex process
and to do that we use the send function
we want to send it back to the parent
so we give it the parents pid
and then we give it the message
in this case our message is going to be a toople
but as the coal said you can use any elixir term
so we're going to use a toople
we're going to tag it with result
again that's just arbitrary you could use any tag there
and then we want to put in our actual file name
so I'm going to use one snapshot jpeg
in spawn returns immediately and gives us the pid
so the spawn process is pid two seventy eight
but that's all the output that we get
but we know that calling sind
is going to put this message
in the mailbox of the parent which is this pid
so let's just take a peaky peak at that mailbox
and we can do that by calling the process modules
info function
and this just lets us query
different attributes of a process
so we want to look at the parent process
and we want to see what messages are in your mailbox
and we see that there's one message it's right here
now you notice it converted into a keyword list
we used a two pole right like that
but it just displayed it as a keyword list
in any event the mailbox has one message
now when you use process info this way
it just shows us what's in the mailbox
it doesn't actually take out any of the messages
at this point the spawn process is long gone
its only job was to send a message back to the parent
then it exited
and we can let the message sit in the mailbox
until we're ready to do something
with it messages will remain in the mailbox
until they're explicitly received
or the process the parent in this case terminates
now let's say we're ready to receive the message
and to do that we call receive and we give it a block
and I'm just going to have multiple lines here in iux
I'm just going to hit return
and then inside of that block
we need a pattern that
matches the message in the mailbox
so it's a tuple
has the atom result
then it has a file name and we want to bind that
to a variable
I'm going to call it file name
and when the message matches that pattern
we want to return the extracted file name
so we just do that
and then we'll just in the block
and we see the result is one snapshot jpeg
so when we call receive it
examine the message in the mailbox
it match this pattern
so this becomes the result of the receive function here
and that's why we see the value one snapshot jpeg in ix
once we've received the message
it's removed from the mailbox
so if we try this again
the mailbox should be empty and sure enough it is
let's in another message with a different file name
I'm going to call it two snapshot
and then I'm going to receive it on one line
so the pattern is result
capture the file name
return the file name end
and it match that message to snapshot
and now the mailbox is empty again
so what would happen if we call receive
before a message actually arrives in the mailbox
well to set that up
we'll have this bond process sleep for 15 seconds
before sending the result
so I'll change this to three snapshot just to make it
different
and then before we do the sin I'm going to use timer
sleep 15 seconds
and just put us in my colon
so we have two expressions there
we're going to sleep
and then we're going to do the send
now let's immediately peek in the mailbox
well it's still empty and now let's call receive
well it looks like it's just hanging there
and it's hanging because receive is a blocking call
it's waiting for a message to arrive in the mailbox
if you call receive
and the mailbox doesn't contain any matching messages
then the current process which is ix in this case
suspends until a matching message arrives
and then finally after 15 seconds we get the message
receive is patient though
it would have waited indefinitely
now what happens if we spawn three processes that each
send a message to the parent's mailbox
first we'll send snapshot two
then we'll send snapshot one
then we'll send snapshot three
and then we'll have a look in the mailbox
well now we have a list of messages in the mailbox
and they're ordered in the same
order in which we sent them
we sent snapshot two first
then snapshot one then snapshot three
so that gives us a snapshot two
and it's removed from their mailbox
snapshot one and then snapshot three
now notice the messages are received in the same
order they arrived in the mailbox
in other words it's first in first out
or first in first received
in the mailboxes once again empty
okay so when we started
why did we assign the parents pid to a variable
and then we sent a message to that parent
so why can we have just use self right here
we see that it spawns a process
so if parent and self are the same thing
then the message should be in the parent's mailbox
hmm but the parent's mailbox is empty
well it turns out this is a really common mistake
remember that
self returns the pid of the current process
so when we call self up here
the current process is this iexcession process
and it returns the pid of that process
but calling self inside of
this spawn function right here
is going to return the pid
of that spawn process
so parent and self aren't the same thing
when this spawn process runs
it's important to keep in mind that the pid return by
self changes depending on where it's called
when it's called here
it's going to be the iexcession process
it's going to be the process that's being spawned
that's why we had to save the value of self
before spawning the process
because self's going to change
but parent won't change because we've saved it off
if we send to self
then the message is put in the mailbox of the spawn
process but then that mailbox gets destroyed
when the spawn process exits
so unless you really want to send a message
back to yourself
you typically won't call
self inside of a spawn function
to send a message
instead you'll have a variable something like a parent
that you're going to send the message back to
now we know how to solve our original problem
yeah when we spawn this process
we need to send a message
back to the parent process
which is the process
that called this route function in the first place
and that message is going to include the result of
calling get snapshot
now let's just focus on the first api request
so we can actually comment out these other two cameras
and we want to send a message back to
the parent process so the first thing we need to do
is save off that parent process
we'll save the parent equals self
and in this context this is the
request handling process
that's the process we spawn in http server
that runs the route function
now you might see this referred to as the caller
since it's the pid
of the process that called this function
but to stay consistent we'll keep the name parent
then when we spawn this process
we want to send a message back to that
so we will send
to the parent
the result of calling this function
but we're going to wrap it into tuple
so it's going to be result
and then the second
element in that tuple is going to be
the result of calling gets napshot
and we don't need this pid
so I'm just going to get rid of this on the front
then once we spawn that process
we'll immediately call receive
and wait for the message to arrive
so we'll say snapshot one
equals receive
we'll put in that pattern
return the extracted file name
just like we did before
now it's important to note that this receive
is getting called in the parent process
because in the parent we want to wait
for the message to arrive
from that spawned process
and because we only expect one kind of message
we just need to pattern match on that message
now processes can send and receive multiple
different kinds of messages
as such
receive can match messages against multiple patterns
similar to how a case expression works
with multiple clauses
we'll actually see an example of that
in the later section
for now though we just need one pattern
then once we get that final even snapshot one
we just need to remember to return
snapshot one here
because we don't yet have a list of snapshots
we just have one
so if we save that away
now we're going to need to restart our server
so I'm just going to restart ix
then we'll spawn our server
then we'll send a request for snapshots
and it should return a file name
and indeed it does
and that's pretty cool
this is a great start
now we just need to do the same
thing for the other two cameras
so let's go ahead and duplicate the code
because it demonstrates something interesting
now don't worry we'll clean this up later
I'm just going to copy these two lines
we'll get rid of this comment here
I'm just going to paste in what I copied
so this is going to be for cam two
and then we'll get snapshot two
I'll paste it again
this is going to be for cam three
and we'll get snapshot three
then we can uncomment this list
so we put snapshot one
two and three in a list
and then we just need to return
that list so we'll call inspect on
snapshots now
so save that away
we'll restart our server again
and what could go wrong
let's go ahead and send the request
whoa it still takes 3 seconds
why well because remember that receive blocks
right we send one request
and then wait for the result calling receive
before sending the next request
so even though each
process runs concurrently
our code is effectively serialized
now this is fairly obvious because of the duplication
but it serves as a warning to be mindful of blocking
calls that become synchronization points in your code
and receive is one of those blocking calls
to fix this problem
all we need to do is rearrange the code
so that we spawn the process as first
then receive all the messages
so I'll take this bond and move it up here
same with this bond
and then we'll do all the receives after that
so now
all the processes are going to get spawned at once
this is going to happen really fast
and then we wait for the three messages
the fastest api request
is going to send a message first
so it's going to be the first one in the mailbox
and then the next fastest
and then finally the slowest one
but overall
since the processes are running concurrently
we only have to wait as long
as the slowest api request
which in our case is just one second
so now if we save this away
restart the server again
and now let's try that request one final time
and we get all three snapshots in just one second
each of the processes are running in parallel
which is really sweet
to coordinate a synchronous work
all we had to do was spawn
sand and receive
now it's worth recognizing that this
only works because the individual api requests
don't depend on each other
and when you have independent chunks of work like this
that you can run in parallel
will buy all means
take full advantage of the power
of elixir's concurrency model
in the next section
we'll remove the duplication we see here
and discover an abstraction for running
any task asynchronously