we're back out here on the refuge
and in addition to our trail cams
we've also installed some sensors
to report the gps locations of our wild things
and to get the gps coordinates
we're going to need to send more requests to another
api now in the last section
we send a request in api and ended up creating a lot
of duplication
if we send more requests
we're probably going to end up with more duplication
so we'll create an abstraction to tidy that up and make
all of our tasks easier
back here in the studio
we see that to get a snapshot we have to do two
spawn of function
that sends the result back to the parent
and wait for
and return the result to the parent process
so we've got a fair amount of duplication to get these
three different snapshots
but looking at this code
the only thing that varies between one and the other
is just the argument to this get snapshot function
which is the camera name
so let's encapsulate these two things
in functions
and we'll put them in a new module named fetcher
so we'll put it in the lib survey
create a new file
fetch your dx
then we need to hoist some coat over from handler so
we need these
two lines where we get the parent and a spawn
so I'll paste those in here
come back over here and we also need a receive block
then we'll partition this code into two functions
since we do these two things at
different times
we're going to put this first part in a function
called async
since it's going to run a function asynchronously
so it's a sync
and we're going to pass in the camera name
and then where we reference this camera
we need to pass in camera name there
we also need to change this to survey
com because we don't have that aliased in this file
and I'll remove this comment
because the parent could be
any process not just the request handling process
and then we'll put this receive block
in a function named get result
and I can remove this assignment
because I just want to return
the return value of receive
so this will block
if a matching message isn't in the mailbox
otherwise it will return the file name immediately
so after calling a sink we can do whatever we want
and then at some later time
we can get the result by calling get result
so what's nice
about this fetcher abstraction is that a person
using it doesn't need to know
the structure of these messages
for example we used this tuple with a result
at the beginning
and then the result of the expression
and then we matched it down here
but because those are only maps inside of this file
the person that's using this module
doesn't need to know how these messages are structured
at all
so we'll save that away then back over and handler
at the very top we're going to alias this in
and then down in our route
we want to go ahead and use that
so we can get rid of this
because that's in that acing function
and we want to change
all of these to use that acing function
in the same way we want to change all of these
to call our get result function
instead of having a receive block right here
then we'll save that away
then over an ex we'll fire up our server
and we don't need to run it in a separate process this
time
and then if we go over to a new terminal session
well it should work just as before
all we've done is move some code around
and sure enough
we get back all the results in one second
just like before
let's take it a step further
right now the fetcher module can
only be used to get a video cam snapshot
because that's what the spawn function does
but you can probably
see how we can arrange things so that we can spawn
any function yeah to do that
instead of calling this specific function
here we want to be able to call any function
what we're going to do is
we're going to
pass in the function instead of the camera name
so I'm going to name this fun that's going to be the
function that gets passed in
and instead of running this function here
we'll just run the past in function we can do that fun
just like that
so whatever this function returns
is going to be part of the message
and then
because the message isn't specific to file names
I'm just going to change this variable here to value
now it'll work without doing this
but it just makes it more generic to see hey
the function returns to value
and that value is part of the message
now the name fetcher doesn't really work anymore
but just go with us here for a minute
then back over and handler
we need to change how this acing function is called
making sure to pass it a function
just like that
so now it's more generic we can pass in any function
if we save that away
go restart our server
just run a quick sanity check here
cool that works too
now let's suppose we want to send a request to
another api let's create a new file called tracker ex
and then we're going to paste in some code
the tracker module simulates sending a request
to an external api
to get the gps coordinates of a wild thing
it's some amazing technology
and it looks a lot
like the video cam module that you saw earlier
here we call get location
for a wild thing and get back
its gps coordinates as an elixir map
so we
want to call this get location function from our route
so back over in handler
let's go ahead and rename this route from snapshots to
sensors since now we're acquiring multiple sensors
and to get the location of bigfoot asynchronously
we can use fetcher since it can take any function
so right down here we'll call fetcher
a sink
with a function
in this case it's going to be a survey tracker
I don't have this aliased in
so I've got to use survey there
get location I'm going to pass in bigfoot
and then we'll get the location by calling
get result since it's also generic
so I'm going to call this
where is bigfoot
fetch your dot get result
now we want to include this in our response body
so down here I'm just going to inspect
we've got snapshots right there
I'm actually going to put it in a two pole
so the first element is going to be our snapshots
and the second element is going to be where is bigfoot
now if we restart our server
and then send a request this time for sensors
hmm something went awry there
we get back a tuple as we would expect
and the first element is supposed to be a
list of our snapshot images
so there's the list right there
and the second element is supposed to be
a map a linear map of the gps coordinates
but the coordinates actually ended up in the snapshot
list and where our coordinates were supposed to be
we have a snapshot image
so what went wrong
well if we look back at the code
we spawned four processes
each of which sent a message
back to the parent process's mailbox
but they came back in a
different order than we expected
why well even though we spawned the track or last
its response came back the fastest
right if we look at its code over here in tracker
well it
only sleeps for five hundred milliseconds
half a second
so it was the first message to arrive in the mailbox
therefore back over here this first call to get result
returns the location
not the snapshot so this isn't going to be a snapshot
and remember how our get result function is implemented
the receive is going to match any message
with this pattern
and all process is spawned by a sink
send a message with that pattern
so calling get result
will simply receive the next message in the mailbox
or wait for a message
if one hasn't already arrived
a hack would be to get the gps location results first
but that's exactly what it is just a hack
because processes run concurrently
there's no guarantee of the order in which
the messages are sent
who knows how long it might take to
actually locate bigfoot
yeah we need some way to tie the call to get result
to the spawn process that produce that result
so this result should come from this spawn process
the one where we call get location for bigfoot
when we call get result here we want snapshot one
well that's this spawn function
snapshot two is this bond function
and you guessed it
snapshot three is that spawn function
if we can tie those together
then it won't matter the order in which we call
get result it will always get the result
for the process that spawned it
to do that
we need to uniquely identify a process and we
actually know how to do that
it's by its pid
yeah when we call a sink here
remember looking at the implementation of that
the last call in this acing function is to spawn
and we know that spawn
always returns the pid
so the return value back here is going to give us a pid
so I'm going to sign this to pid one
pit two and so on
now to tie them together
let's suppose for a minute
this isn't going to work just yet
but let's suppose that the get result function
takes a pid as the argument
and returns the result
for that process we would say okay
for bigfoot we want to pass in pid four
we want its result
this would be pid one
pit two
and pit three
well that would be ideal
then the ordering wouldn't matter
let's step away from fetcher for a moment and hop
into sex to see
how we'll make this work
I'm going to have to quit it that I get back
to a prompt
so let's sort of simulate what's happening inside
of our acing function
the first thing it does is set up the parent
and it just assigns it to self
that's the calling process or the parent process
and then as we just saw the last
line of our acing function called spawn
and returns a pid
inside of the spawn function
it just sends back to the parent
some message
right now it looks like this result
and I'll just put in a hard coated snapshot
so that's the way it currently works
but what we'll do is include
the spawned process is pied
in the message that it sends back to the parent
so the tuple currently has
two elements result in the image
we want to put a new element on the front of this
we could put it anywhere
but we're going to choose the front of it
and it's going to be the pid of this spawn process
well how do we get the pid of the spawn process
well we call self
it always returns the pid of the current process
and so when spawn is called self in this context
is going to be the pid of that process
which is going to be the same thing as pit one
but we're including it in the message
so that we can pick it up on
the received side of things
so in this case I'll send a snapshot
then I'm going to send a second message
this time instead of sending a string
I'm going to use
an elixir mat where we put our coordinates in there
I'm just going to use x one
y is two
doesn't really matter
we just want something different than a snapshot name
and I need to change this pid over to pid two
and then for the third message
I'm going to send another snapshot
we'll just call this one snapshot one
so that it's different and this will be pid three
okay now let's peek inside of the mailbox
that's the parent's mailbox messages
okay cool we've got three messages inside of here
and you notice that each of the message tuples
has a pid as the first element
so snapshot three was one fifty eight
and that's right one fifty eight there
our coordinates were one sixty one that matches up
and one sixty three is our final snapshot
so as I said calling self inside of here
is going to be the same pid that gets returned here
and we see that
so now suppose we want to receive the message
with the gps coordinates
what we do receive
and then the pattern we want to match is
a pid
and then the atom result and then our coordinates
which I'll just call cords
when that matches
we just want to return the coordinates
but the question is what pid do we want to match
well the coordinates are here
one sixty one and that's pid number two
one sixty one
so this should be pid two
but not so fast
this is a variable
and we don't want to bind that variable
to the value that's in the message
which would be this pid
instead we want a pattern match
pid too's existing value
which is this pid structure right here
so to do that we need to use the pin operator
that's that carrot right there
and that's going to
match against the variables existing value
not bind it to a new value
so this is saying that this
must match the exact value of pid two
and if we do that
well receiver turns the matching message
even though it's not the first message in the mailbox
it was actually the second message in the mailbox
that's right if the first
message doesn't match
it continues examining the remaining messages
until it finds a match
and if it doesn't find a match at all
it waits for a new message to arrive
now back in handler
we need to make a couple changes to make this work
remember I said passing a pid in the get result
won't work yet
so let's go ahead and make the changes
so that will work
so over in fetcher
the first thing we need to do when we're sending this
message back is include the
spawn process is pid
just like we did in ex
it's going to be self right here
then our gib result function needs to take the pid
and then
pattern match against it using that pin operator
so what happens is
we call self to get the spawn process as
pit and stick it in the message
that's going to be the same
value as the pid returned by spawn
which is the return value of sync
so when handler calls a sync it gets that pit back
then it uses that pit when it calls get result
so in this case get result pit one
that gets passed in
and then we pattern match against it
so this will only receive messages that were sent by
this bond process
now we need to make sure to save this away
also need to save away the handler
because it's currently not saved
and we're ready to fire up our server one more time
to make sure we have a clean slate
I killed everything and then I'll fire up ix again
and then restart our server
now if we send a request for sensors
well everything's in the right order
we have all of our snapshots in that first list
and we have our gps coordinates as the second
element of that tuple
so that fixed it
now in the case of snapshots we have three
calls to a sink
and three calls to get result
it turns out there's
a more concise way to do this using a pipeline
yeah let's rearrange things a bit here to set that up
we want to put these inside of a list
so let's get rid of the p
and this will be a list
I need to put a comma here and a comma here
just like that
so what this is going to do is spawn three functions
one for each camera
and we're going to end up with a list of three pits
now what we can do is take that list of pids
and pipe it into emu map
and for every one of those kids we want to call fetcher
get result we know how to do that
we can use the capture operator to do that
it's just going to be fetcher
get result
and then we can either use
ampersand one like that
or as we learned earlier
there's a shortcut we can just use the reality one
so for every pit in this list it's going to call
get result with that pid
and when all the process is finished
while we've collected
a list of three file amps fact
we'll just go ahead and assign that to snapshots
and then we can get rid of that down here
and get rid of all the get results
so this will work
but you notice we're just calling
get snapshot three times here
passing it in a different argument each time
so we can further refine this
what we'll do is create a list of camera names so
cam one
cam two and cam three
and then instead of calling this three times
what we want to do is pipe that list into a new map
and for every one of those camera names we want to call
this fetcher acing function
passing it the function calls get snapshot
and then instead of cam three right here
while we just want to pass in
the next camera name from this list
and then we pipe that into get result
which calls get result
for every one of the
kids that are in the list returned by this map
let's go ahead and save that away
we'll restart our server
give it a quick sanity check
and cool that still works
one advantage to this approach is that it
always calls git result
for each process
we don't have to remember
to call it a certain number of times
one disadvantage is our tracker process right here
doesn't get spawn until
after the snapshots have been received
which means we've created an unwanted
synchronization point in our code
again
we've got to wait for all these snapshots to come back
before we can then go figure out where bigfoot is
so in this case we want to spawn everything first
so I'm going to move this up here
we'll spawn the get location go look for bigfoot
and then we'll go ahead and spawn our get
snapshots we'll wait for the snapshots
and then by the time they're back
well we should have a result for bigfoot too
so we'll just get that result
now spawning a process for a one off
a synchronous task like this
and getting its result at a later time
is so common that elixir provides an abstraction
yeah similar to our fetcher module
elixir has a task module
it includes several convenience functions
two of which effectively do the same
thing as our fetcher
and because we designed fetcher the way we did
wink wink task is a drop in replacement
so let's change our route to use task
and I'll start with bigfoot here
we just change the fetcher module here to task
and similar to the acing function and fetcher
task has an acing function
it spawns a process that runs a function
then cind is called to send
that functions result back to the parent process
sounds pretty familiar
in similar to the git result function in fetcher
the task module has a function called a weight
and inside of that function there's a receive block
that matches and returns
the message sent by sync
now unlike the fetcher we don't get back a pid
when we call task a sink
we actually get back a task structure
so I'm going to call that task
and the struck just includes the parent process pid
it calls it the owner and also the trial process pid
and then it uses that task structure
to match up the spawn process
with the results we have to pass it in here
task sounds pretty familiar
then let's go ahead and change our pipeline to use
task as well so task here
don't have to change a sink but have to change this
over to a weight
cool so while we learned a lot writing fetcher
we don't actually need it anymore
don't you just love it when a plan comes together
yeah I do I also love removing these aliases
that's less code that we have to write
so I'll just remove that there
save that away
restart our server
send the request one final time
and it works just like it did before
but now we have less code to maintain
now you basically know what happens
under the hood of the task module
you'll want to use
task in situations where you need to run a function
a task asynchronously
in a short lived process
so in what other use cases our process is useful
well in the next section
we'll look at an example of a process that has a
longer life and responds to multiple messages