let's say we're running a pledge drive
to build a crocodile swamp on our refuge
gee I hope we don't attract a lock ness monster
people would pledge a lot to see that
in any event how's our server going to handle pledges
well to create a pledge
a name and an amount will be sent to our server
as a post request
we'll route that request to the create
action of a pledge controller
which will in turn
send the pledge information to an external service
via its api because
after all we're busy running a wildlife refuge
and can't be bothered to handle all
the intricacies of a pledge drive
you know like managing user accounts
charging credit cards and the like
so we'll let the external service handle all of those
details then when we want to get all the pledges
we'll send a get request to our server
we'll route that request
to the index action of the pledge controller
which will turn around
and fetch the pledges from the external service
but
suppose we're only interested in displaying the three
most recent pledges
not all the pledges
well rather than hitting the external service
every time we want to display recent pledges
we'll create an in memory cash
when pledges are created
will send them all to the external service
but only keep a cash of the three most recent ones
so when a new pledge comes in
we'll bump the oldest pledge out of
the cash and add the newest one in and in doing so
only keep the most recent three
then when the recent pledges are requested
we'll return them straight from the cash
now we already know how to handle git and post request
we've done that in previous modules
so we've prepared that code to give us a head start
in handler ex we've defined two new routes
so if we get a post request for pledges
we're going to delegate
to the crate action of a pledge controller
and if we get a get request for slash pledges
we're going to delegate to the index action of that
same pledge controller
and we went ahead and created the pledge controller
you see it over here pledge controller ex
it has a crate action and an index action
the crate action just captures the
name and the mount parameters
and then it needs to send that pledge information
to the external service and also cash it
so we'll do that in a function called
create pledge notice
it takes two arguments the name in the amount
and then in the response body we just say
name pledged whatever the amount is
then in the index action we need to get the reason
pledges from the cash
we're going to do that in a function
called recent pledges
the returns those pledges
and then we just inspect them
and put them in the response body
so we need to define two
functions this create pledge function and
recent pledges function
and it doesn't make sense to define those in this
controller module
so we'll define those functions in a new module called
pledge server
and then we'll call the functions on that module
so this is going to be
serve pledge server
and just take that
and we're going to call recent pledges on that
same module
now let's go ahead and create the pledge server module
it's going to be in the lib survey directory
plug server dx
servey dot pledge server
and then that first
function that we want is called crate pledge
it takes a name and an amount
and then what should this function do
well first
it needs to send the pledge to the external service
so let's say we have a function called
send pledge to service
we'll just go ahead and shuttle the name and the amount
over to that function
and then it's going to return a tuple
if it's successful it's going to be
the adam okay and then some id
it might be like a transaction id
of the pledge or the pledge id
just
some unique identifier that that pledge got created
we'll assume our pledge is always successfully created
but you can imagine returning a different tuple
and if there's an air
then you can use
a case statement to handle either the success
or the failure
okay now for this sin pledge to service function
I'm going to
make a private function for that sin pledge to service
and we're just going to stub this out
we're not
actually going to send it to an external service
so I'm not going to use the name
so I'm going to use underscore name
just so we don't get any compiler warnings and
underscore mount
and in the body of this well we would have some code
code goes here to send pledge
to external service
and then we'll just return a
canned response so it's going to be a tuple
we're going to assume it
always returns ok as the first element
and then we need an id
and just to make it interesting
I'm going to use a string
it's going to be pledged dash
and then we're going to generate our random number
just so that we have something unique here
and I'm going to use the rand module
that's an urban module
and it has a function uniform
and it will pass it 1000 and that will return
a random integer
uniformly distributed in the range from one to 1000
so we'll have like pledge
4 5 6 for example
so this
simulates sending the pledge to the external service
but this function
also needs to cash the pledge in memory
so the cash is just going to be a list
and inside that list we want our pledge information
and we're going to represent that as a tuple
the first element of the tuple will be the
person's name
and then the second
element will be how much they pledge
so larry pledge $10
so if crate pledge gets called with larry and tin
then our cash is going to look exactly like this
okay so what should our recent pledges function do
well it needs to return
the most recent
pledges and that's our cash
so if our cash is currently this list
then it would need to return that list
so sticking with our wildlife theme
here's the big crocodile in the room
where do we store this cash
so that the crate pledge function can update it
and then the recent pledges function can return
those pledges
well modules can't hold state
modules aren't like
objects in an object ornate language
that can hold state
in instance variables
ah but it turns out processes can hold state
in the pledge server
module will define a function named listen loop
that continuously receives and handles
messages in an endless loop
and will spawn a process that runs that function
in that server process will keep some internal state
a cash of recent pledges
when the process starts
its initial state will be an empty elixir list
when we get our first pledge
the request handling process will send a message
to the server process
with the pledge information
when the server receives that message
the pledge info
will get passed along to the external service
we won't concern ourselves with how that happens
more relevant
to our objective
the server process will
also add the pledge to the cash
which is the state managed by the server process
the server process will then send a message back
to the request
handling process
indicating that the pledge was successfully created
or not the request
howling process then
sends a corresponding http response back
to its client
for example a browser and the process dies
then when we get our 2nd and hopefully
subsequent pledges
the request howling process will send a message to this
same server process updating its existing cash
then when the recent pledges are requested
the request handling process will send a
different message to the server process
when the server receives that message
it will send a message back
that includes the pledges in the cash
so the server process will need to receive
and be able to handle different kinds of messages
this is pretty interesting
elixir processes can store state
and other processes can change
or retrieve that state by sending messages
stepping back
we see two different types of processes
each with specific roles
a server process is typically our long running process
that maintains state
and as we'll see later
can also perform arbitrary work concurrently
client processes on the other hand
send to and receive messages from the server