back in our pledge server module we'll come in out
create pledge and recent pledges for now
we'll come back to these later
but for now we want to start with the loop
I'm going to put that right up at the top here
and we need a function that continuously receives and
handles messages
in an endless loop
so we'll just call that function listen loop
you can call this whatever you want
and then we'll start off by printing out
waiting for a message
and then we need to receive block
so when listen loop is called
it turns around and calls receive
which will block
suspend the process
waiting for a matching message
to arrive in the process's mailbox
but remember
receive only processes one message in the mailbox
so to handle more than one message
after receiving a message we need to loop back
up to receive
so the server process can wait for the next message
and to do that
we'll recursively call listen loop right here
so we'll match the message then we'll run some code
and then we'll loop back up to listen loop here
which is going to say okay waiting for another message
and then it's going to block on this receive
waiting for the next message
okay so the first message we want to handle
has this pattern
it's going to have the atom create pledge
then the second element will be the name
and the third element will be
the amount
then in terms of the code what we want to do is
send that pledge at the external service
so I'm just going to paste that right there
so we just extract the name
and the amount from the message
and shuttle those through
to that function that sends it to the external service
and then I'm going to use a print out
name pledged
the amount
and then we loop back up to listen loop
now we also want to add the pledge to the local cash
which will be the state stored by the server process
well we want to do that
right after we've sent it to the external service
and our cash is going to be an elixir list
I'm going to say cash
here's the list
and then each element of the list is a tuple
so it'll be the name
and the amount of the pledge
but this is going to create a new cash each time
through this listen loop
because
this is just a local variable that we assign to here
so instead we need to
remember the cash and add to it each
time through the loop
because we want the pledges to end up in a single list
in other words we need the server process
to maintain the cash as internal state
now
we learned how to do that when we parsed http headers
earlier on in the course
we just need to pass the state which
is a list in this case
as an argument to this listen loop recursive function
now rather than calling this cash
I'm going to change it to be new
underscore state
so we set the new state and then we recurs with it
now for that to work
we need to change this listen loop
to take the state as an argument
and I'm going to call this one state
so some states going to get passed into the listen loop
and then down here
when we're creating the cash
what we want to do is put this name and amount tuple
as the head of the list state
so we're using the cons operator here
and this pledge is going to get added as the head
of this list which is our state
that's going to give us a new list
which we're going to assign to new state
and then we recurs with that
which
will become the value that gets passed in the listen
loop and the next pledge will become the head
of that new state
now for now to see the new state
we'll print it to the screen
so just after I print out the name of the mount
we'll print out
new state is
and then we'll call inspect
on the new state
so now that we have this
listen loop function
that receives and handles messages in an endless loop
we can spawn a process that run that function
for now we
just want to experiment with this server process
we'll actually hook it up later to our controller
so let's just spawn it in if
we know how to do that
we just call spawn
we're going to give it our module survey pledge server
then the name of the function we wanted to run
it's called listen loop
and then the third argument is
a list of arguments to send
to that function or to pass to that function
remember listen loop takes the initial state
we want the initial state to be an empty list
so we're going to pass in an empty list there
so we've got a list
that has an empty list inside of it
and the process is waiting for a message
we see the pit is one sixty five
now remember when we're in an ix session
we're already in a process
and now we want to send a message to the mailbox
of the spawned server process
so you can think of the ix session like a
client process
so to send a message to the server where we call send
and then we give it the pit of the server
and then we give it the message we want to send
looks like this
create pledge
we're going to say larry
is the name and $10
now you notice I didn't use parentheses right here
sin is a function
and you can use prostheses right there
but I think removing the prostheses
it just makes it clear
what those two arguments are doing so it's a pid
and then a message so you can do this any way you want
I'm just going to use this style for now
cool the message was received
we see the output of that disputes that we had
in listen loop
we also see that our new state is a list
with the tuple larry and tin
and then you also see this thing printed right here
which is the message
while this sin function
always returns the message that was sent
which is why we see this
in ix because it always prints out
the return of the function that you just called
and then our listen loop re back
on itself to wait for the next message
which is why we see waiting for message
so $10 isn't going to get us very
far on our crocodile pledge drive
so let's create another pledge
let's say mo gives us $20
okay we see the state was updated our cash now has
mo at the head of the list with $20 and then
larry is the second one in the list
now you probably notice when I hit return there
that sen didn't block waiting for a response
it simply puts the message in the
server process as mailbox
and then returns almost immediately
so we can carry on doing other things
while the server process handles the message
just remember sending a message is
always an asynchronous operation
curly wants to get in on the action two
so he's going to give us 30 bucks
cool now our cash has three pledges
and curly is at the head of the list
so because listen loop is a recursive loop
the spawn process never terminates
it runs continuously receiving and handling messages
and we see right now it's waiting for the next message
now you might be concerned that this recursive
loop would waste a bunch of cpu cycles
but most of the time
the process is blocked undeceived
and so the scheduler
preempts or suspends the block process
so it doesn't tax the cpu
we only have three pledges so far
so we really
don't have to worry about keeping just the most
recent pledges
but we'll get to that later
for now though
instead of the server process
simply printing the cash to screen
we want the client process which is ix right here
to be able to get the pledges in the cash
to do that the client will send a
different message that the server needs to handle
receive can handle various
messages using pattern matching closets
similar to a case expression
so we can just add a new pattern right here
the message is going to look like this recent pledges
it's just an atom there's no tuple
when it receives this message
it needs this in the cash which is the current state
back to the client process using send
and when we send back the cash
we'll wrap it in a message that looks like this
we'll just have the atom response
and then we need to send back the state
now you could just send back the state as the message
but we
tagged it as response just to make it less ambiguous
and then finally
although handling this
message doesn't update the state
it still needs to loop back with the current
unmodified unchanged state
because we haven't changed the state here
we just pass it back through
there's just one problem
what's the pig
well it's the pit of the client process
that's asking for their recent pledges
the server process needs to know the pit
of the client process
in order to send the pledges back
to it and remember
processes can only communicate via messages
so the client process that sends this message
must include its pid in that message
so we'll have the client process send its pid
as the first element in the message
we'll make this a tuple
and then the first element will call sender
and then whatever that first element is in the message
will be bound
to this variable sender
now
this doesn't have to be the first element in the tuple
but it's common for the sender to be the first element
so we're going to stick with that idiom
you can think of it like the return
address of the message sender
it's saying hey
send me the reply
then we can use the sender to send a message
back to that client process
and just to see what's happening
we'll print the sender to the screen
so I'll just say scent pledges to
and then I'll inspect the center
so now we have two patterns
which means receive will wait for a message
that matches any of those patterns
and just as with case
messages or pattern match from top to bottom
and the first pattern that matches has
its associated block of code executed
okay let's give this a whirl in ix
I'm just going to reload the
server module since we changed that
then I'm just going to clean that up
and now we can go ahead and respawn
our pledge server listen loop
we'll create a pledge for larry
there's one for mo
and finally there's curly
now at some later time
we want to get the recent pledges
so we can need to send
a message to our server process
and the message has two elements remember
the first one is the pit of the process
that the server should
send the response back to
well we wanted to send response back to
this process the ix process
we can get that by using self
and then the second element of the message
is just this atom
recent pledges
okay
we see the output that the server sent the pledges to
pid one sixty three
that's our ix process id
so let's pick in our mailbox we use that info function
the pit is self and we want the info
we want to see the messages
and sure enough we have a message
tag response and it's a list of our pledges
now that
just let us peek at the messages in the mailbox to
actually receive the messages
from the client's mailbox
we need to call receive
from the client process
and we're in the client process
because we're in the secession
so receive due the pattern we want to match is response
and then we'll bind whatever value is at this place
in the message as pledges
you can call that whatever you want
and then we're just going to extract that and return it
as the return of the receive statement
and we get back to the list of pledges
now we use ix as the client process
just to experiment with the server
but ultimately the client process
will be a request handling process
that spawn from our web server
so when we get a post request for pledges
this function is going to be run
in the request handling process
so it's going to be the client process
that calls create pledge
and if we get a get request for recent pledges
then this function is going to run
in a request handling process
so it's going to be the client process that calls
recent pledges
for this to work we need to implement these
two functions create pledge and recent pledges