in the previous video we used fix is the client process
to send messages to the pledge server process
we've mimicked what we did in sex by adding some
code to the bottom of pledge server ex
it's outside of the pledge server module
just right down here
and in addition to larry moan curly
we've added two more pledges
for a total of five pledges
then we send a message to get the recent pledges
and we've got a receive block
that picks those up
and if we run that
well sure enough we have our five pledges
so in this context we have two processes communicating
all this code outside of the pledge server module
right here is going to run in the client process
and then the server process is this
listen loop that gets spawned
okay so now we want to encapsulate
creating and getting recent pledges
in these commented functions right here
so let's just start with this first one crate pledge
so right now
it's sending the pledge to the external service
and then cashing it
but that happens up inside of our
listen loop which runs in the server process
right here
so what the create pledge function needs to do
is just send a message to our server process
send to a pit
and the message is
create pledge
name and amount
and for that to work
we're going to have to pass in the pid
we'll pass it in as the
first argument to this function
so this is going to run in the client process
and then
this part is going to run in the server process
down here now we can call our crate pledge function
so we call pledge server
create pledge
the first argument needs to be the pid
of the server process and that was returned by spawn
so we have a pid variable already
just like that
we save that away
well it works just like it did before
now let's implement the recent pledges function
and I'm going to take
this code here with us
let's right up here
we'll uncommon it
and the body of that function
we need to do two things
we need to send a message to the server process
and then immediately wait for a response message back
from that server
so this function also needs to take a pit
we'll send to that pid the message
recent pledges telling it a send the reply back to us
and then we'll
have a receive which picks up the pledges
and instead of doing io and spec right here
I just want to return the pledges
and so because this pattern matches
we run this it
gives us the pledges and that's implicitly going to be
the return value of the function
recent pledges
now something to keep in mind here is although the sin
is a synchronous sending
a message is always a synchronous
receive is a blocking call
it's going to wait for a response from the server
so this function as a whole
is going to be synchronous
so now down here we can replace all this with
pledge server
recent pledges
passing that pid
and that's going to return to us the pledges
and I'm just going to use io
inspect to inspect the returned list
save that away
run it again and we still see all five pledges
but we only want to get recent pledges
which we'll say is the last
three pledges or
the first three pledges in the list
we'll fix that up here
when we get a new pledge we want to take
the two most recent pledges
and add the new pledge to the head of the list
so that the new state has three pledges
so to do that we'll add a line here
let's say most recent pledges
and the menu module has a take function
we want to take from the state that's a list
the two most recent pledges
so that's going to give us a list that has at most
two elements inside of it
and then we want to put
the new pledge at the head of that list
so here's the new pledge that we're adding
we're going to add it to this list
and that's going to give us at most
three elements in the list
save that away
run it again
and sure enough we've got grace daisy and curly
so now that we have this running and we feel really
comfortable with it
we can remove the debug statements
or the put as statements that print out to the screen
there and also will remove waiting for message
but that does leave us wondering
what if sending to the external service fails
how will the client know if the pledge was successfully
created or not
the client process would like to know about that
so we need to send a message
back
to the client process indicating a success or failure
and we actually know how to do that
yeah we just need to include the client's pid
in the message
so this will be the sender
and then we need to reply back to that sender
so once we have the new state figured out
we'll say send
to the sender
we'll give it a message tag response
and then we're going to send back this id variable
again that's just
some unique identifier for the pledge that was created
then we need to change
this create pledge function right here
so it needs to send self as the first
element of this message tuple
and then just like
recent pledges
it needs to wait for a response
so I'll just copy that receive block right there
instead of pledges
this is actually going to be
we'll just call it this status
and now both functions are synchronous
then down at the bottom because
these now return a status
well I'll just add an io
inspect to the front of all those lines
and now if we run it
what we see we actually get pledge 4 6 9
and different unique ids for different pledges
so we get an indication that they were created
and then the end we see our recent pledges
while we're making functions
let's wrap or encapsulate
the spawn in a function named start
I like to put it at the top of the module here
we'll call it start
now there's paste in what we have
but before that I'm going to print out put us
starting the pled server
all right then we want to spawn the pledge server
I need to use serve
pledge server there to listen loop
just the same as before
and then down in the client
we can just do this
blood server start
and that works just as well
now that works but here's a neat trick
if at some point down the road we decide to change
the name of the module which we use right here
then we'll need to remember to change this spawn line
to make this more flexible
we can use underscore underscore module
underscore underscore
and at compile time this will get replaced or expanded
with the name of the current module
which is see dot plug server in this case
and that still works
so now if we take a look at the client code down here
well we see that
it's easier to play the role of a client
it doesn't require
any knowledge of how messages are structured
or sent back and forth
between the client and server processes
and that means we can change
the internal details of the server process
without affecting the client code
one thing you probably
noticed about this client code though
is that we have to pass the pid
to each of the functions
and since we only plan to have one
pledge server process running at any given time
passing the pit around kind of feels redundant
yeah the client interface would be a lot
simpler if we could remove
all references to the pid
so we'd like to get rid of those
and also right here for recent pledges
but then the question is how would the client functions
know where to send their messages
well it turns out
it's easy to register our server processes pid
under an arbitrary name
and then use that name
when sending messages to the server
and we'll do that up in our start function
on the process module
there's a function called register
it takes a pid
and then it takes a name and the name must be an atom
I'm going to use pledge
underscore server but this is totally arbitrary
and yes an error will be raised if another
process has already registered with the same name
and then we'll also return the pid
just in case the caller wants it so
now that we have our server process registered
under this name
here plug server
down in these functions like create pledge
we can remove the pid as an argument
and then when we call
send instead of sending to the pid
we can send to the name of the server
in the same way we can remove pid from recent pledges
and then we just send to that name
cool that still works
now one downside of this is if you decide to change
the name down the road
it's easy to forget to change
one occurrence
so you might remember to change this one
but then not this one
so here's another trick
we can use a module attribute
so that the registered name is
only in one place
now I'll use the module attribute at name
that's just something I made up
it's fairly conventional but you could call this
process name if you wanted
it's just an arbitrary name
and then we'll associate with that
the atom pledge server
so basically we just have a concept now
and then we can use at name
to reference the registered name
so we're going to register our pid
under the name pled server
and then we have to make sure to also change these
this is going to be at name
and so will this one
but the beauty of this is you don't have to change
these down the road if you want to change the name of
your process
you just change it on this one line right here
and everything flows through
so save that away it should work
and sure enough it does
now before moving on
we'll comment
the code at the bottom of the pledge server module
since we're just
using it to kick the tires of the pledge server
and we also don't want this code to run
when we fire up in in the next section