remember way back at the beginning of this section
we introduced you to a pledge controller
well it should now work
because we've implemented create
pledge and recent pledges
so I've restarted it
just to get a totally clean slate here
and we're going to start by
firing up our pledge server
we'll use our handy start function
all right and that gets spawned into a process
it's processed one sixty five
and then we need to start up our http server
I'll start on port 4000 as usual
now when we call start here
this doesn't spawn a process
remember it just spawns processes for each request
so this is going to tie up sex but that's okay
now over in a separate terminal tab
we'll use curl to send some requests
so the first request we're going to send to
slash pledges
it's going to be a git request
so this is going to return our recent pledges
and right now it's just an empty list
all right so let's create some pledges
I'm going to use curl again
I'm going to use the x post option
to post this data as a post request
to slash pledges
and that's going to get handled by the crate action
of our pledge controller
solar is going to pledge $100
and then we'll have mo pledged $200
curly's gonna pledge 300
daisy once in on the action she's gonna give us 400
but not to be outdone as grace and
she's giving us five
and we might just get ourselves an alligator or two
cool now let's have a look at our recent pledges
and we've got our three most recent pledges
looking back at our pledge server module
we now have five
functions in this one module
and it's important to note that these functions run in
different processes
this start function is called
by the client to spawn the server process
then this create
pledge and recent pledges functions down here are
also called by the client
and they run in the client process
so let's actually grab those
and we'll move all the client functions together
I'll put these up under start just like that
and then let's add a comment up here
all of these are client interface functions
now this listen loop down here is different
it's called by spawn
which means it runs in this spawn server process
so let's add a comment up here
everything below here is run in the server
at first
it might seem strange that a single module can have
different functions running in different processes
and in really
complex cases you might want to separate
your client and server functions
into two separate modules
but it's actually quite common and acceptable to have
both types of functions in the same module
because after all
modules are just buckets for functions
to see what we would have to do
in the client and the server to implement a new
message let's suppose we want to get the
total amount of the recent pledges
we could do that by having
the client get the
recent pledges
and then total them up in the client process
but the server process can do more
than simply store state
it can actually do work
that's right and just to demonstrate that
we'll have the server process
do that computation
so down at the bottom here
we'll uncombed this code again
because we want to run it
we're going to add a line down at the bottom
we want our client interface to look like this
p server we want to call a function total pledged
and that should return the total
and then we use inspect just to inspect it
so to make that work
we need to define this client interface function
we'll do that up here under client interface
I'm just going to copy this one to give us a head start
so this can be called total pledged
it's going to send to the server
it needs a reply back
so it includes self in the message
and then the
atom or the message here is going to be total pledged
it'll mimic the function name
that doesn't have to be true that the function name
is the same as the message but it's common to do that
and then the response is going to send back the total
so this is going to be the total
and we just
extract that and return it from the function
so similar to the other client interface functions
this function is synchronous
it expects a reply from the server
then we need to handle the message
in the server process
we need to add a claws down here
the pattern of the message is sender
and the message is total pledged
and we know we're going to have to send
back to the sender
a message that looks like this
response and whatever total we compute
and then we're going to have to recurs
listen loop passing in the existing state
because we're not going to change the state
so what's the work the server is going to do
well I just need to compute this total
now there are a couple different ways to do this
you could use reduce if you wanted to
but I'm going to use map
so I'm going to take our state
and remember our state is a list of tuples
where the first thing is the name
and the second thing
is the amount
and there's a function that elixir called lm
and it takes a topple
I'll just call that t for a second
and then it takes the index that you want to get
and there's zero based index
so this one would get the name
this one would get the amount
but to use that with map
we need to capture the function
so we used to capture operator
and we wanted
to pass us the topple so this is going to be
ampersand one
maps going to call this function
with every element in the list and
every element is a tuple
so we pass the tuple in as the first argument
and then we want the amount so we pass in one there
so that's going to give us a list of
all the amounts that then we can pipe into e nous
so this isn't very hard work for the server to do
but it's an example of work
the server process is now storing state
and performing computations on that state
we save that away
well sure enough we get a total and it's 120
so we have several patterns in the receive loop
but what happens if our server receives a message
that doesn't match any of these patterns
we have client interface functions that send
expected messages
but someone could send us an unexpected message
yeah to demonstrate that down at the bottom here
well we could just send to that pit
because start returns to the pit
and we'll just send it the message
oh it's a two pole
first element stop and the second one is
hammer time
then at the end
we'll use io and we'll inspect the processes messages
so this would be the pid messages just like that
if we save that away and run it
while we see at the end
the messages include stop hammer time
so because none
of the patterns matched
then the unexpected message just
hangs around in the process as mailbox
so to avoid cluttering the mailbox like this
which can ultimately impact performance
it's a good idea to add a pattern at the end
that will match all messages
we do that up in the received block
and it's going to be the last pattern here
and we'll just use unexpected
that's a variable
so that's going to match any message that falls through
and then we'll just print out
unexpected message
and then we'll call inspect on that unexpected message
so we're basically just logging the unexpected message
and then we have to remember
to call listen loop at the end
so this is guaranteed to match all unexpected messages
because it's the last claws
and because we just use the variable here
it's just going to soak up any message pattern
now if we save that away and run it
well appear we see unexpected message stop hammer time
but then
when we peek in the mailbox a little bit later on
there are no messages
so here's something important to keep in mind
imagine our web server gets five
concurrent requests to create a pledge
this results in five create
pledge messages
being sent to our single pledge server process
remember though that receive
always handles messages one at a time
so although each request
runs concurrently and likely in parallel
message handling is
always sterilized in the server process and
as such server processes are
synchronization points in an application
now initially this might seem sub optimal
but it's exactly how
we want the server state to be managed
can you imagine having multiple concurrent processes
all trying to update the cash at exactly the same time
it would be a free for all
and the cash would likely become corrupted
so while it appears that the server
process is simply storing state
it's actually doing more than that
by sterilizing access
it's preserving the integrity of that state
while underload from multiple concurrent processes
so now we know how to store a simple state
in a server process that can
also do other work
in the next section
we'll look at how to make the server code more generic
and we're on our way to a gen server