so we're ready to start
handling requests
and we'll need a new module where we can define
functions to do that
so where do we put this module file
well that's the power of conventions
we don't have to arbitrarily decide
we know our application code lives in the lib directory
and by convention
we need to create a subdirectory
under lib with the same name as the project
so I'm going to create a new folder under lib
and the name of our project is service
so I'm going to have a folder or
directory called survey
and then we put our application code inside of
that directory
so here I'm going to create a new file
we're going to call it handler
ex and this or we'll write our first module
so we use def module
the name of this module is going to be survey dot
by convention
the module is name spaced inside of the
see module which is the same as the
directory name we've got our code inside of lib see
so the module here is going to be called
serve dot and we're going to call it handler
okay so let's look at the first
http request we want to handle
now I'm just going to paste this in
because as multiple lines
and you can find
these in the code bundle so you can paste them into
if you're following along
http requests have multiple lines
so we've used an elixir hair
dock
which lets us format a string across multiple lines
hair docks start with a triple double quote
and then the ending triple double quote
must be on its own line
so if you're new to seeing a raw http request
it has three parts
the first part here is called their request line
this is the method we want to get a resource
this is the path upon
which to perform the request
so we're getting the wild things resource
and then this is the he particle
then the second part is a list of
headers or key value pairs
we have the key which is host here
and then the value is example
com so that's the host of the resource being requested
the user agent is the software
typically a browser making the request
and then this accept line specifies the media
types acceptable for the response
in this case it's wild card so it'll accept basically
anything
then there's an important blank line right here
separating the headers
from the actual body which is optional
we don't have a body here
but a body is typically used to pass form parameters
and we'll see a body like that when we
actually handle a post request a bit later
and here's the response we want to send back
now an http response also has three parts
it starts with the status line
which includes the http version
the status code 200 in this case and then a
reason phrase
then we have our response headers
these are again key value pairs
this one is the media type of the body
in which case it's
text html because we're sending back html
and then content length is the size of the body
then there's a blank line which separates those headers
from an optional body
and we have a body
in this case because we're sending back html
and we're just sending back bears lines on tigers
now we're using animals and our domain
just to make it fun
but sometimes folks want examples to be more realistic
so please feel free to substitute in
products or to dos or
whatever feels fun for you
in the body of your response
at a high level we need to handle this request next
so let's start by writing a
handle function
that will ultimately transform the request
to a response
we'll do that up in our module
we'll define a function called handle
it'll take a request
that's going to be the request string
and we're just going to leave the body that
function blank for now
then down below outside of the module itself
we'll go ahead and call that
we could say our response is going to be equal to
calling survey
handler that's the name of the module
name of the function is handle
and then pass in the request
we've got our request up here
stored in the request variable
and then we'll just print
out
io to put us the response
elixir has really
changed the way I think about programming
instead of thinking about
objects and calling methods on those objects to change
their state now I think more in terms of
transforming data with functions
in this case we have a request
and through a series of transformations
we want to turn it into a response
and that's really what a web server does
and our web server is going to make three
high level transformations
each transformation step will be a function
so let's take a look at those
so I'm going to paste in those
functions so we can focus on the concept
not the syntax
initially we'll come back to the syntax though
the pars function transforms a request ring
into a key value pair
now this is an elixir map
which is similar to a hash and ruby or an
object in javascript
and we'll look at the details in the next section
we just set the method to get
the path to slash wild things
and then we've got a response body which
starting off is just going to be empty
and we'll refer to this map as the conversation
since it represents a very
short conversation between a browser and our server
and we'll just abbreviate it as come
and obviously
we're going to need to parse the requesting
into that map
the route function then transforms that map
into a new map that also has
a response body
so if we look at the response body its bears
lions and tigers
because that's the appropriate response for a request
to wiling
so we're going to need to take the map
co and v that comes in as an argument to this function
and then
also add a response body filling out the map even more
and then we have our format response function down here
now it's going to take the final map
that's co and v that's coming in as an argument
and transform it
into a valid http response string
so we're going to need to get the values
from the map in order to create
this response string
so because we've already got a response string inside
of our format response function here
I'm just going to remove this
expected response variable down here
because we don't need it
so we have the transformation functions
we now need to call them in the right
sequence in our handle function
so let's walk through this sequentially
we're going to take this request
ring and we're going to pass it into parse
what's going to come back
is a map that's partially filled out
we're going to call it convey
it's missing a response body
then we want to pass that map to the route function
which is going to fill in the response body
and we want to capture the result of that in con
so we're just transforming con each time through
here filling out more data
then finally we want to take that final map
and pass it to format response
which will generate our response string based on
what's in the final map
and because this is the last
expression in our handle function
that response string will get implicitly returned
by the handle function
now this will work
but there's a more concise
and idiomatic way to represent this
using elixir's pipe operator
so I'm just going to comment these out
and let's express this as a pipeline
we're going to take the request
pipe it into the parse function
so what's going to happen here
is the request is going to get past
as an argument to the parse function which just has
one argument then the result of that function
which is our conversation map
we want to pass that to the route function
so we just pipe that
a little bit further into route
that's going to return a map
our final map which we then want to pass into
format response
so in a pipeline like this
the result of the function on the left
is passed as the first
argument to the function on the right
now in this particular case
all of our functions only take one argument
but just remember that it's always passed as the
first argument to the function
and we can make it read more
like a list of transformation steps by
putting each step on its own line
just put those down there like that
save that away if I run it
and we see the expected response
so we know that we've got
the basic pipeline all set up
so what we've done here is use a pipeline
to basically give us an outline of our program
or a shell of our program
the
transformation steps that we want to take it through
we're transforming the request here
into a response
which is the final thing
through a series of explicit transformations
by piping the result of each function into the next
now if you're making a change
from oo programming to functional programming
one of the big differences is learning to think
in terms of transforming data
and we're going to see a lot
more examples of this throughout the course up
next we're specifically going to look at how to parse
the request string
into them out