let's step back and squint at the code we have so far
looking at this client server interaction
we see two flavors of code
code that's common to all messages
and code that's specific to a message
in terms of the client interface
all three functions send a message to the server
and then wait to receive a response
the receive block at first appear specific
but these variable names are arbitrary
so we can make these blocks generic
simply by renaming the variable to response
now the
only thing that specific to each
function is the actual message
that's sent
now what
about the code in the listen loop that
runs in the server process well
one thing to notice is that all expected messages have
sender as the first element
also each clause ends by doing the same two things
they send a response message back to the sender
and then recursively loop with the state
to be used when handling the next message
in the case of creating a pledge
the response includes id
and the state is the updated cash
in the case of getting recent pledges
the response includes the state
which is the list of pledges
and since the state didn't change
the next iteration of the loop uses the current state
and in the case of getting the total pledge
the response includes the total amount
and the state is unchanged
now you can imagine that
every time you introduce a new message
you'll need to write more of this generic to handle
the low level details of client server interaction
but surely elixir wouldn't make us do that
writing spadeful server processes like this is
so common that there's actually an abstraction
gen server which stands for generic server process
encapsulates the generic code
that's common to spadeful server processes
and that way
we can focus on writing the application specific code
so we could convert our pledge server
straight to a gen server at this point
but if we make that leap
gen server is going to film magical
probably too magical
yeah instead
we want to refactor our
code towards the gen server style
and by the end a gen server will just sort of fall out
and you'll have a better
understanding of how it works under the hood
let's start by removing the duplication
in these client interface functions
yeah we'll try to help our method that encapsulates to
send and receive steps inside of these
so I'm just going to go ahead and copy one of these
and take it with us
we're going to find a function down here
called call think remote procedure call
it's a synchronous request
it sends a message to the server
and then waits for our response
and gender refers to synchronous requests as calls
so we'll follow suit
then just paste in that coat
and let's make it more generic now
so call is going to need to take a
pid and a message
and we're going to send to that pid
the message so we can remove this specific message
it's just going to be whatever message gets passed in
and self must always be the first
element of the message
and this function takes care of
making sure that's always true
and then in the receive block
we're going to tag the response as
response which is an atom
and then we're just going to bind
the response to a generic variable
we're just going to call response
so now let's change
the client interface functions to use
our new call function
so we'll start by removing this receive line
I'll just remove that in all the functions
because call does that for us
and then instead of calling
cind right here we want to call
call and we'll pass it at name
that's the pit of our server process
and then in terms of the message
we don't need to include
self is the first element because the
call function takes care of that
okay and this message is a tootle
so we've got curlies around it
but we don't need curlies around these
because they're just adams
so I'll remove those
now if we look down in the received block of
mizzen loop down here
you notice that
this great pledge message
well it's not in curly's but this one up here is
so we need to make sure to nest this in curly's
right down here
save that away and if we run it
well it works just like before
but now we've removed the duplication
in those climbed interface functions
now down in the listen loop
we want to separate the
common code from the application specific code
and to do that
let's add a generic clause to the
top of the received loop
since all expected messages have the same basic pattern
yeah they start with a sender
and then there's the rest of the message
in each claws ends by doing the same two things
they send a response to the sender
so it send sender
and the message looks like this
response and then there's some response
associated with that
and then they recursively call listen loop
with the state
to be used in the next iteration of the loop
each clause also has message specific code
so here's some message specific
code for creating a pledge
total pledges does a computation right there
and we don't want any of that code in the receive loop
we want the loop to be generic
well that's no problem
we know a way to conditionally run code
based on pattern matches
we can use multi clause functions
yeah we'll put it below this listen loop
and we'll name the functions handle underscore call
because they handle the synchronous call
we got from the client
and then they're going to take two arguments a message
and the state
and we're going to need a
function clause like this for every specific message
so let's start from the bottom and work our way up 1st
we need a handle call function clause that matches
total pledges
so that's going to be the message
I'll just paste that there
and then we'll take the message specific code
and paste it in as the body of the function
and now this function returns the total
which is the response that we want to send
back to the client process
so now if we go back up into our generic claws here
what we need to do is invoke handle call
pass it the message in the current state
it's going to return
the thing that we should send back to the client
so we're going to bind that
to a variable called response
and then we include the response in the message
right there
now you notice we just passed this part of the message
into handle call
we didn't have to pass the sender in
because the sender is used on the line
after handle call to send back to the sender
so all handle call needs is this part of the message
so now we can remove this clause for total pledges
because the generic clause takes care of that
next we need a function clause that
matches the recent pledges message
all right we'll copy that message
at a handle call function clause
that's going to be the message
also has to take the
state
so what's the response in this case
well the client wants the recent pledges
so we just return the entire state
that's the response we want to send back to the client
and now we can remove the recent pledges claws
because our generic claws at the top
is going to take care of that
and then last
but not least we need a
third function clause that matches the create
pledge message
all right
handle call
there's the message
there's the state
then I'm going to go back up and get the message
specific code
it's everything before the send
so I'll just copy that
okay so what's the response in this case
well we want to return this id
that id is bound
as a result of calling this sin pledge to service
so it's whatever id
the external service sent back to us
so we'll just put that on the last line the function
and then it'll get returned
and then that id
will be part of the response that sent back
to the client
and then we can remove that clause in our received loop
because our generic clause is taking care of that one
now too
okay so let's run it
well that's not quite right
we see
that the pledges were created in the external service
but our cash is empty and our total is zero
and that's because create
pledge transforms the current state
into a new state
but the generic clause
is always recurring with the current state
yeah if handle call updates the state
that gets passed to it
then we need to recurs with that new state
so we'll change
handle call to always return two things in a tuple
the first
thing will be the response that we want to send back
to the client
and the second
thing will be
the new state that we want to recurs with
so we need to change state here to new state
now for that to work
we need to change our function
claws down here to return
two things the first thing is going to be the id
that's the response we want to send back to the client
but we also want to return the new state
so we're returning a tuple there
that way when we transform the state to the new state
we return that back
in the same way
we need to return a two element tuple in the
other handle call
function clauses
so for total pledged
we want to send back the total to the client
and then we were going to recurs with the state
because we haven't changed the state
we're just going to return the existing state
and then for recent pledges
we want to return
this state to the client
because the state has all the pledges and
they're asking for all the recent pledges
and we also want to re curse with that state
so this tuple has
two elements that are both state
save it away and run it
hey and that now works
now we commented out the line that has
our unexpected message
if we put that back in now and run it
well we get an error
right it says there's no function claws matching
it's trying to call the handle call function
with hammer time
well that's because this message is going to match our
generic message claws
it thinks this is the sender and this is the message
so up here if we look at our generic claws again
so this pattern is going to match stop
hammer time
and this is going to try to call handle call
with hammer time
which is why we get that air
there's no function claws that matches that message
so to fix this we're going to add a guard claws
to this pattern right here
I'm going to say when is pid sender
so that's saying this should only match
if whatever is in the first element of this tuple
is a pid we use the stupid function and pass in sender
that way it won't match
stop the atom that we have in our unexpected message
it will only match if this is a pid
and now that works
now there may be situations in your app
where you want to send a message to a server process
but you don't need to wait for a reply
basically you want to fire off
a message to the server and then forget about it
so let's look at a simple example for now
later we'll look at a more involved example
let's suppose we want the option of being able to clear
out the cash so we could call like a clear function
yeah let's assume we have a pledge server
clear function like that
so let's go ahead and implement that
client interface function
I'll put it right up here
so all it needs to do is send
to our server process the message clear
and in contrast to the other client interface functions
clear is a synchronous
it just fires off a message to the server and
since it doesn't need to wait for a response
it returns almost immediately
now you can imagine a scenario where you have
more than one
function that simply sends a message like this
so in the same way that we wrote a call helper function
that encapsulates synchronous requests
similarly
we can write a helper function that encapsulates
a synchronous request
just for symmetry
so I'm going to put a comment here
here are helper functions
and down below call
will define a new function
I'm going to call it cast
think of this like casting the message to the wind
it's an e synchronous request
it sends a message to the server
and doesn't expect a response
so it's going to take a pid and a message
and this is going to send
the message to that pit
then we can change clear to instead of calling send
it's just going to call cast
now that didn't buy us much
other than some renaming and some cemetery
but hang with us for a minute
then in our received block
we can handle that clear message
I'll put it right here
clear
and all we need to do is
reset the state to an empty list
so the new state
is just going to be an empty list like that
and then we need to recurs with that new state
the client doesn't expect a response so we don't send
anything back
so if we say that away and we run it
while it works
now our recent pledges
just includes grace because we cleared it
and everything else was gone
and then we added grace to the recent pledges
but suppose you have more than one of these
and you want a generic way to handle a
synchronous messages
well to do that
let's add another generic clause to the receive loop
and the message pattern here will never have a sender
just a message
an asynchronous message clauses
only need to recursively call
listen loop with the state
we'll take care of the message specific code in another
multi clause function
which will name handle cast
because it handles a synchronous request
sent by the client
it needs to take a message in the current state
and then return the new state
then it's going to recurs with that new state
so unlike handle call
handle
cast doesn't need to return a response for the client
because the client doesn't expect one
so now let's define handle cast
we only have one cast message to handle
so we only need one function claws
the message is clear
then the second argument is state
but we're not going to use the state
so I'm going to use underscore state
so we don't get a warning
and then all we need to do is return the new state
well that's just an empty list in this case
so now we can remove this claws
because our generic claws right here
handles that
so now if we save that away and we run it
oh we get another error
it's the no function claws matching error
but this time is trying to call handle cast
with stop hammer time
and that's because stop hammer time
will match this pattern right here message
because it's just a variable
it's going to soak up
whatever message we get right here
remember patterns are matched top to bottom
and all unexpected messages are going to get matched
too early by this pattern message
so we need a way to match call and cast messages
but then let
everything else fall through to the unexpected clause
to do that
we're going to tag the messages as either being a call
or a cast and we'll do that by adding an
element to the message tuple
so we'll have the atom call right there
and we'll have the atom cast inside of this tuple
now for this to work
the client must send messages with these tags
well that's no problem
because we already have
these helper functions call encase
that are used
by the client interface functions to send messages
so in call
we just add the atom call right there to that message
and in cast will change its message
to automatically tag those
so now cast is
actually pulling some weight
by tagging the messages for us
yeah and what's nice is we don't have to change
any of these client interface functions
because the call
and cast helper functions do the tagging
if we save that away it should work and indeed it does
so let's step back
and separate what's generic to all
server processes and what's specific to this
particular server process
yeah let's just go ahead and start at the top here
so these client interface functions right here
are specific to pledging
but these helper functions down here
while they're generic
they're used by the client interface functions to send
call or cast messages
so let's go ahead and move these into a new module
and I'm just going to put it at the top
of the file here
just so it's easier to run inside of sublime
and we're going to call the module survey
generic server
and I'll just paste in
those helper functions
then down in pledge server
we're going to alias that module in
and then down in our client interface functions
where we have the call right here
well that's just going to be generic server
call now
because that's where the call function is defined
in the same way for cast
we're called generic server cast
if we save that away and we run it
well no surprise it works just as it did before
next up is this listen loop right here
and it's also generic
there's nothing
application specific about this code at all
the application specific code
lives in these multi clause functions
handle call and handle cast
you'd need to include this generic loop function in
one form or another
when writing any server process
so let's go ahead and move it
into the generic server module as well
so now when listen loop receives a message
it needs to invoke the corresponding handle call
or handle cast function
that's in the pledge server module so this needs to be
survey
handle call in the same way
we need to call handle cast on that module
now going back down to our pledge server module
what else could we move
well with a couple minor changes
we could move this start function
of to our generic server
I'm just going to copy it
and we'll paste it up here
we'll remove this first
io dot put us because we're not starting the pledge
server this is more generic
and since this
underscore underscore module
underscore underscore will expand
to the current module which would be serviced
generic server in this case
well this line is going to go ahead and spawn
the listen loop that we have to find
inside this module
so that's all good
but this at name is specific to a process
and this initial state
which in this case is an empty list
is specific to a process
so to make this start function generic
we're going to need to pass in these two things
as argument so we'll pass in the initial state
it's the first argument
and then the second one will be the name
and then we'll substitute here instead of an empty list
it's going to be initial state
and then
instead of using at name we're just going to use name
then down in the start function of our plug server
right here we don't have to do this stuff anymore
we can just call generic server start
and then pass in this process's initial state
which is an empty list and then the name
which we have in at name
save that away and run it
and that works just the same
and now everything
else in pledge server is specific to pledging
but if we go back to our
generic server and look in the listen loop
well we've hard coated pledge server
to truly be generic generic servers should work with
any module
as long as that module implements the two functions
handle call and handle cast
we want the generic server to call back
to our pledge server module to run
the application specific code
in other words pledge server
is to be our callback module
we'll have a variable called callback module that
holds onto that callback module
and then we'll call
handle cast and handle call on that module
so how are we going to feed this callback module
into the generic server
well first down in our start function here
when we start the generic server we need to tell it
which module implements the callback functions
and we'll pass the callback module as the first
argument
now the callback
module that implements the callback functions
is this module
it's the pledge server module
so we can use this trick again
so we're telling the generic server
that we are the current module
the pledge server module
where the callback module
now for that to work
we need to change
the start function up here
in generic server to
take that callback module as the first argument
and then ultimately we need to pass it down to this
listen loop we'll remember the third argument to spawn
is a list of arguments to send to
the function that's getting spawned
in this case it's listen loop
so right now
listen loop just takes one argument the initial state
but we can pass it a second argument that's
going to be our callback module
then down in listen loop
we'll have callback module there
and since this function now
takes two arguments we know
we're going to have to recurs with those same
two arguments
so we're going to have callback module passed there
there and also there
save that away and run it
hey cool that works too
who
so now generic server encapsulates all
the generic code that's common to server processes
it relies on a callback module
such as the pled server module
to implement the application specific code
in the callback functions handle call and handles
so down here in our pledge server
we can change this comment
server right here
to server callbacks
because these are just callbacks that are called by
our generic server
and now we're in a great
position to start using the gen server abstraction
and it's up next