you've done some really
hard work in the last two sections to create
a server process
that has state
and does work asynchronously
and all that work is about to pay off
because elixir has an abstraction
for writing server processes and believe it or not
you now know how it works
the abstraction is called wait for it
gen server
so in a minute we're going to get rid of all this code
and replace it with the gendered module
but before we move away from this code
notice it encapsulates calm and server behavior
and delegates to call back functions
to run code that specific to a process
as such it enforces an implicit contract
the callback
module must implement certain callback functions
handle call and handle cast
so this code implements a design
pattern for spadeful server processes
in top a design
pattern like this is referred to as a behavior
gen server is a behavior
for writing spadeful server processes
it's included in the top libraries
top includes other behaviors that encapsulate
design patterns for
other processes such as supervisors
which will learn about a bit later
now probably doesn't come as a surprise
to you that converting from our generic server
to the gen server module
is going to turn out to be pretty straightforward
in large part
because we follow the gen server naming conventions
but before we do that
you might want to save off a version of this code
just for your
reference
one way to do that would be to duplicate this file
we could call it pledge server hand rolled for example
then down here we need to change
the name of this module to match
so I'll just get all those occurrences
and change them to pledge server hand rolled
then I'm going to comment out
all the code that's outside of the module
because we don't want this
code running when we fire up sex
and finally we need to change the registered name
we've got this at name up here
we don't want this to be pledge server
because we can only have
one process registered under a given name
so I'm going to change this to pledge server
hand rolled and by renaming all this stuff
we won't end up with any naming collisions
with the things
that we're going to have back in pledge server
now the first step to converting
from our generic server to a gen server
and we love this step
is to completely remove the generic server
the gendered module takes care of all
of these generic details for us
and a whole lot more
then we can get rid of this
alias because we don't have a generic server anymore
and then everywhere we call generic server here
all these occurrences
this is just going to be gen server
that's the module that's in the top libraries
now we're calling start on the gen server module
and the way you
set a name for a gen server is the third argument
needs to be a keyword list so these are options
we're going to say the name is going to be at name
and that'll register the process under that name
now unlike our hand rolled generic server module
the gen server module expects the callback module
to implement six callback functions
since we followed the gen server naming conventions
the pled server module already defined
two of the six required callback functions
handle call and handle cast
now we don't need the other four
required callback functions just yet
we'll look at those a bit later
and oftentimes
you don't need the other four functions at all
so instead of having to implement all
six callback functions
to fulfill our side of the bargain
we can let the gendered module
generate default implementations for us
and we can do that by going to the top of the file
and adding one line
use g
the use macro
injects default implementations of the callback modules
into our pledge server module
we've already defined handle call and handle cast which
override
the default implementation of these callback functions
but we need to change them very
slightly to conform to what gen server expects
yeah handle cast needs to return the state
wrapped in a tuple
and the first element of that tuple is the atom
no reply
and then the second element is just the new state
and other atoms are
possible here
but no reply is by far the one you'll use the most
our handle call functions already return to tuple
but they need to be
tagged with the first element being reply
just like that
so we'll put that down here
and down here as well
reply
indicates that the server should reply to the client
it's going to send it the second element this value
and then the third element is the new state
we need to make one more change
to these handle call function clauses
they currently take
two arguments but gendered requires them to take
three arguments
the second argument is some information
about the sender I'm going to call it from
but it's typically not needed
so we'll just ignore it we'll use underscore from
so that's the second argument we'll put it here as well
and finally down here
the last change we need to make is down
here where we start the server
right now on the left hand side we just match a pid
but remember that pledge server start
calls gen server start
and it returns a tuple rather than just a pid
the tuple has an atom okay
and then the pid is just a second element
so now our pled server fulfills all
the requirements of a gen server
so it should work
we save it away
and sure enough it does ya
so when you see this used line in a module
you know right away
that it's a server process that
at least that a fundamental level
behaves like all other gen server processes
now that we've converted over to use a gen server
let's introduce a new message
just to walk through the steps
our cash currently holds three pledges
but let's suppose we want to be able to change
the cash size while the server is running well
since we can't hard
code the size
it'll need to be part of the server state
so the state will include the list of pledges and
a number representing the cash size
which means when we start the server
passing an empty list won't be enough
well we could pass it a map
the map would have a cash size key
was that default value of three
and then it would have our pledges which is a list
and that would work
but it gets unwieldy if we have even more state
so we want to show you another technique
as the state gets more involved
it's handy to define a structure with
fields having default values
so let's do that
we're going to put our s
right inside of our pledge server module
so the structure is going to be called state
def struck and then it's going to have two fields
cast size and pledges
and those are going to be the default values
then we can change our start function
to use that initial state
just like that
now we need to
change our callback functions since
they assume that the state
is just a list of pledges
so down in our clear cast right here
we're going to need to change this state
so I'm going to remove the underscore there
because I'm going to change it here
and we just want to set the pledges field of this
struck to an empty list
and to do that we go like this we say state
remember that's a structure and we want to modify
the pledges field and set it to an empty list
so this will return a new structure
that has the current cast size
but the pledges field is changed to an empty list
now in terms of this total pledged here
instead of mapping on state we want to map on state
pledges because we're summing up
the total of the pledges list
and then for reason pledges
well we want to recurs with the state
but we want to return
state pledges back to the client
okay now on to create pledge
well instead of taking from the state
we need to take from state pledges
and instead of hard coding the number two
this is going to be state cash size
and then we're going to subtract one
because remember
we're going to add
the new pledge to the head of that list
but the problem here is this
isn't the new state that we want to return
this is actually the cash pledges now
the new state
is the current state
where the pledges gets changed to the new cast pledges
and then we take that and we recurs with it
so before we run this
let's go down and rearrange our code
we'll call clear after larry
and now when we run it
well we should see the three most recent pledges
because after all
that's the default cash size
but now what if we want the cash size to be for
well
first we need to implement a client interface function
so let's call it set cash size
yeah we want to be able to call it like this
led server
set cash size
passing in a No.4
so let's go ahead and implement that
up in our client interface functions
it's going to take a size
okay so should this be a call or a cast message
well this is really a design decision
in this case the client doesn't really need a response
it can assume the request was successful
and it's not critical if for some reason it fails
so we'll make it a cast
so it's gendered
cast at name and the message will be set cast size
and the size
so now we need to function claws to handle that message
and it's going to be a cast
so we're going to put it right
below this existing handle cast
because we want to keep these together
all the handle casts
and all the handle calls get grouped together
so handle cast
the message
set cash size size
and then it also takes the state
and then the new state
will be the existing state
but we want to change the cash size
to whatever gets passed in
and then we need to return the two pole
no reply because this is the cast and the new state
and now if we save this away and we run it
well now our cash has four pledges instead of three
we said earlier that when you add
use gen server to a module
six default callbacks are injected into that module
you then add application specific behavior
by overriding any of the default implementations
we've overridden two callbacks so far
handle call and handle cast
so now let's look at two of the other most frequently
overridden callbacks
currently when we initialize our server
we use the default state
so when we start the process the pledge list is
always empty ideally
when we start the process
it would go and fetch the most
recent pledges from the external service
and then prep populate our in memory cash
and that's where the nit call back comes in
here's the default implementation of that callback
and I'm going to put it down
under server callbacks
it looks like this and knit
it takes rag and then returns the tuple ok and rag
so what happens is when we call start up here
this 2nd argument state becomes the value that's
passed into a knit a knit is automatically called
it passes in that 2nd argument
which is going to be a value of a here
and then the default implementation just turns around
and returns drag in a tuple
so in our case argues is the state
so let's just change that to state
just to make it more clear
and then because state is returned in this tuple
that state will get
used to initialize the server when it starts
so by default it just passes the state through
it's a no up
but we can override it to do whatever we want
so what we want to do is are populate our cash
well we added a function down here
fetch recent pledges from service
so you'd put some code here to actually go
fetch the recent pledges from the external service
and we're not going to worry about that
and then it would convert whatever got returned
into a list of tuples
that our gendered expects and then we just return that
so you can imagine wilma and fred
being the most
recent pledges returned by our external service
now back up in our knit callback
let's go ahead and use that to prep populate the cash
so we'll say pledges
equals fetch recent pledges from service
okay now we want to update this state because remember
this is the default state
structure which has an empty list of pledges
so the new state
is going to be the existing state
where the pledges field is updated
to be whatever got returned by that external service
and then we just need to make sure to change this
to new state
so just to recap what happens here
when start is called to start our server
this 2nd argument is going to get passed to a knit
and knit's going to be automatically called by gen
server
so state is going to be the default structure our state
then we want to update that state
we go fetch the pledges from the service
update the state to have
those pledges in the pledges field
that becomes the new state which we return
and gen server uses this value new state
to initialize the server when it starts
now before we run this let's go down to the bottom
and let's comment out clear
and all the pledges after larry
so now when we run it
we see that the server starts the
cash with the two pledges from the external service
and then adds on larry's pledge
now there's one caveat to this
it's important to note that
start will block and tell this
a knit function returns
so just be mindful of how long initialization takes
let's go down to the bottom one more time
because I noticed that the line
where we send an unexpected message
it's commented
so let's uncommon
and now run it
and see what happens now that we're in gendered land
ooo we get an error
notice it says the pledge server
received an unexpected message in handle info
of reality two
and then it shows the unexpected message
while in ginger land
handle info is a callback function
that's automatically called to handle
any messages that aren't sent using call or cast
and our unexpected message was sent
directly using the send function
kind of like a message that came spontaneously
out of the blue
and when that happens
the handle info callback is called
with that message
now the default implementation just
logs the air as we saw right here
but we can override the callback to do our own thing
all right we'll go up here
we're going to put it under handle call
the callback is handle info
we know it's an eternity two
the first thing is the message
the second thing is the state
and then we'll just print out
can't touch this
and then we'll inspect the message
then it needs to return a tuple
the first element is the atom no reply
and the second element is the state
if we save that away and run it
while now that we see the output of our implementation
now this example is a bit contrived we'll give you that
but it turns out
handle info has many practical uses
beyond handling unexpected messages
we'll see a more practical example of the handle info
callback in the next section
we started by hand rolling a spadeful
server process and then we converted it to a gen server
so you'd have a better
idea of what goes on under the hood
it's no longer magical
so when you go to write your own server process
we strongly recommend using gen server
right off the bat
rather than rolling your own
jen server has been battle hardened over many
years of use in production environments
all the rough edges air handling
subtle corner cases in the like have been smoothed off
and jen server includes many production ready features
we didn't even touch on
use it
and you'll be standing on the shoulders of giants