so we've seen one example of a gen server
we'd like to now show you a
different example of a gen server in action
in particular
we can use the nit and handle info callback functions
to make it easy to schedule periodic work
remember a while back we worked on a sensor's route
now that route a synchronously gets three
snapshot images
and bigfoot's current gps location
and even though the api request one concurrently
so that we get all the results in just one second
this sensor data it doesn't really change very often
so there's no sense in us hitting these apis
every time we want to get a request for sensors
instead
we want to cash the results and refresh the cash
every hour
so to do that we're going to need another gen server
so we've gone ahead and started to write
a sensor server
let's walk through it
it's a gen server
we have the use gen server line right there
and then in terms of our client interface we've got a
start function that just starts the gen server
and we gave it a name
just like we did with our other gen server
this one's name is sensor server
didn't we have a get sensor data function
that is a call since a call message
it's get sensor data over to the server
then in terms of our server callbacks we have our
nit function
remember that gets called automatically by the
start function
now the start function
its 2nd argument is this empty map
but we just ignore that as part of the state
because what we want to do instead
is run the tasks to get the sensor data
and have that be our initial state
that gets returned from a knit
so when the process starts
it immediately runs the tasks to get this data
so what does this function here do
well it's just what we had in our handler
it runs the task to get bigots location
and the task to get the snapshot images
and then it returns a map
we use the map this time
the key of snapshots has a list of snapshots
a key of location has
bigots location
and then that return map becomes our initial state
which we return from a knit
then there's a handle
call function clause that handles to get
sensor data message
and it just replies with the state
that's what we send back to the client
and then the state we want to recurs with
is that same state
and the results are already in the cash
so when the client calls get sensor data
it just comes straight out of the cash
let's give it a quick spin and ex
fire up our sensor server
all right we see that
it's running the task to get the sensor data
so our cash is all warmed up
now if we call service
sensor server
get sensor data
well it returns immediately
with the location
and the snapshots that are already in the cash
now you might notice that our snapshot image
file names are a little different
we've changed the video
cam to assign random numbers to the end of each
file name just
so we can demonstrate the upcoming cashing behavior
we did that over in the video cam module
you notice we just added a dash and then we use
that rand uniform function again
to get a random number between one and 1000
so now that we know that this works we can change
our sensor row in handler
ex to actually use our gen server
yeah we can get rid of all this now
because that's in our gen server
and we'll just say sensor data
equals sensor server
get sensor data
and then we'll just inspect it
to make it the response body
so here's how our sensor server currently works
when the start function is invoked
it calls back to the nit function
which fetches the sensor data from external apis
and caches the data as the process estate
then when a client invokes the get sensor data function
it simply returns whatever data is in the cash
behind the scenes though
every hour we want the cash to refresh with
new sensor data
but how will the sensor server know to refresh its cash
well the only way a process knows to do something
is by receiving a message
so we'll have the sensor server
send a refreshed message to itself
every hour here's how it will work
the nit callback function will do two things
fetch and
cash the initial sensor data from the external apis
and then schedule a refresh message to
sensor server 60min in the future
an hour later that message is then sent
it's handled by the handle info callback function
and the cash is updated
but an hour from now
how does the server know to refresh its cash again
well every time handle info handles the refresh message
it will schedule the next refresh message to be sent
60min in the future
and in this way
a refresh message is sent to the sensor server
every hour now refreshing the cash every hour is
reasonable if this
were running in a production environment
but we don't think you want to wait around that long
to see it in action
so we'll actually make it only 5 seconds in this module
in the nit callback function
let's schedule the first
refresh message to be sent and we'll do it right
after we have our initial state
and we're going to use a new function
it's in the process module and the function is called
send after aha
and it takes three arguments
the first one is the
pid that we want to send the message to
in this case is going to be ourself
so we're just going to call self
then the message
is going to be refresh
and then the third argument is how long we want to wait
until we send that message
and it's a time expressed in milliseconds
but rather than doing the math to get to 5 seconds
I'm going to use the early timer module
and there's a
function called seconds and we just pass it five
and then that'll give us back
the number of milliseconds
so the send after function is going to send
this message to this process
after this mini milliseconds
now this message is a raw or plain message
it's neither a call or a cast
and remember
all messages that aren't sent using call or cast
are going to be picked up by the handle
info callback function
so we need to define one of those
I'll just do it right here
it's handle info
the message is refresh
and then the second argument is always the state
which we're not going to use
so I'll use an underscore there
and then I'm just going to start by printing out
refreshing
the cash
and then to refresh the cash
we need to run that function
run task to get center data
and then we'll just assign that to new state
that'll be our new cash
and then we return that as a tuple
no reply
new state
okay so that handles the message
and now our mailbox would be empty
so then how will the server know to refresh its cash in
the next hour
well after refreshing the cash
we need to schedule the next refresh message
yeah I'm just going to grab this
because we're going to need to do the same thing
and then we're just going to put it right here
after we calculate the new state
while we're going to schedule the next refresh message
for 5 seconds in the future
now I just copied that down
so we've got some duplication here
let's clean it up by writing a quick function here
it'll just be a private function
and we'll call it schedule refresh
and then we'll just put this inside of there
and then on this line we can call schedule refresh
and the same up here
and then to make it easier to change
the actual interval
we could put this time
in a module attribute so let's go ahead and do that
I'll call the module attribute at refresh interval
and then up at the top here
we'll just define it as at refresh interval
and then it'll be 5 seconds in our case
but if you were in production you would use something
like timer dot
minutes
okay let's give this a spin in a new fix session
we start up our sensor server
and after 5 seconds we see that it's
refreshing the cash and
running the task to get the sensor data
oh there it went again after another 5 seconds so
every 5 seconds it's refreshing the cash
so now let's go ahead and get the sensor dana
well it returns it back
notice here that we've got snapshot three thirty one
and in the background
it's still refreshing the cash every 5 seconds
so if we get it again
now this is changed to four eighty four
and so on
so behind the scenes
the server still
takes care of updating the cash on a periodic interval
we hope this gets you thinking about
other interesting use cases for a gen server
beyond just simply storing state