we currently have three
server processes
that should run continuously and never miss a beat
but things don't always go according to plan
yeah a process can crash
and when it does we need to take action
so our application doesn't miss a beat
now designing for this sort of fault tolerance
sounds like a tall order
but it's baked into the erlangvm and the otp libraries
here are our three server processes http server
pledge server and sensor server
how can we make these processes resilient to failures
well we want to put in place something
that will start each process
continuously monitor that process
and then if it detects that the process crashed
start a new process in its place
so how are we going to do that
well in the case of pledge server and sensor server
these processes are gen server processes
and otp includes a supervisor behavior
that we'll use in the next module to start
monitor and start new processes as necessary
but the htp server process isn't a gen server process
it's a regular elixir process that
doesn't follow the otp conventions
and as
such we can't use the built in supervisor behavior
instead we'll write a simple gen server process because
as we'll see we want it to be a long
running process that handles messages and store state
and we'll name a kickstarter
think of kickstarting a motorcycle instead of the
popular funding platform
this process will start the http server
process and then use something called a link
to detect when that process crashes
so it can start a new process
and learning about linking processes is fundamental to
understanding how the otp supervisor behavior works
under the hood
all right so let's create the kickstarter module
kickstarter dx
this could be serve kickstarter
and then we want this to be a gen server
so we're going to say use gen server
and then just like our other gen servers
we'll write a start wrapper function
and we'll just start off by saying ioputas
starting the kickstarter
and then it needs to call gen server start
to actually start up the gen server process
and then this module
kickstarter is going to be the callback module
so we'll set that as the callback module
and then we don't have any state
so we'll just use the atom ok for the state
and then we also want to register this process
under a name and the name is
actually just going to be the name of the module
so we'll use this again
so the name of the process is just going to be
survey kickstarter
when the kickstarter process starts
we also want to start an http server process
we'll refer to this as the web server process
from now on we'll do that in the nit callback function
and because we use the adam ok in genserver start
well it needs to take ok right there too and we
know
this is going to be automatically invoked by genserver
start and because we pass ok right here
well
that's why we need ok here so that a pattern matches
and it runs this function
then we'll just print out
starting the hdp server
and then to start it up we're going to use spawn
serve hdp server
the function is start
and then we want to pass it the port 4000
just like we've done many times
and then we'll capture the server pid
on the other side
oops this actually needs to be 4000 instead of 400
all right and let's
also register the web server process under an alia
so it's easy to demonstrate crashing it
we'll just say process register
the server pid
and we'll just name it http under score server
then we need to make sure to return a tuple
with the state
being the server pid
so it'll be okay
and then the state is just
that server pin
so let's take this away and give it a quick whirl in I
yex
so to start the kickstarter we use survey kickstarter
dot start that's our wrapper function
and this is going to return a two pull with ok
and the pit I'm going to call it the kick pid
remember
start is calling gen server start and gen server start
always returns a tuple
ok and then some pit
so we're pattern matching that on the left hand side
cool we see that both the kickstarter process
and the web server process got started
now what happens if the web server process crashes
for some reason
we could set it up to crash by
raising an exception in the code
but rather than changing the code
we can cause the process to crash by sending it an
exit signal
so first we need to find that web server process
we want to get a hold of the pid
because we registered an alias we can use process
there's a where is function
and then we pass it the name
of the process
we registered
http server
there we go we've got the pids stored in server pid
and then to crash it we can use the process module
again there's a function called exit
we give it the server pid
and then we give it the reason
that it should exit
and I'm just going to use the atom caboom
all right now let's see if that's still alive
nope the web server isn't alive anymore
but what about the kickstarter process
if we pass in kickpid here
well it returns true
so the kickstarter process is still alive
the reverse is also true
if we were to crash the kickstarter process
it wouldn't affect the web server process
who by default both processes run in isolation
but we need a way for kickstarter to detect
when the web server process crashes
okay so how is one process going to monitor the other
well we can link them together
we're in the nit function here
and we've spawned the hdp server process
then right after that we can say process link
server pit
and because we're calling process link
from within the kickstarter process
because it's getting initialized here
then that kickstarter process is now linked
to the web server process
that's the process corresponding to server pid
let's give this another world in a new iex session
that way we don't have to worry about cleaning up
registered processes
so first we need to fire up the kickstarter process
then we need to find our http server process
and when we started up the kickstarter
the nit function was called
so now these two processes should be linked
we can find out by using the process module
the info function will give it the kickpid
and then we'll ask it what are your links
well it's linked to process one sixty six
which is our hdp server process
so what about the reverse
what is the server process link to
well it's linked to pid one sixty five
which is our kickstarter process
we see when it got started up there
that's the pid of it one sixty five
now you also see that it's linked to a port
a port is just a way
for elixir to communicate with external programs
doesn't have anything to do with linking of processes
here the key thing is these two processors are linked
by directionally
so the kickstarter pid references the hdp server pid
and the hdp server pid
is linked to the kickstarter process
so now let's crash the web server process
just like we did before
by sending it the exit signal caboom
so it dies but what happens to our kickstarter process
ah well this time it also crashed
so here's what happened behind the scenes
we sent an exit signal to the hdp server process
that caused it to terminate
it then notified the
linked kickstarter process by sending it the same
exit signal and
because the exit signal indicates the process exited
abnormally
then the linked kickstarter process crashed as well
so when we link two processes their fates are tied
together when one crashes the other one crashes
but that's not exactly what we want
we don't want the kickstarter process to crash
if the web server process crashes
the kickstarter needs to continue running
so it can restart the web server
which really means starting a new web server process
there's no way to actually restart a dead process
we just want to start a new process
to do that
the kickstarter process needs to trap exit signals
and we'll do it in the first step of the nit function
we use process
there's a function called flag
the flag is trap exit
and then we just want to pass in true
now any exit signals that get
propagated from the linked web server process won't
cause the kickstarter process to crash
so let's see what our trap catches in a new iex session
fire up the kickstarter process
find the web server process
then we need to caboom the web server process
ooh this time we get an error message
now we'll come back to that in a minute
but what happened to our kickstarter process
well it's still alive
so even though both processes are linked
the kickstarter process didn't crash
that's exactly what we wanted
now back to the error message and it's pure gold
it's saying that the kickstarter process received an
unexpected message
and here's the message
so kickstarter trapped the exit signal
sent by the web server when it crashed
and converted the exit signal to a message
we see the atom exit
and then the second element here is the pid
this is the process that crashed one sixty six
which is our web server process
and then the third element
is just the reason it crashed
well it's that atom caboom
and because this is just a plain message
it's not a call or a cast
then gen server expects it to be handled
in a handle info callback
which is why we see received unexpected message in
handle info it's trying to invoke handle info
with a message that matches this pattern
so in our kickstarter module we just need a handle info
callback that matches this message
and restarts the web server
handle info
and then
I copied the message that was in ix so I can just
paste it in right here
and then I'll just change it
so this is going to be
the pid of the terminated process
we don't need that
so I'm going to use an underscore
so we don't get a warning
and this is going to be the reason
and then because of this handle info
the second argument is always going to be the state
and we're not going to use it either
so I'm going to use underscore state there
and then we'll start by just printing off
http server exited
and then in printheses will just inspect the reason
you likely want to permanently log this air
so you have forensics to help diagnose the problem
we're just going to print it out for now
so regardless of the exit reason
we want to start a new hdp server process
so we'll just copy these lines from a knit
right now we'll clean this up a little bit later
we'll just come down here and I'll just paste those in
and then we just need to make sure to return
the expected tuple
and since this is handle info it needs to be
no reply
and then the state which is just going to be the
new server pit
because remember
we started a new hdb server process right there
assigned it to server pid
so the new state is going to be that server pit
we'll try this in a new
iex session and we should be home free
start up the kickstarter
find our hdp server
caboom it and perfect
we see that we started a new web server process
and now if we go find that new web server process
and we caboom it again
well actually not again
this is a different process entirely
well we see we're getting a new pid every time
this is pid one seventy three
before it once once 70 and before that
let's see it was one sixty six
that's just what we want
so every time our web server dies
kickstarter starts a new process
now if we look back at our code we have four
lines duplicated here
which is an ideal
so let's refactor these into a start server function
I'll just copy these out and then down below
here we'll define that new function
start server and I'll just paste those in
and then we just need to remember to return
the server pid as the last line there
and you could make this a private function if you want
just use defp
and then we just need to use that function up here
so in a knit we can remove all this
and just call start server
I'll copy that in the same way we can do that right
here
no one actually we can remove this pudex too
so now these two functions are nice and tidy
now you notice
down here we're calling spawn
and then we're turning around immediately and calling
link now
you often want a spawner process and
link it to the calling process
so there's a shortcut for this
rather than calling spawn
and then link as two separate steps
you can instead call the spawn link function
so you just say spawn
link like that and then you can get rid of that line
this has the same effect
but it's more convenient and
also more robust
as the spawn and link happen in one atomic operation
to avoid any potential race conditions
okay now for a quick sanity check
we start our kickstarter
get our http server
crash at one last time
oh and it looks like it gets restarted
so our refactoring didn't break anything
so now if our web server process crashes
we automatically give it a kick
so hopefully we don't miss any requests to our site
next up
we'll do the same for our pledge and sensor servers