are you ready for another top behavior
bring on the supervisors
at this point
we have the kickstarter process
link to the web server process
so if the web server process crashes
a new web server process is kick started now
unlike http server
the pledge server and sensor server
are top gen server processes
we can therefore use another
top behavior called supervisor to start
monitor and restart these processes if they crash
will name ours services supervisor
a supervisor is like a mother hand
who watches over other processes
commonly refer to as her children
that's right an top supervisor can supervise one
or more gender processes
and as we'll see a bit later can supervise
other supervisor processes
top supervisors can support a variety of strategies
for restarting the child processes if necessary
one common strategy is one for all
which means if one process terminates
the supervisor will terminate all
the other children
and start new processes in their place
in our case
since the child processes aren't dependent on
each other we'll use the one for one restart strategy
which means if a child process terminates
only that process is restarted
after all
there's no need for us to restart both processes
so let's get started
let's create the module
name of the file is services supervisor
and there's no magic to this name
here services supervisor
the magic comes when you actually use
the supervisor behavior
now a supervisor is a process in its
own right just like any other process
so to start
the supervisor process will write a rapper function
this time called start link and you'll see why
in a minute and then we'll just start by printing out
starting the services supervisor
to start the supervisor process
you might think we could call supervisor
start because that's what we did for a gen server
but the supervisor module doesn't define a start
function it only has a start link function
calling start link spawns a supervisor process
and links it to the process that calls this
start link function here
initially we'll call start link from the ix process
but later on we'll write a top level
supervisor process
that then is linked to this supervisor process
now similar to how the gents over behavior works
the supervisor behavior
also needs a callback module
and that's the first argument to start link
and it's going to be this module
our services supervisor
and then we'll use ok as the argument
and we're also going to register this process
under the same name as the module
so we use the name option
and then we want it to be this module
now
the supervisor behavior expects the callback module
to implement in a knit function
so that's our next step
and we'll pattern match on ok
just because we pass that in
similar to how a knit works with gen server
and knit is
automatically invoked when we start the supervisor
here and because we passed ok is the second argument
well it's going to pass that in
to a knit is the first argument
so we just pattern match it
now
the nit callback is where we tell the supervisor which
processes or
children it needs to start and then supervise
in our case it's responsible for two child processes
and we'll put those in a list
yeah we'll call the list children
and it's going to be the pledge server
and also serve
sensor server
then we need to call supervisor
nit
we pass at the list of children as the first argument
and then we also give it the restart strategy
and as we said earlier we're going to use the one
for one strategy and notice that that's an atom
so let's go ahead and
fire up the supervisor to see what happens
over an ix
to start the supervisor we would use
services supervisor
the name of our wrapper function is start link
alright and that's going to return a pid
which is going to be wrapped in a two pull
okay the pid I'm going to call sub pid
just like that
uh oh we get an air
well it's trying to invoke the pledge server
start link and pass an empty list as the argument
we'll notice in our code
we didn't tell the supervisor how to start
the child processes
so the supervisor assumes our
code follows some conventions
when a child process
starts it needs to be linked to the supervisor
so the supervisor can detect a crash
so the supervisor assumes that the child
process defines a start
link function
that starts the process
and links it to the current process
which will be the supervisor in this case
and if we look over in our pledge server
well it doesn't follow that convention
it defines a start function of ability zero
it doesn't take any arguments and it doesn't do
any linking and this is the same for our sensor server
start function
so that's why we get the air
because the supervisor is looking for a
start link function
so let's fix that
we'll rename this interface function from start
to start link
then instead of calling
gen server start link
that's going to spawn the gen server process and
link it
to the process that calls our start link function
and the supervisor is going to pass this start
link function
in argument we don't really care what it is
we're just going to use underscore arg
but we saw in the air message
it's just going to be an empty list
and then we'll
also add a print out here at the top of this
because we don't have one right now
it's just going to say
starting the sensor server
while we're here
let's crank the refresh interval way down
so that the d bug output
doesn't get in the way of what we're seeing when
the process is start
so let's put it on an interval of 60min okay
well we've got that commented at the end
so we'll just take it out of here
we'll comment our 5 seconds interval
and then we'll have it be
60min that way we won't see as much debug
let's also fix our pledge server in the same way
we want our interface function to be start link
gen server start link
oh and it takes arguments which will ignore
now that we're following the conventions
the supervisor should be happy
so let's try that out in a clean slate here
all right let's start up our services supervisor
ah that's looking a lot better
yeah we see the services supervisor
starts and then automatically starts the two
child processes
this is a good time to point out that the supervisor
module itself
has some handy functions worth keeping in your back
pocket for example
let's say we want to see which
children it's supervising
well we can use this supervisor module
this isn't services supervisor
this is just a built in supervisor module
it has a function called witch children
and then we pass it the pid of a supervisor
well that's our sup of pid
and we see that it has two children the sensor server
here's the pid of that child
it says worker
and when you see worker
it just means any process other than a supervisor
and then we've got our pledge server it's
pid and it's also a worker
if you wanted you can also count the children
just change which children to count children
and we see that we have two workers
so let's crash our sensor server
yeah first we need to find it
so we'll use that where is function
and then we have our sensor server registered
under sensor server
that's going to return a pid
and then this time I'm just going to use a pipe
I'm going to pipe it into process exit
because the first argument of that is a pig
the second argument is the reason we want to exit
and we'll use kaboom again
perfect only that child process got restarted
because we're using the one for one restart strategy
and for good measure
let's go ahead and crash the pledge server
yeah we have it registered under pledge server
so we'll kaboom it as well
and we see that it gets restarted
woo hoo
now suppose
we needed to configure the sensor server
when it's started
for example to set the refresh interval
well since we're not starting the sensor server anymore
that's now the supervisor's job
this is where the start link argument comes in handy
yeah we want to pass the refresh interval in here
as this arc
to do that we come back over to the services supervisor
and you notice this list of children
we're just using module names
but another way to do this is to use a
tuple the first
element of the tuple is the module sensor server
and then the second element is going to be an argument
so in our case
if we wanted it to be 60min refresh interval
we could use 60
but this could be any argument
you could use a list here
or a map or whatever you need
to configure your server process
so now 60 is going to get passed
over to our sensor server as this argument
so this is going to be interval
and then we'll just print out
starting the sensor server
with
interval and I'll say men refresh
now we'll get a clean slate over here
fire up our services supervisor
and you see it says starting the sensor server with
60min refresh
now for this to actually work
you would need to put the refresh interval
in the state rather than just using a module attribute
which is a constant
but we'll leave that as an exercise for you
the point is you can arrange things
so that the supervisor passes
whatever arguments are needed
to its children
so following the conventions gave us a quick wind
but sometimes you want to color outside the lines
don't understand how to do that
let's dig a little deeper
back over in our service to supervisor
we initialize the supervisor
with a list of children like this
notice we didn't have to tell it how to start
each child process
so how does it know
so check this out survey pledge server
we know that that's a gen server
and when a process uses the gen server behavior
we've seen that some
functions are automatically injected
into the module
well one of those
functions that we haven't looked at yet is called
child spec
so by default
when we give the supervisor a child module like this
like pledge server
well it calls the child spec function
passing in an empty list just like this
and that returns what's called a child specification
which is an elixir map
describing how the supervisor should start
and supervise the child process
you see it has an id here
that's just set to serve pledge server
and that's just used internally by the supervisor
to identify this child
it also has restart
which indicates when a terminated child process
should be restarted
now permanent which is what it's set to right now
by default means the child process is always restarted
another option is temporary
which indicates the child process should never
be restarted it also has shut down
which indicates how a child process should be
terminated this is a timeout value
we see it's got a type and that's a worker
because this isn't a supervisor
it's a regular gendered process
and then here's the key to how it gets started
we see that the start key has a value that's a tuple
where the first element is the module
the second element is the function
to run
and then the third element is a list of arguments
well it's going to pass an empty list
so the list of arguments
is just one argument up by default
which is an empty list itself
so this is typically referred to as the mmafa
module function
and then the argument
and given that information
this supervisor knows how to start this child process
you can think of a child spec as a
recipe the supervisor uses to spawn its children
now the default child specs work
great for the purposes of our application
but we'll give you some starting points
so you know how to customize if need be
for example what if you wanted to change
restart from permanent to temporary
well I'll just copy this out
we'll come back over here we'll go to our pledge server
and then when we use
gen server we can tack on some options
we're going to say restart is now temporary
and by doing this we're going to override
the default restart
that's in the default child's back
if we save that away
come back over here and we reload
survey pledge server
and we look at its child spec again
by calling that child spec function
well look at that restart is now temporary
now taking it a step further
if you wanted to change a bunch of these defaults
you can override the default child spec function
so you can just take this map I'll just
copy this whole thing here
we'll come back over to our pledge server
and then I'm going to remove this
because I don't just want to override that
and I'm going to define my own child spec function
it's child spec
it takes an org
and then you just paste that map in just like that
and change any of these values you want
and then
when the supervisor calls the child spec function
well it'll get all your overrides
armed with this knowledge
you have a lot of flexibility when it comes to
overriding the defaults for custom behavior
now we don't need this level of customization
so I'm just going to remove this before moving on