returning to the big picture
what happens if either the kickstarter or
services to provide their process is crash
who's going to supervise the supervisors
well supervisors can supervise both gen servers and
other supervisors
because the supervisor
itself is a special type of gen server
so we'll add a top level supervisor
simply named supervisor
and thereby create a supervision tree
an upshot of nesting supervisors hierarchically like
this is if a worker process crashes
its exit signal
doesn't propagate beyond its immediate supervisor
remember each supervisor traps exit signals in this way
runtime airs are isolated to a specific sub tree
and the rest of the application keeps humming along
let's create the top level supervisor
it's just going to be called supervisor got yx
and survey supervisor
and again there's no magic to this naming
this is just our top level supervisor
we call it supervisor
you could call it top level supervisor
or whatever makes sense to you
the key thing is that you use this supervisor behavior
now we're going to need a start link and an
nit function very
similar to what's already in our services supervisor
so I'm just going to go ahead and copy those over
there's our top level supervisor again
and I'll paste those in
and then we'll just change
this from starting the service supervisor to starting
the supervisor
and then in terms of the children it's going to be
servy kickstarter
that's a gen server and then the
second one is going to be
servy services supervisor
which is our 2nd level supervisor
and again we're going to use this
one for one restart strategy
if you wanted it to restart everything
if either of the children crash you could use one
for all
but we're going to use one for one
just keep in mind that each supervisor in the tree
can use a different restart strategy
depending on the situation
as we did before
for this to work
we need to make
minor changes to both kickstarter and
services supervisors so
that they follow the conventions
so we'll start with kickstarter
we'll rename the interface function from start
to start link
and when we start the gen server we need to call start
link as well and then remember
the supervisor is going to pass an arg
which will ignore
save that away
then over in our services supervisor which is the
other child
well we already have a startling function to find
but it needs to take an arg which will ignore
with those changes made
we're ready to fire up the top level supervisor
so okay and it's going to be the supervisor pid
we call survey supervisor start link
awesome that starts up
everything for us
now we know how it started its children
yeah since kickstarter is a gem server
it has a child spec function
so survey kickstarter
it called the child spec function
passed it an empty list
and that returns its child spec
notice that the function is start
link and it passes in
a empty list and we've got a start link function so
it just called it
and interestingly
even though services supervisor is a supervisor
it also has a child spec
so if we look at services supervisor
call its child spec function
well look at that
it's got a map that looks very similar to kickstarter
only difference is
you know it's services supervisor
it's going to start
services supervisor by calling start link
in an empty list
and you notice the type in this case is supervisor
rather than worker
so when you use the supervisor behavior
a default
child spec function is automatically injected
into the module which has a default type of supervisor
basically it's just child specs all the way down
now if our web server process crashes
it should get restarted
without affecting the rest of the application
let's go find it
each itupee server
will pipe it into process exit
and we'll send it caboom
perfect the kickstarter
trapped the exit signal and restarted the web server
but the other processes weren't impacted
let's try crashing the pledge server
which is managed by the second level supervisor
okay in this case the second level services supervisor
trapped the exit signal which
triggered a restart of the child process
we see that right here
and it
also prevented the exit signal from being propagated
further up the tree
so again
the arrow was isolated to this supervisor sub tree
so now let's crash the services supervisor itself
I'm just going to get it this way
process where is
and we registered this under the name
which was its module so its
services supervisor
that's the pid
and then we can call process exit on that pid
and to make the supervisor terminate abnormally
we can't just send it caboom
we can't send it any old reason like that
the supervisor will trap exit signals
but kill is an untrappable exit signal
so we're gonna pass it kill
it sounds pretty brutal
but that's what we need to do to crash a supervisor
and we see that it gets restarted
and it also started its children
so why did it have to restart its children
while terminating the services supervisor
caused all of its children to be terminated
because remember
links are by directional
this is actually a good thing
you can terminate a supervisor
without worrying about its children being orphaned
and running around unsupervised
so now you understand how elixir
riding atop the earlang vm
and leveraging otp libraries
is well
suited for systems that require high availability and
fault tolerance
it's pretty amazing stuff and remember
it's been battle tested through many
years of production use