currently we have to jump into fix
and manually start our top level supervisor
yeah instead
we'd like the supervisor to start automatically
when the application itself starts
so when the application starts
how do we get it to run this line of code
it starts our top level supervisor
which fires everything up
but to answer our question we need to take a step back
up to this point
we've been using the term application fairly loosely
but an application is a first class top entity
and all along
we've been working in the context of an to application
let's see what's been going on behind the scenes
1st I'm going to get out of ix
and I'm just going to clean up all the build artifacts
all the compiled code
by using mix clean
okay then if I use mix compile
while we see it compiled to 20 files
and then it said generated
servile in the same way
if I were to clean up everything again
and jump into an ix session
well it automatically compiles everything
compiling 20 files and it also says generated
servi app
now we'll come back to where
the app got generated in a minute
first
let's see which applications are currently running
to do that we can use the application module
and there's a function called started applications
well this is pretty interesting
we see that our survey app is a running application
along with a bunch of other applications including
poison which is an external dependency
we added earlier in the course
now
poison started a few other applications that it needed
including ssl
and public key and crypt
and we even see elixir
and mix and sex and standard lib and colonel
those are all currently running applications
so calling ix
dash
s mix automatically started the survey application
and all of its dependencies which are
also applications
but how did it know to do all that
well this brings us full circle back to the mix
ex file that is
right underneath the survey top level directory
you'll remember
that this file got generated when we
created the project
using mix new
and in the project function we see the application name
survey also the version number
and then it calls the
depth function to get external dependencies
and down there
we added poison as an external dependency
earlier on in the course
and poison is an application in its own right
and then we also have this application function
that describes the application
we saw that the poison application was automatically
started because it's listed as a dependency
and mix infers
what to start
and then we can use this extra applications to start
any extra applications that are included
or shipped with elixir early
for example
by default the logger application is started
so all the information in this file is used to generate
the survey application
so where is the generated survey application file
I'm
in a regular terminal session here in the top level
survey directory
and all the build artifacts live in the
underscore build directory
now once we go into this directory we're in earlingland
so the structure feels a bit on orthodox
to an elixir developer
but it follows the conventions expected by top
and the earling vm
so under the bill
directory there are two sub directories
dev and test so I'm going to go down into dev
then there are two sub directories under it
consolidated don't worry about it
and then live we're going to go down there
and then under lib we see two sub directories
poison and survey
those are the two applications
let's go into the survey sub directory
and then there's consolidated which will ignore
and the most important part is the e bin directory
so what's inside of there
well it includes a bunch of files ending in
beam that correspond to each of our modules
these are compiled binary files that run
on the earling vim
during compilation
all the files in our lib directory were compiled
and the resulting beam vials ended up in this directory
but if you look at the bottom
notice that there's also a survey dot app file
it's a plain text file
so let's go ahead and see what's inside
and I'm just going to use the cat command to do that
it's just going to print out what's in that file
servey dot app
and
I'll just shrink it down so we can see everything here
well interestingly it's earling code
this is just one big earling topple right here
it includes the application name survey
there's a description survey
we see that there's a version number
right there
it also has a list of compiled modules here's the list
and each of those modules corresponds to a beam file
and then there's also a list of applications
so we see the poison application logger
and then
also colonel's standard lip and elixir were in the mix
so you can think of this
as a specification that defines the service application
this file was automatically generated by mix
in part by using information that's in the mix
excess file we looked at earlier
now the good news is we never have to touch this file
it's generated for us
well let's add a better description of our application
let's call it a humble http server
yes we just come back over to our mix ex
and we can add a description key under project
a humble http server
save that away
now back over here
I'm in my top level survey directory
if I use mix compile
and then we look at that service app again
well you notice the descriptions changed
it's now a humble hip server
so the service dot app file got updated
when we ran mixed compile
now we saw that the build directory
also had the poison app
so let's take a look at that
it's under build
and it's under dev lib poison
and we want to go down into e bin directory for it
well
and you see that there's just a bunch of beam files
corresponding to all the modules
that are in the poison library
and there's also a poison dot app file
looks pretty familiar
let's have a look at that
poison nut app and I'm just going to run the
cat command on it
shrink it down a little bit
so we can see the full thing
well it's got a description has all the modules
it's got a version number
and then the applications that it needs started
so when we fire up if s mix it compiles
everything that's out of date
generates a new service file
and then top looks for the service file
and uses it to start the application
and all of its dependencies
including poison we see right here
back over an ix
we can also stop the application as a hole
and then start it again
so we can use that application module
we can call stop
on our survey application
okay now if we look at started applications again
well you notice servi isn't at the top
so we could restart it by using start passing serve
and now it started again
so the takeaway here
is that an top application is a first class entity
that can be started and stopped as a unit as
a whole and can be reused in other systems
in this way it's more like a component
or a service than a traditional application
so now that we have a better
understanding of what an top application is
let's return to our original goal
even though our application is running
we still have to start the supervisor manually to
bootstrap everything
instead of manually starting the supervisor
we want the supervisor to start automatically
when the application itself starts
so how do we typically tell top to do something
that specific to our application
well we use a callback
we've used callbacks to specialize gendered behaviors
and we've used
callbacks to specialize supervisor behaviors
in the same way
we'll use a callback to specialize
the application behavior
as the callback module will use this file survey
ex it's under lib
but it's not in the survey sub directory
it's this top level file that was generated when we ran
mix new a long
long time ago
so we'll get rid of this hello stuff here
and then we're going to use the application behavior
and the application behavior expects the callback
module to define a start function
start function takes two arguments
the first one is going to be the type
now this is typically just the atom
normal so we're going to ignore that
and the second one is arguments
and we're going to ignore those as well
then we're going to print out
starting the application
so this start function will be invoked
when the application starts
what do we want to do
well we want to start our top level supervisor
and I happen to have that quit
I'm just going to paste it right in there
in start must return a tuple
okay pid where pid identifies the supervisor process
so we can leave it like this
or we can just remove this
because we know that a tuple is going to get returned
and then that will be implicitly returned
by the start function
which fulfills our side of the bargain
so by writing this application behavior
we basically want to override
the generic application behavior for the application
and to do that we need to make sure
that this survey module is called
and we do that in mix ex
down in this application section
we're going to add a new line here
it's going to be mod
and mod specifies that callback module to invoke
when the application is started
we give it a tuple and then we give it the module
survey
and top will invoke the start function of that module
that's part of the contract
and we can pass it rag
and we're just going to use an empty list
but you could pass whatever argument you need
the callback module can be
any module that uses the application behavior
so you could have created a new
survey application module for example
but it's also common just to use this
top level module survey
the takeaway here is that top will automatically call
this module start function
when it starts the application
so we'll save that away
and then we want to start a new sex session
and look at that
this time it fires everything up
it started the application
then it started our top level supervisor
and then everything else fell in place
now what if you wanted to start the application
without the sex shell
well you could use mix run
yeah I'll just get out of here if you run mix run
like that
and it starts everything up
but then we end up back in a terminal session prompt
well that's because the instance
terminated as soon as our service
start function finished
after the top level supervisor started
so to keep it running we need to use this
no halt option
no dash halt
perfect
seeing that output reminds me that our web server
always runs on port 4000
yeah the port number is currently hard
coded in our kickstarter module
so over here under survey
there it is kickstarter
and then down here we're starting it on port 4000
we can make this easier to configure
by adding a default port value
to the applications environment
to do that we come back over to our mix ex file
and then we'll add
another line down here under application
it's going to be end and then we give it a keyword list
so our port
we want to be 3000 I'm going to use 3000
just so that you see it changes from 4000
so what this is going to do is add this key value pair
to the applications environment
so let's save this away
then back over here
I'm going to kill sex and I'm going to use mix compile
that's going to generate a new service app file
and if we have a look at that
we'll notice that the port 3000 is part of
this application file
so now when top starts the application
the default application environment
will include the port
then back over and kick starter
rather than hard coating the port
we can read it from the application's environment
yeah
the way we do that is we use the application module
there's a function get end
we pass it the application's name serving in this case
and the name of the variable which is port
then we can just use that port variable right down here
and now when we fire up ix s mix
well you notice
our web servers now listening on port 3000
pretty cool now that we have a complete
proper top application running
let's see what it looks like in the observer gooey
yeah let's fire that up
earlier on in the course we looked at
the individual process is running by going
into this processes tab
but now we can go to the applications tab
and see all the applications that
are currently running
it's over on the left hand side here
including our humble little survey application
so let's start by having a look at the sex application
well this is interesting we see its supervision tree
it has a supervisor and then it has
two gen servers here
and we now know exactly how that works
yeah if we look at colonel
well it has a supervisor
colonel sup is what it's named
and then notice it's got a second level supervisor
colonel safe sup
and then it has some processes under here
so this is its supervision tree
if we look at logger
well it's got a top level
supervisor and then it's got a watcher supervisor
and then it's got some worker processes
and now for the big reveal
here's our supervision tree
we've got our top level supervisor
we've got our kickstarter
our services supervisor that's our 2nd level
and then they're managing children
okay
let's see what happens when we kill a worker process
such as the pledge server
okay if we click on that
we see down here it's pied one sixty nine currently
so I can right click on it
kill process send it to kill signal
okay we see down here
starting the pledge server
so it got restarted by our services supervisor
and if I click on pledge server now
well it's a different pid now it's 4 6 6
oh that's pretty cool
what happens if we kill the services supervisor though
if we click on it right now it's pit one sixty eight
we'll kill it the same way
all right we see
the services supervisor is getting restarted
which started the pledge server
and the sensor server
and if we click on services supervisor its pit is now
4 7 4 that's pretty sweet
that wraps it up for this course
thanks so much for joining us
we hope you have a lot of fun
using a picture to build your own apps
we'll see you next time
now let's go photograph some bears
or maybe even sasquatch