now as you'll recall our request string has
multiple lines and we need to parse that first line
so we know how to respond
that's right
we need to parse the request string to create a map
that looks like this
now an elixir map starts with this %
and then we have a curly brace here
and a curly brace at the end
and then inside of here we have key value pairs
where the keys in this case are
elixir atoms which are like ruby symbols
again it's a constant whose name is its value
so we've got the key method
and the values get path is wild things
and obviously we want to
replace these hard coded values here and here
with whatever is in this request string
so let's fire up sex and let's play
around with how to parse the request string
alright sex
and then I'm going to paste in our request string
which is a here dock
just so we have that available
so to parse this string we're going to use a
string function
and you can use the handy h
function inside of ix to get some help
we can say string dot that's the name of the module
then if you just hit tab
it uses auto completion to show us all the functions
we can call
and notice that there are three split functions
split one split split two and split split three
the number here indicates how many
arguments the function expects
it's often referred to as the functions airily
so a module can define
multiple functions with the same name
and a different ability
and then the function is uniquely
identified by its containing module
in this case the string module
its name and iterate
in this case we're going to use split two
so then if I just complete
this with split and hit return well
it gives us a little bit of help
about how to call split with some examples there
so split returns a list
which I'm going to capture in a variable called lines
we're going to call string split
I have the request
that's the first argument to it
and then we're going to split it
on a new line
because
remember a request of multiple lines that we want each
line to be an element in that list
that will just split it on new lines that way
and that gives us back a list of all the lines
then if we wanted the first line we could use
the list module has a function called first
and pass it in a list
and that will just give us the first line
it's the request line that we're interested in
so another way to do this will be using a pipe
so we stay first line equals request
pipe that into string split
now the first argument to that is the request
the second argument is what to split on
well the first argument is going to be piped in
from the left
so we just have to specify the
second argument
that's going to return a list
and so we can pipe that further
into
list first
we get the same thing
so let's just go ahead and copy this line at well
paste it into our parse function
and I'll just paste it to replace our to do there
so now that we have the first
line we now need to split it
into its own parts
I'm just going to clean this up
and we have our first line
remember that's already been stored
and now we just want to split this first line
into these three different parts
so we're going to say parts equals string split
we'll take the first line
in this case we'll split it based on a space
and we get back a list of three elements with
each of those parts
but we're only interested in the method in the path
not really the protocol
so one way to get at these would be to use the e new
module that's built into elixir
and there's an app function
you give it a list in this case parts and then
the index of the thing you want
so index zero would give us the method which is get
and index one
would give us the path
now that works but it's not idiomatic
elixir code pattern matching gives us a more
elegant and powerful way to do the same thing
and pattern matching is a huge influence on how you
design elixir code
it's also an important
difference if you're transitioning from oo
to functional programming
so let's look at
some examples of pattern matching in sex
so here's something familiar let's say a equals one
what this does is that binds the value
on the right hand side
one in this case
to the variable a that's on the left hand side
and we would recognize that as just assignment
so now the value of a is one
but the interesting thing is the equal operator
an elixir isn't assignment
like we're used to in other languages
it's actually called the mash operator
so check this out
one equals a well that returns the value one
so what's happening here is
elixir always tries to make the left hand side
this same as the right hand side
if the mat succeeds
it returns the result of the match expression
and that's exactly what happened here we got back one
this match is because both the left and right hand side
are equal to one
but what happens if the left and the right
don't match so two equals a
well we get back a match air
because the value of a is one
and two equal one is a match air
now if there's a variable on the left
and a value on the right
then the variable gets bound
to the value to make the match succeed
so if we say a equals two
well we've got a variable on the left
and a value on the right
so it's going to bind two to the variable a
and it's a match so we get back two
as the result of that expression
this effectively rebinds a to the value of two
it started off with the value of one
but we rebound it to a value of two
so now if we say two equals a
will those match and we get back two again
now sometimes you don't want to rebind the variable
instead you want a
pattern match against the variables existing value
in that case you need to use the pin operator
it looks like that
if we say a equals three
well it's a match error
notice it didn't try to bind the value three
to the variable a
instead it looked at the existing value of a
which is two in this case and that doesn't equal three
so how is this useful in practice
well actually pattern matching is used all
over the place in elixir programs
and we'll see many examples throughout this course
and one of the most
powerful ways to use pattern matching is to destruct
complex data types
such as lists
so let's just start at the top again
let's say I've got a list one two and three
we can say equal one
two and three so
the right and the left are the same
and we have a match
but we'd like to restructure this list
that's on the right hand side
and to do that we can put
variables on the left hand side
so here in this position I'll just say 1st
if we hit return there well it's a match 1 2 3
so that variable first on the left hand side
got bound to the value one
because that's in the position
of the list on the right hand side
to make this whole match succeed
so now if we look at the variable first
well it has the value one
now it's important to note that elixir will only change
the value of a variable that's on the left hand side
so if we had a variable over here
it wouldn't try to bind it to anything
so now if we wanted to restructure our list
a little bit further
we can use multiple variables on the
right hand side
so this might be first
we'll leave the two in there in the middle
and if we use last here
what we've got first being one and last being three
so you can think of the left side
as a pattern you're trying to successfully
match with the term on the right hand side
in this case the right and the left
have the same structure
there are three element lists
the literal two on the right hand side
matches the literal two
in the same position on the left hand side
and then to make the match the value one is bound
to the variable first and the value three is bound
to the variable last
so one of a specific value doesn't match
like let's change two to seven
well in that case
the two literals don't match in the middle
so we get a match here
now that's not surprising
but it demonstrates that we can use pattern matching
to both check
literal values
and extract values
now what if the structures are different sizes
like let's remove this seven all together
yeah we'll just have a two element list over here
well that's a match error as well
so now we know how to apply
pattern matching to parse our string
yeah we've got our first line in there
remember that's in the first line variable
so we can split it string split
1st line split it
on spaces and we know that's going to return a list
like that so let's make it match
this is going to be the method we want to capture that
in a method variable
this is going to be the path
and that's going to be the version
and that's a match method is get
path is wild things
and the version is http one rot one
now we're not really interested in the http version
so another thing you can do is
just use an underscore right here
which will match
anything on the right hand side
it's basically a wild card
so now we can go ahead and copy this out of here
paste it back in our parse function
so this line
assigns the first line so we can just paste in here
the thing that splits that first line
and gives us the method path
and we ignore the http protocol
and now we can change our map to use
the parsed values rather than these hardcoded value
so this is going to be method
and the value of path is going to be
what's ever in the path variable
and we can remove this co n variable because
this is the last expression of the function
so this is what's going to be implicitly returned
so parts is going to return a map which is
exactly what we want
so this will work
but we can make it more concise using pipes
so let's rearrange this a bit
we'll get rid of this temporary variable first line
so we take our request which is a multi line string
we want to split it into a list of lines
then we want to get the first line
then we want to split that first
line into its three parts
so I'm just going to take this out
cut it out here into my copy paste buffer
what we really want to do is pipe
the result of this expression
which is going to be a string
into this function
and the pipe will do that it will supply
first line is the first argument there
so the pipe will supply that argument
and then all this is going to return
this again
so you can kind of think of this as a hierarchy
of pipelines
we've got our high level pipeline here request
transforming all the way into response
and then in this particular step of the pipeline
we get into this pipeline here
which does sort of sub related to that
you can almost think of these pipelines as being
fractal we could have one of these
call a function that then does a whole another pipeline
so it's kind of like pipelines all the way down
we're going to see a lot
more examples of pattern matching going forward
for now though
this transformation is complete
and we're ready to update the response body next