so now that we have our requests
parsed and we know it's asking for wild things
we need to fill the response body with
those wild things
bears lions and tigers
oh my now
obviously we're going to have to handle requests for
other things which we'll do in the next section
but for now it's all wild things
now as things stand
the parse function returns a map
with an empty response body
and in our pipeline the result of that
is passed into rout
so down in our route function
this co and v map
already has the method and the path filled in
but the response body is empty as nicole said
so in our route function we just need to update the map
to include the response body like
bears lines and tigers as we have here
and we won't need to set
method and path as we're doing here
because
that's already going to be set on this co and v map
when it comes into route
now we've seen this map syntax before
it's a collection of key value pairs
so I said let's hop back
into sex and get more familiar with elixir maps
sure
I'm just going to copy this map and take it with us
I already have an ix session running
so I'm just going to paste that in
and then I'm going to change
the response body to be
an empty string because that's how
this map's going to
start out now
the keys on our map are atoms
so we can get the value for those keys using ceo and v
that's the name of the atom there method
and we get back get
if we want to get the path we can do it that way
and just something to notice
atoms always start with a colon
and the method here uses the syntax method colon
if you're using
atoms as keys in a map
this will be familiar
again if you've programmed in ruby
but what happens
if we try to get the value of a key that doesn't exist
like mike we get back nil if there's no matching key
so instead I prefer to use the dot notation
which is a bit more strict
we can just say con
path
that'll give us back that and if I try it on my name
while I get an actual error
there's no key mic found in that map
now just be aware that this dot notation
only works if the keys are atoms
so what we want to do is update the response body value
now if you're coming from an object oriented background
you would expect that we can use the assignment syntax
because in oo program state is mutable
so you think you could just do a familiar assignment
something like this
where you assign it to
bears for example
but we get this funny compiler partially because
remember that the equal is a match operator
but more important is that
in elixir all data structures are immutable
so we can't change
the co and v map using assignment like this
rather than modifying or mutating the map
we need to transform it into a new map
and we do that by calling a function
so I'm just going to start at the top again
we'll use that h function to get some help
and there's a module in elixir called map
by just key and dot and then hit a tab
it'll do some auto completion
and we want to put a new key and value into the map
so there's a function put
and you notice it has an verity of three
which means it takes three arguments
so if we just have a look at the help
well the first argument is the map that we want to
change is going to create a new copy of this map
we want to add a key
which in this case is b and a value of two
and that's going to return a new map
so we just use map put
first argument is the map and that's in our co and v
variable the key is response body
and the value is bears
and you notice we get back a map
which has the response body
with the new value of bears but if we look at clv
well it's unchanged it has a response body
equal to an empty
string
so it's important to recognize that this didn't modify
this co and v map
remember all data structures and elixir are immutable
instead it creates a new copy of the map
which has the updated response body
so we can add
new key value pairs
but the original map is never modified
all functions that transform data such as map put
return a new copy of the data
therefore in order to capture the new map
returned by the pud function
we need to bind it to a variable
yeah we'll just rebind it to this co n variable
just like that so we used our initial co and v map map
put returned a new copy of that
that we then just rebounded to co and v again
and this is a pretty common way to do it
we just transformed one map
into another map
and if we look at co and v now well
we see that the response body is set to bears
just as we would expect
now updating a map is
so common that there's a handy shortcut to do this
instead of using map put we can use this syntax
we give it cnv then we use a vertical bar
and we give it the key in
the value we want to change would be response body
and let's say this time we want it to be bears lions
tigers
and then if we look at co and v now
we see that this also returns a new copy of the map
the response body is now bears lions and tigers
one thing to keep in mind is using this shortcut
you can
only modify values that already exist in the map and
we already have a response body field
so this works
so this is a nice little shortcut
let's just go ahead and copy this
and we'll paste it back in our
route function
so we'll just paste it in here
we can get rid of this line
and our to do is done
because this creates a new map that
also has the response body
so we have one final to do
now we need to update the http response string
based on what's in the map
like
we don't want content links to be hard coded anymore
and we want this to be dynamically generated
we already know how to access values in the map
so this is pretty straightforward
we're inside of a hear dock
and we can use string interpolation
so instead of this hard coated 20
we can just interpolate
the length of the response body
so we'll use the string module
it has a length function and then we'll pass it the
response body part of the conversation map
and then down here we'll just interpolate
con response body
and that should take care of this to do
and if we save this away and run it
well we get our response
we've been seeing the same output all along
but now it's being dynamically generated
because the route's getting called with
the co and v map
we're putting a response body
and then that's getting passed into format response
and we're dynamically generating that content
so essentially our initial request
is being transformed into a valid response
through a series of functions
next up we'll look at our 2nd request