so we're making good progress
but our server's still kind of dumb
after all it can only handle one request
well let's create a second request
I was thinking this one could be for
just the bears at our wildlife refuge
oh that sounds like fun
now before we do that
let's print out the request
so we can see what it looks like
before it gets routed
so we want to add some
logging into the pipeline and it's going to be
after the parts
but before the route so we'll just add a step here
and I'm going to call the function log
what's cool about this pipeline
design is we can plug in
any function that takes a conversation map
and returns a conversation map
so then we can define log
just put it right here
it's going to take a co n map
it's going to have to return one as well
to work in that pipeline
and then right here I'm going to use io inspect
we want to print out a map
so instead of using put us I'm going to use inspect
and we want to inspect that map
now this will work but we can make it more concise
because inspect prints the data structure and
also returns the given data structure unchanged
and because of that we could remove this line
and now we're just left with a
single line function here and there's a more concise
way to represent single
line functions that's to put a comma here
a colon after do
then we can just bring this up here
and then get rid of the end
then if we save this and run it well
we notice we've got
a representation of our map being printed out
right here before we see the response so we
see what we're getting in as a request
so let's handle another get request
so let's take the one we have
and change it for slash bears
okay I'm just going to take the request we have
and all this stuff
and I'm just going to copy it for now
and we'll change the request from wild things to bears
but if we run it now
well we get the same response before
because our route function currently returns
only one response
yeah both of these are returning bears lions and tigers
so to fix that we'll just look at our
route function here
and a conventional solution would be to use
an if statement
elixir it looks like this
if do else end
nothing really surprising here
so we could look at the co and v it has a path key
we'll say if that equals wild things
well then we want to return this map
otherwise we're getting a request for just bears
so we'll return a list of bears which would be like
teddy smoky and paddington
and if we run it well
that works for our first request we
get back bears lines and tigers
because we're requesting wild things
when we request bears
we get back teddy smoking paddington
but in elixir you don't use
if conditionals as often as you would
in imperative languages such as ruby
instead
it's more idiomatic to control the flow of the program
using pattern matching and functions
in this case we can use pattern matching
to match incoming requests
and run an appropriate function
to fill in the response body
so we'll have a function called route
it's going to take
a co and v as the first argument and we need that
so that we can update the response body
and then it's going to take in the path
in this case this one will be for wild things
and when that function gets run
while we want to return this map
then we'll define a second route function
this one will also take the map
but it will have the path of bears
and when that function is run
we want to return this map
so we have two function definitions with the same name
and the same number of arguments
in this case two arguments
and in elixir parlance
we refer to these as function clauses
and if a function has several clauses
elixir will try
each clause until it finds one that matches
now these functions take two arguments
but in the pipeline route gets past a single argument
con right and that's this function here it
has an ability of one co and v so
inside of here we don't want to do this
we've got this represented in our function clauses
so what we need to do is take this one arty function
and call a route method
that takes two arguments or has an ability of two
so we'll just pass along conv
and we'll also pass along conv path
so we've got a one arty function
calling a two ability function
and when that two ability function is called
elixir will run
the first function clause that matches that pattern
so pattern matching applies
anytime we need to bind values to variables
for example when calling a function
and passing arguments to it
so we're going to call this function like this
co and v is going to match that
and then whatever the literal value of the path is
we'll match the second parameter there
so it's going to do pattern matching on those strings
and does it work
if we run it we get teddy
smoky and paddington for the second request and bears
lions and tigers
now http requests are uniquely identified by their path
and their method
get post etc so let's change
the function clause to include the method too
yeah we'll put the method as the second argument
so these are begets
put that one down here as well
so now these functions have an ability of three
so when we call it here we need to
also pass the comfort method
so now we have a one arty function calling a
three arty function
so we're on a roll
let's try a third request this one for bigfoot
all right I'm just going to copy these down here again
we'll clean this up a little bit later
but for now we're just on a roll
so we're going to
keep going with this
instead of bears I've got a request for bigfoot
now we know we don't have a function clause that
matches this request
so what's going to happen
well when we run it we get an error says no function
claws matching
route three and we see that the path is
bigfoot so elixir tried to find a matching function
but it doesn't exist
because we're only matching wild things and bears
now we'll go ahead and fix that in the next section
but one thing we've noticed so far
is that pattern matching removes the need for
if else conditionals
and we know we're going to handle
more requests coming up
and so we're not going to end up with this
long fl's conditional
instead we're just going to use
function clauses to match on those requests
that's right
instead we can write short declarative functions