so we left
you with a bit of a cliff hanger at the end of
the last module
has bigfoot been spotted at our wildlife refuge or not
well unfortunately no it hasn't been
in either case
what happens when a route doesn't match in our server
well
we should also handle requests that take parameters
one of the reasons we decided to build a web
server in this course
is it presents different scenarios to learn
different features of elixir
so let's look at some more pattern matching techniques
as they're central to building elixir apps
so here are the two routes we have defined so far
one for wild things
1 4 bears and these
are the two resources that our application knows about
but for everything else
for any other requests that we get
we want to send a four row four response
saying that the resource can be found
and to do that we'll define a catch all route
I'm just going to do it right up here
so be route it's going to take our conversation map
and then instead of using a literal string like get
I'm just going to use method
that's a variable that will get
matched to whatever argument is passed in
as the second argument there
and then in the same way we want to match any path
so I'm just going to use a variable path there
which will match anything
and then inside of here
well we just return
a updated conversation map so co and v
our vertical bar and then our response body
in this case is going to say
no
path here
so whatever the third argument is that gets past
this function is going to get bound
to the variable path which we can use
inside of the function body
and if we run this right now
we'll get a warning saying that method wasn't used
inside of the function body
so we can just ignore that warning
by putting an underscore
before that variable
if we save that away and run it
well we see no bigfoot here at the bottom but
no bears here
no wild things here
everything is matching this
route that's returning know whatever here
if we go to the top we see we get this warning
this function claws cannot match
because of previous claws online
26 always matches
and that's because
elixir tries to match function clauses from
top to bottom
in the order they're specified in the file
that's right and we have our catch all route to find
above our other routes and we used variables here
so whatever value is passed in is the second argument
it's going to match automatically
to that variable method
or it's going to bind that value
the same way
the third argument value is going to be bound to path
so this is going to match any method and path
and because it matches all requests it's going to
get called for every request that we try to handle
so any routes to find
below this are never going to be considered
so we only want this function to be called
if no other clauses match
in other words it's the default function clause
so we need to define it last
yeah we'll just take it off the top here
put it down below our other routes
and if we save that away and run it
well we get no bigfoot here that's what we expected
but all of our
other requests are getting handled as we would expect
one other thing we should mention
not only is it helpful to group the function clauses
together so you can easily see the order
but if you move the catch all route out of the group
say we move it below format response
and then we run it well
if we scroll up
we'll see a warning
that says they need to be grouped together
so before moving on we'll just undo that
so our response body is being updated
but the 200 ok is our status
well that really isn't correct
it really should be a four or four
but right now it's hard coated in our response string
so to make this more dynamic
we need to be able to pull out
the status code from our conversation map
and then we can just interpolate that down here
so we need to add a status field to the
conversation map and that's just up here at the top
I'm going to split these out
into multiple line
just to make it a little bit easier to read
and we'll just have a feel
called status and we'll set it to nil initially
then down in our catch all route which is at the bottom
here we can set the status to four or four
and this just demonstrates
you can update
multiple fields in a map using the syntax
and just remember you're going to get back a
new copy of this map
and then we also need to set a status here
this is going to be status 200 that was successful
as well this is going to be status 200
and then finally
we can interpolate that instead of a hard coded 200
here we'll just use
com status
now status codes have a corresponding reason phrase
for example 200 is okay
but four or four is not found
so to do that
we need a mapping of the status codes to their
corresponding reason
and to make quick work of this
I have a function here
that we can just paste in to do this
now sometimes you want to define
private functions that can
only be called within the module
that they're defined in
and to do that you use def instead of def
so just to demonstrate that
we've set this status reason
to be a private function and as such it can't
be called outside the module
and it takes a single argument the code
and then inside of the function body
we have a map
in this particular case
we're trying to map status codes to their reasons
and so the keys in this map are numbers
they're not atoms
then as such we need to use this a to
tie the key to the value
and this will be familiar
if you are a ruby programmer because you use
similar arrow syntax in ruby hashes
so given a code
we can use a square bracket syntax
to access the value that's associated with that code
given this function then we can interpolate
the status reason instead of the hardcoded
okay we just interpolate
status reason
and pass it in the status which is cv status
save that away and run it
now for no bigfoot
here we see it's a four or four not found
but for everything else it should be a 200 ok
so let's create a new request
let's take the request for bears
and change it to bears one
that way we can get a specific bear by its id
bear one bear two bear three whatever
now if we save that away and we run it while we get no
bears one here
and it's getting picked up by our catch all route
to handle this
we're going to need to define a route function clause
that matches the path with
bears at the beginning
and then any number at the end
and there's a really cool way to do this
and to set it up
I'm going to jump into I
x so let's say we have the string bears
and we want to concatenate
the No.1 to the end of that string
well in elixir strings are binaries
and to concatenate binaries
we use the less than greater than operator
and then I just give it the string one
we get back slash bears one
but what's cool is we can also use
the less than
greater than operator
to match the beginning of a string in a pattern match
so let's just replace this one
with a variable id
and then we'll use the match operator and
see if that matches
bears
one and it does what it did is it bound the value one
to the variable id to make
this pattern match the right hand side
and if we look at the id variable well its value is one
so it matched the beginning of the string
and then the rest of the string was bound
to the variable id
so we can use this to define a new
route function clause
it's going to be a get request
and then we want to match a string beginning with
bears slash and then having an id after that
and then in the function body
we'll return an updated conversation map
where the status is 200
and the response body
is bare and then we can use
the value that's bound to the variable id like that
and this works because pattern matching applies
anytime we need to bind values to variables
in this case when this function is called
the third argument
is going to get pattern matched against this pattern
so the argument will be like bears one
it matches the pattern and because it matches it binds
the value one
to id so this is different from these
other route functions
because here we were just matching
literal strings
here we actually have a variable in the pattern
that we match against
and then we can use
that variable inside of the function body
now if we save this away and run it
well we get 200 ok for that request
and it just says bear one
imagine all the
people who would visit our wildlife refuge if we had
a bigfoot
we could charge a fortune for selfies with bigfoot