so now that we have requests flowing through our
pipeline we can add
specialized functions to transform either the request
or the response
for example
let's say we get a request for slash wildlife
well we want to handle that the same way
we would a request for slash wild things
ah we can add a transformation that rewrites
only those requests
and to do that we'll need to pattern match on maps
which is a technique that's used extensively in elixir
and it's also really powerful
we've started by adding a new request for wildlife here
now if you're feeling uneasy about all these
requests being
copied and pasted at the bottom of the file
well just go with it for now
a bit later on
we'll add these to an automated test and
get rid of all this
duplicated code
so we want the request for
wildlife to be handled by this function class
in order to do that we're going to need to change
the path of that request from wildlife
to wild things
so it matches the function claws
and we're going to need to change that path
before the route happens
so if we just look at our pipeline up here
we've got pars log and then rout
so it needs to come after pars obviously but before
rout and I'm actually going to put it before
log as well so that we can log out
the final result
so right here in the pipeline
we're going to add a step called rewrite path
and then to define that function
be right path
well it needs to take a conversation map and
also return a conversation map
and all we want to do in here is update
the given map and change its path to
wild things
so now if we run it well
we see that it pretty much rewrites
all of our requests
to wild things
we only want this function to run
if the map has wildlife as the path
and we can actually use pattern matching to do that
let's play around with pattern matching
maps in sex for just a second
I've got a conversation map set up here
with a key method and a key path
and what we want to do is pattern match it to a map
that has a path of
slash wildlife
we use the match operator
use that map on the right hand side like that
and it matches
even though the map on the left
doesn't have the same number of keys as the map
on the right as long as this left hand side is a map
and it has a path key with wildlife as the value
then this matches
in other words we don't have to provide
all the keys or values for a successful match
and this is great
because we're only interested in matching the path
we don't care what the method is
now let's say we change
this around and set a wildlife we use bears right here
well that's not going to be a match
because the value of the path key
in the term and the right
is not bears it's actually wildlife so
we get a no match air
so we'll set it back to wildlife
and then what happens if we have a key name
with a value mic on this left hand side
well that's not a match because the
map on the right hand side doesn't have a key name
and the keys in the pattern
must exist in the map on the right
now if we were
only interested in get requests we could do something
like this method is get
and that will match the conversation
it will match
any map on the right hand side that has a method of get
now let's suppose we want to check
that the path matches wildlife and if it does
then also extract the value of the method
so instead of using a literal git here
we'll just use a variable method
and then path will use a literal wildlife
and it matches and now
the value of the method
is bound to that variable method
it's
also worth noting that we can bind multiple variables
in one go
yeah we'll just bind method and
also the path we don't care about the literal string
we just want to
bind whatever path we have to the variable path
and we get that as well
so this gives us
everything we need to finish our function clause
yeah remember we just have an argument co nv here
but we'll pattern match it
we'll say we want it to be a path
with the literal slash wildlife
and then we can use the match operator right here
so what this is going to do is
match the incoming argument against this map
and also assign it to the variable co n
and we need to do that because we need to use
co and v in the function body here
to update that conversation map and return a new one
if you didn't need to use it in the function body
well you could just do it just like this
and it would match the argument that's coming in
and only run this function if that matches
but in our case we need to capture that
so we can do that
so let's give that a save and run it
ooh and we get an error here
it's saying that there's no
function claws
that's
matching a map where the method is get and the path is
wild things
well that's because we're calling rewrite path for
every request in the pipeline
but the function claws here
only matches
when the argument is a map with the path key of
wildlife not wild things
so we also need a default function clause
for all the other paths
and since we know that order
matters we need to define it last
right we'll put it right here
rewrite path
it's just going to take any map we'll call it co n
and since this is a single line function
we'll make it more concise
using this deuce intact
and then we just want to return that map unchanged
so this is going to
match any requests where the path is wildlife
and then for
everything else it's going to fall through
and this function clause will get run
just returning the conversation map unchanged
if we give that a save and run it
well sure enough
now all of our requests are
matching the way we would expect
now we can use this same technique to add some tracking
let's say every time we get a four or four
let's log the missing path
well to do that
we'll just add a function
that matches a four or four status code
and then extracts the path
now we'll need to wait until the conversation map
has a status key
and that happens in the route function
so we'll slip in a new track function right
after it in the pipeline
and then we'll define it
we only want this function clause to run
when the status is a four or four
so we'll use a pattern match for it
status needs to be four or four
and then we want to capture the path
and we'll just capture it in a variable call path
and we'll assign that to co
n so we can use it in the function body
now we could do anything we want with this information
but for now let's just print out warning
the name of our path is on the loose
we can use path inside of the function body because
we pattern matched on path here
and because this is a variable
then it's just going to be bound
to whatever value is in the path
and we need to remember to return the conversation map
so it continues flowing through the pipeline
now as we learn with the rewrite function
we also need to define
a default function clause that matches all
the other conversation maps
yeah that's right
so this one just takes
a conversation map and returns it unchanged
if we give that a save and run it
and if we scroll up to the bigfoot request
well we see the response was a four or four
and we printed out that bigfoot is on the loose
so you may have seen this coming
but now that we know how to pattern match on maps
there's a different way to design our route functions
aha
in the pipeline
we're currently calling this route function
that takes one argument
this conversation map
and then we delegate
to the route function that takes three arguments
and then we have multiple function clauses
that pattern match on two string arguments the method
and the path but we
now
know that we can just pattern match on what's in this
conversation map
so let's start by commenting this out
because we won't need it
and then we can update this to just take one argument
I'm just going to copy these
we want this just to take a
conversation map and then we can pattern match on it
so we'll have our map here
I'm going to paste those in
like that and then this is going to be the method
and this is the path
now we need to change
each of these function clauses to just
take one argument
so that they can get cold in the pipeline
so I'll take this one
I'll just paste it down here
and this is just going to be bears
we take this one
paste it down here
this one's a bit different because we need to
pattern match on that parameter
and we can do that right inside of here
using that binary concatenation operator less than
greater than and then our id
so that's kind of neat
we can use this matching inside
of a map that we're matching on the left hand side
and then for our catch all route down here
well we'll get rid of these
and the map will look like this
all we care about
is the path and we want to extract its value
so we'll just restructure it that way
and now all of these function clauses take just one
argument the conversation map
and the pipeline calls route with one argument
so these should just work
we save that away
sure enough it works just as before
as always there are multiple ways to do the same thing
and it's often simply a matter of preference