now the last few sections we focused on
pattern matching
specifically with strings and maps
because pattern matching is a
different way of thinking about programming
and it takes a bit of practice
and you'll use pattern matching all over the place
an elixir even for something
as straightforward and familiar as reading a file
I'm thinking maybe you have a file in mind
as a matter of fact
I've created a top level pages directory with an about
html file in it
now you can make your own file
or you can find this file in the code bundle
and we want to serve this file when we get a request
for slash about
so we already have a request teat up over in hand
ex the request is get slash about
and we've prepared a route function that
matches the request
since there's nothing new to learn here
it just looks like this
we're going to pattern match on the path slash about
and then obviously we want to fill in
the response body
with the contents of the file
for now though if we run it it should work
yep we just get back
contents of file so
we need to serve the file as those contents
so let's hop
over to an ix session to see how to read a file
I'm going to use the h
helper function
and then the
file module contains a bunch of functions for
working with files
we want to read a file so no surprise
the function is called a read
and it says that it returns this
if reading the file was successful or this thing
if reading the file was an error
so what are these things in curly braces
well it's something called a tuple
and a tuple is just an ordered
collection of values in curly braces
most commonly you'll see like
two to four values in these
so in the case of success
the first element of the tuple
is an atom in this case it's okay
and then the second element is a binary
remember strings are binaries in elixir so
this is going to be the contents in the file
and if there's an error
then the first element is the atom error
and then we're going to get a reason variable
and that'll be bound to some result
and if we look down below we see the typical error
reasons would be something like the atom
e and to which indicates that the file does not exist
many built in elixir functions use
this idiom that returns a tuple
so how do we check that reading a file was successful
and if so extract its contents
well you guessed it
by using pattern matching on the return tuple
we're just going to clean this up
so we go back up to the top
so we can use file dot read and
because I started ix in the top level survey directory
then the relative path to our about file is going to be
pages
about html and we know that's going to return a tuple
and we expect this to succeed
so we can match it against the atom
okay and then the contents will get bound
to the contents of that file
and sure enough it's a match if we look at contents
well we've had the contents of our file
well let's see that the file doesn't exist
for example we look foreign about us file
yeah if we try that
then the match fails
because it's actually returning a tuple
with error as the first element and then this
file not exist atom as the second element
so how do we want to handle the case where it fails
well we can write a match for that
yeah we'll just change the match here
this is going to match an error
and then we want to capture the actual error in
a reason variable
and that's a match and if we look at reason
well it's that atom
that tells us that the file doesn't exist
so now back in our route function
we first
need to read the file and we know how to do that
but relative to the directory of the handler
ex file it's two directories up so we're going to use
slash just like that
and then we can use a
case expression to handle the
success and failure scenario
so we say case and then do and end
and then inside of the case
we can match the result of the file
reed expression against multiple patterns
so the first pattern will match will be
okay and then content and we use a little arrow
in that particular case we want to take the
co and v map and update the status to be a 200
and the response body
is going to be whatever that content is
then in the case that there's an error
we'll have the tuple error
and then we'll capture the reason
just like we did in ix
in this case we want to return
a conversation map that has
a status of 500
and the response body
we're just going to say
file air and then will interpolate the reason
so we have a pattern that matches all errors
but let's say we want to return a four
or four with a specific error
if the file isn't found
well we can add that branch above this final branch
so the pattern's going to look like error
but it's going to be a specific error
it's that e and to amp t atom
in that
case we were going to turn a map that looks like this
the status is going to be a four or four
and the body is just going to say
file not found
so just remember that the order here matters
the first pattern that matches is going to win and
that's why we placed
this pattern above this pattern because this is a more
generic form it's just going to capture any reason
in that reason variable
where this is a specific literal match
on that adam e and often
and the result of whichever pattern matches
becomes the result of the
overall case expression
so we don't need this line down here
because our case is going to return the updated map
now if we run it
we see we've got the quote as the
body of that response
now if we change it to about us and then run it
well we should see the file not found there
yep we get a four or four
so now let's change it back to about
and let's run it from the command line
alright I've got it changed
and then at the command line
I'm at the top level of survey directory
so I run elixir
lib survey handler ex
ooh and it says file not found
and that's because we're running at the top level
survey directory
and in our code we're trying to find the about page
relative to this directory
slash pages now
this works in sublime because the current directory is
lib slash survey
so we need to get the absolute path to the about
html file so it can be found
regardless of which directory were in
when the app is run
here's how to get the absolute path
and I'm going to use
temporary variables for a minute
but we'll clean this up with a pipeline
a little bit later
so let's say we have a pages path variable
and then the
path module in elixir has a whole bunch of functions
for dealing with paths
one of those functions is expand
and what we want to do is expand this path
pages relative to the directory in which
this file is defined
and we can get that by using underscore
underscore underscore
so this returns the absolute path of the
directory of the current file
wherein handler
ex so that's going to be the absolute path down to lib
serve and then path expand is going to expand this path
relative to this 2nd path
so pages path is going to be the absolute path
down to this pages directory
now that gives us the directory
but we also need to join on the actual file
so to do that
we'll have a variable file and it's going to be path
there's a join function and it takes in our pages path
and then we want to join on about
html and that'll make sure to
use a proper file separator
so now that we know how these functions work
and the arguments they take
let's remove the temporary variables and
use a pipeline instead
so ultimately we want a file
we can take the expanded path
and then pipe it into
path joint which means this path is going to be
the first argument that's piped in
so we can get rid of that
and then down in file dot read
while we just pass it that file
so let's run it in sublime and it works
and if we run it from the command line
it works as well
now we have a design decision to make here
a key's expression is just a way to conditionally run
code based on pattern matches
and we know a different way to run code conditionally
multi clause functions
so I'm going to copy the version of our
route function that uses case
and I'm going to comment it out
just so we can compare it when we're done here
and then paste it in up above
and then I'm going to comment out this case expression
so let's continue on with our pipeline and express
what we want here
at this point we have a joined absolute path
we want to pipe that into file read
and we know that's going to return a tuple
so then we can turn around and pipe that tuple
into a new function we haven't written yet
I'm going to call it handle file
it's going to take the tuple as the first argument
and we also need to pass in the conversation map
so that's going to be the second argument
and that's going to return an updated conversation map
so we can get rid of this file equal
and that's going to be the
entire function body right there
and then we just need to define this
handle file function
and just to make it a little bit more space
let's just go ahead and get rid of this
because we've got it in the function down below
so it looks like this handle file
we know it takes a topple
and we can pattern match on that
so if it's okay and content
remember there's a second argument
it's the conversation that got passed in right here
so
the first argument gets piped and the second argument
we just pass in co no like that
so if that pattern matches
then what we want to do is return
this updated map
so I think you see where this is going
we can define another handle file function clause
and the pattern we want to match here is this one
and then it takes co and v
and then in that case we were going to return
this updated map
and one more time we've got handle file
that takes this pattern down here
the map
and it should return
this updated map
so we have three
function clauses that use pattern matching
and remember if a function has multiple clauses
while elixir will try
each clause until it finds one that matches
and the first function clause that matches is run
so if we save that away
and give it a go
while we still get our quote as the content of that
file that's being served
so we get the exact same output
as we did when we use the case expression
so which way is better
using case or multi clause functions
well as I mentioned earlier
it's really a design decision and
there's no right or wrong answer
the choice you make
will vary depending on the situation and your
personal preference
in this situation the case is simple enough to read
it has three branches and
one line associated with each branch
now if it had more branches or
multiline expressions for each of those branches
then the readability starts to suffer
and I'd use multi clause functions instead
the only downside
to multi clause functions is that you have to define
separate functions for each branch
but I really like the declarative feel of separate
small functions
with arguments that are pattern matched
it just feels more
congruent with the elixir way of doing things
that being said we're not totally consistent
so try both approaches to develop your own preferences
given the situation
and don't be afraid to change your mind
and change your code